A New Preface from Michael Cox, 2016

A Carr for the Twenty-First Century

For a generation which never really experienced the Cold War, or who came to intellectual maturity long after it had become but a distant memory, it is difficult, if not impossible, to convey what an extraordinary shock it was to nearly all of us to see the certainties of nearly 40 years simply evaporate before our very eyes between 1989 and 1991. Of course, for those who had always preached that there was no rational alternative to the market, the collapse of an old order underpinned as it was by what Ronald Reagan had earlier called an ‘evil empire’ could only be welcomed. Yet others were not so certain. Indeed, one of the more famous doyens of academic International Relations (IR) warned both liberals and triumphalists that the world might soon be missing the Cold War or at least should not be welcoming its passing with such gusto.1 He was right to sound a note of warning. Indeed, when the demise of Soviet power was followed in turn by the tragic collapse of former Yugoslavia, genocide in Rwanda, economic catastrophe in ‘reforming’ Russia itself, a horrifying but successful attack on the USA in 9 September 2001, the Iraq war, the great financial crash of 2008, and then, to cap it all, a revolt in North Africa which began with such high expectations but very soon threatened to destroy the state system in the Middle East, then it was palpably obvious that, that much heralded ‘new world order’ announced back in 1991 by President George H.W. Bush was not about to be realized any time soon.

Meanwhile, the discipline of IR, having first tried to come to terms with the end of a bipolar order it had for decades assumed to be stable, has been struggling ever since to make sense of an international system which in one sense has never been so peaceful—great power war we are told is a thing of the past—but at another so full of so many risks. The world today may be richer, more democratic, more middle class and just a little less scarred by the kinds of poverty once assumed to be normal in the ‘Third World’. Globalization has delivered something as economists constantly remind us. But never has this same world been so unequal, or, its future prospects apparently so uncertain. Indeed, it is difficult to know where to start, with all manner of danger arising—or so we have been warned— from either the long-term decline of the West, a ‘new’ Cold War between Russia and the West, and of course by the apparently irresistible rise of China which according to some pundits at least (including some in China itself) can only end in tragedy.2 Add to this the threat caused by the failure of several states close to Europe and the possible collapse of the European project itself, then it is fairly self-evident why many are now insisting that we are living through seriously dangerous and uncertain times with possibly much worse to come.3

Amidst all this change it is perhaps reassuring that a number of more historically minded scholars have returned to look in a more systematic way at some of the early classics of the discipline. Whether this is because they are finding it impossible to make sense of the real world with all the new theories that have been served up on the academic menu over the past two decades, or simply because they believe that the past (and an older) generation of writers has something to tell us, does not really matter much. The fact of the matter is that since the early 1990s, and amidst all the turmoil, there has been a veritable flood of significant work on some of the founding fathers of IR.4

One of these ‘fathers’ of course is Hans J. Morgenthau. Born into a ‘morbid age’ in which civilization itself seemed to be on the brink of collapse,5 Morgenthau later tried to draw upon his own experiences as a German Jew, an émigré, and a representative of a generation of European thinkers who had experienced fascism first-hand, to help explain the harsh character of the ‘real’ world to an America which he felt had neither the wisdom nor the experience to run the international system effectively. Erudite, ambitious and immensely well connected—a would-be ‘Prince’ to those who wielded power—Morgenthau was IR for a generation of students in the West after the war. Yet influential though he may well have been— even critics still talk of his work as having been ‘path breaking’6—by the time of his death in 1980, his intellectual star had faded amongst an up-and-coming generation who regarded him as something of a pre-theoretical ‘has been’ who had little interest in morality, even less in peace, and whose realism had either led to an uncritical defence of power politics (untrue) to a justification for US expansionism (even less true) or refusing to think about any possible alternative to the existing state system (perhaps the biggest canard of all). Moreover, as realism went out of intellectual fashion following the end of the Cold War, Morgenthau appeared to become little more than an historical footnote in a subject now increasingly shaped by a new wave of scholars who believed that his kind of realism, or indeed any kind of realism, had not only failed to predict the end of the Cold War (sin of all sins) but was steeped in the false enlightenment idea that one could—‘objectively speaking’—know the world scientifically.

Yet the heart of the corpse that was realism never quite stopped beating, and as the first flush of post-Cold War euphoria passed, Morgenthau began to make something of a comeback. In fact, within a fairly short space of time he had become a minor cult figure amongst certain scholars—at least that is how it appeared in terms of the number of articles7 and volumes that now began to flow from the press. Amongst the more interesting of the books at least was an original biography which dealt with his early years,8 another significant work—by a left-wing writer no less—on the progressive character of his realism,9 a study on the Jewish sources of his thought,10 another rather more obscure work on his discussion of Aristotle,11 and an important edited volume which amongst other things tried to show that Morgenthau was a much more complex and interesting figure than the one-sided, almost cartoon-like figure still routinely referred to in even the better of the modern IR textbooks.12 Criticized at different times for being either too wordy, too reductionist, too much focused on power or horror of horrors—too state centric, it would be no exaggeration to say that his reputation today has never been higher.13

In many ways, Ken Waltz needed no such rehabilitation. His two great books on IR (the first being by far and away the more original of the two) virtually defined the subject of IR after Morgenthau.14 As one writer has put it, these two studies alone ‘provided the framework within and against [which] international-relations argued for much of the post-WWII period’.15 Eschewing Morgenthau’s rather long-winded digressions on the history of diplomacy—not to mention his ill-conceived attempt to root the sources of state behaviour in ‘human nature’—Waltz provided something which Morgenthau probably never did: a more systematic theory of international politics with clear causal categories which helped explain why states behaved in the way in which they did and whether or not they were likely to survive in a world where power was always going to be unequally distributed. Conceptually rigorous in his claims, but never claiming that his theory explained everything about the foreign policy of a particular state, his influence was, by any measure, immense. Moreover, with a rare capacity to sometimes think the unthinkable—the Cold War contributed to order he once argued,16 and Iran getting a nuclear weapon may be no bad thing he later insisted17—Waltz was never less than challenging, interesting or influential.

Still, even his version of realism suffered the same critical fate as that of Morgenthau following the end of the Cold War. But again, like Morgenthau, he too has been revisited of late, and not just in the many heartfelt and generous tributes that were (justifiably) heaped upon him following his death in 2013.18 Indeed, only a few years earlier his many virtues were celebrated, and some of his weaknesses criticized, in a conference which referred to Waltz as being ‘The King of Thought’. This was followed, a short while after, with a volume based on the conference (held in Aberystwyth) in which he was described by its British editor as being no more, and no less, than the ‘ indispensable theorist’ of IR.19 A year on and Ken Booth was making equally strong claims. Indeed, in a powerful and effective attack on the pretensions of most IR theories and theorists who had presumed to dismiss writers like Waltz, Ken Booth took a few intellectual prisoners in one of the more powerful modern defences of ‘critical’ realism in general and Waltz’s understanding of international politics in particular.20

If Waltz became mainstream in American IR, the same could hardly be said of E.H. Carr, a Cambridge classicist turned Foreign Office mandarin who went on to write biographies of radical thinkers before taking up a Chair in International Politics at the then University College of Wales, Aberystwyth named after an American president—Woodrow Wilson—whose reputation he then set about trying to destroy! A public intellectual of some influence who made more enemies than friends, and who as one admirer put it, simply could not stop himself taking pot shots at an establishment of which in some ways he was part, Carr always was, and still remains, a difficult writer to pin down.21 Indeed, only a few years after having authored what is now regarded as one of the classics of IR—The Twenty Years’ Crisis no less—he almost seemed to ignore the discipline altogether, even suggesting at one point that he wished he had had nothing to do with launching IR in the first place. Nor did he take any interest in the many ‘great debates’ that marked the history of IR in the post-war period, including, interestingly, those that revolved around his own contribution to the subject. There was work to be done he insisted, and work hard he undoubtedly did on his many volumes devoted to the history of Soviet Russia in its early years. But as for IR, it was to all intents and purposes a field that held very little interest for him right up until his death in 1982.

None of this however made much difference to students and scholars of IR. In fact, while Carr himself was busying himself in the archives trying to make sense of the great struggles that finally culminated with the rise of Stalin, his work in IR continued to be discussed and debated, nowhere more seriously at first than in the USA itself where a generation of post-war realists—including Morgenthau—drew inspiration from his insights.22 Of course, like all realists, Carr suffered in reputation when the Cold War came to an end. If anything, he possibly suffered more because his ‘side’ in the Cold War—the USSR—lost. Yet while his standing in the field of Soviet history declined precipitately, his reputation in IR went from strength to strength—so much so that Carr today can lay claim to at least one full-length biography written by a former student,23 a study of his years as a journalist while at The Times during World War II,24 a couple of edited volumes,25 a new edition of his most significant volume on IR,26 a translation of the same into at least one foreign language,27 and several other articles and book chapters dealing in a largely sympathetic way with his ideas across the range.28 More recently we have even had the rather interesting spectacle of a well-known American realist defending Carr against his would-be British (mis)interpreters.29 Not that Carr had in earlier times been much feted by what passed for British IR in the post-war period. Too important to ignore entirely (though significantly he was not invited to join the British Committee for the Theory of International Politics when it was set up in 1958) Carr was always the outsider, regarded by insiders like Herbert Butterfield, Hedley Bull and Martin Wight as something of a pariah, roundly condemned not only for his foreign policy views before the war, but for having written a book before it which in the view of one writer (a celebrated member of the same Committee) was not merely the product of ‘diseased times’ with little to say about the world more generally and the field of IR more particularly, but according to Bull at least, of having questioned the very idea of international society, an idea ‘with which a new analysis of the problem of IR should now begin’.30

That said, one can still legitimately ask, what does a writer who was a product of what is now fashionably called the “long” twentieth century have to say about the many issues facing the international system today? and more specifically, why has there been a surge of interest in Carr over the past few years? Carr after all seemed to stand on the wrong side of history in that long drawn out contest between actually existing socialism and imperfectly functioning liberal capitalism. Some of his views on German foreign policy in the 1930s look dubious to say the least. His (by no means uncritical) support for the USSR against its western critics now appears decidedly bizarre. And his attachment to old-fashioned historical materialism looks methodologically dubious to a current generation schooled in everything but. Nevertheless, interest in his work has never seemed to be as great.

There are a number of possible answers to this conundrum. One clearly relates to the new ways in which a younger generation of writers has started to look into the real as opposed to the imagined history of IR as an academic discipline.31 When the discipline was much younger there was, naturally enough, not much interest in uncovering its past. Moreover, when people did begin to write about that past as they increasingly did in the USA after the war, it was invariably presented in the form of a ‘great debate’ between an earlier generation of liberal ‘utopians’ who promoted the naïve and potentially dangerous view that the League of Nations and international law could save the world from the scourge of armed conflict and a later generation of realists—Carr most obviously—who preached the virtues of power politics while rejecting the idea that the world system could be managed or its contradictions tamed by passing fine resolutions in Geneva. This utopian way of thinking about the inter-war system (as Carr defined liberal theorists in The Twenty Years’ Crisis) had many problems, but the most crucial—it was reasoned—was that it was bound to lead to illusions, including the illusion that good men and good women could work together across borders to tame the beast that had led to wars in the past and could easily do so again in the future.

This particular reading of the subject has come under massive assault over the past few years.32 As a result what we might call the traditional narrative— in large part based on Carr’s caricature of his liberal opponents’ position in The Twenty Years’ Crisis—has been replaced by a more nuanced and, it should be said, much more convincing account—and one thing appears to have emerged from all this: there was almost certainly no great ‘debate’ between a well-defined bloc of starry-eyed idealists on the one side and hard-nosed realists on the other. In fact, according to modern scholarship, there were several alternative positions in vogue during the inter-war period ranging from those on the left who thought capitalism was the main cause of conflict,33 through to reformist writers who hoped the world could be made safer without fundamental change,34 on to those on the geopolitical right who thought that war was not only inevitable but possibly desirable too. Either way it is simply wrong to think of the discussion about the future of international affairs between the two wars as being between liberal idealists who simply did not grasp how the ‘real world’ operated and all-knowing, wise, yet cynical realists like Carr who did.35

The attempt to rethink the history of IR has also led some writers to look at yet another, equally important issue relating to the nature of realism more generally.36 For earlier writers there was really not much to discuss. Realism it was often thought (quite often by those who failed to read the realists themselves) flowed from an essentialist understanding of an international system whose immutable logic could not be altered, whose structures could not be changed, where power was the only thing that mattered, and whose principal organizing unit—the state— meant that the world was bound to continue along its same competitive path for ever. But as more modern analysts have noted, this not only simplifies the nature of realism. It is basically misleading when it comes to thinking about Carr himself. Indeed, as one writer pointed in a seminal piece, Carr’s analysis neither implied that the world was unchanging (quite the opposite in fact) or that one should not think seriously about how the world might be changed for the better.37 Nor is it accurate to portray realism, as many once did, as being by definition conservative. Take Carr himself. For the greater part of his life he stood on the left. His classic, The Twenty Years’ Crisis, was suffused with Marxist categories. His closest colleague during the Cold War moreover was the Marxist historian Isaac Deutscher.38 And while he published nothing of note on IR after 1945, he did in fact publish fairly regularly in the left-wing journal New Left Review.39 Of course, other realists did not share all of Carr’s enthusiasms. But nor were they the rather drab group of apologists for the powerful they were often portrayed as being by critics. Thus Morgenthau opposed US interventions in the Third World; Waltz was no defender of unalloyed American power either—indeed always warned of the dangers of the USA possessing too much power after the Cold War; and very much later, the bulk of American realists (including Ken Waltz amongst many others) came out against the Iraq War. In fact, a very strong case could be made—and has been in recent work—that far from being an ideology of the powerful, realism might be better understood as a way of criticizing the uses and abuses of power by the powerful.40

This brings us then to another fairly obvious reason why realism more generally, and perhaps Carr’s particular form of it, has been revisited with such gusto of late. This relates to something discussed earlier: namely, the increasingly disturbed character of the modern world. For several years it was fashionable to believe—in fact liberals took it as a given—that the collapse of communism followed in turn by the spread of the market would help resolve most, if not all, of the world’s problems.41 We were even told by certain writers that increased turbulence in an age of globalization where non-state actors were becoming increasingly important rendered not only realism irrelevant, but states too. As we now know, things have not quite turned out that way. Indeed, over the past few years the international system has confronted several rather old-fashioned challenges that liberals and others of a more post-modern persuasion believed had been consigned to that proverbial dustbin of history.42 Some of these it is true have stemmed from major foreign policy errors by the USA itself. But the most significant have arisen either because of a shift in the balance of power which has worked to the disadvantage of the West more generally or because new rising powers like China simply refuse to play by rules laid down by old ones.43 Either way, the power struggle between states goes on and, in many ways, is going on with an increasing intensity that many liberal theorists must find difficult to explain.44 Nor have other theories fared any better. Indeed, those like James Rosenau (a considerable figure in the field to be sure) who had earlier talked of the world having become ‘post-international’45 now look like having been left with nowhere to hide in an international environment where those so-called defunct entities known as states are continuing to compete with great determination to ensure that their position, and not someone else’s, is the one that continues to determine outcomes in an international system where the strong still try to do what they want—though not always successfully to be sure— while the weak, as another critical realist of a fairly radical disposition has pointed out, continue to suffer what they must.46

Of course, the world today is a very different place to the one Carr inhabited.47 Nonetheless, there is at least one major issue that Carr addressed back in the 1930s which continues to have enormous significance for the world today, namely: how to prevent great shifts of power leading to intense competition with the ever present possibility of war as a result. As anybody familiar with Carr’s work knows, his discussion on what he termed ‘peaceful change’, or more precisely of how to ‘effect necessary and desirable changes’ without this leading to, or being brought about through, war, forms a central part of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. In purely policy terms it is in effect the main reason why he wrote the book in the first place, and why he ended up suggesting (controversially) that unless something was done to accommodate Germany, the rising power, then war would, inevitably, follow. His prediction of course turned out to be true. However, his advocacy of a policy of appeasement came under sustained attack at the time and has been used ever since to blacken his reputation. Yet even if his foreign policy seemed to have gotten Hitler and Nazi Germany very badly wrong, his more general argument—that coming to terms with rising powers was at least something worth contemplating if one wished to avoid the bloody alternative—is one that has much contemporary relevance. Indeed, there are many today who have revisited Carr and his notion of ‘peaceful change’ and wondered whether this idea forged in the 1930s when the West confronted a very assertive Germany may not have some relevance today in relation to China. The differences between Germany then and China now are immense, as even the most hard-nosed of American strategists recognizes. Yet there are still lessons to be drawn from the past, and in many ways it was to be the Chinese who initially drew them.48 In fact, their own contribution to the contemporary IR debate borrows heavily from history, and based upon their reading of what happened before when in the twentieth century other great powers rose with ultimately disastrous consequences, they have come to the not-illogical conclusion (though whether they still adhere to this idea today is now contested) that the only way forward for them was by rising ‘peacefully’. Indeed, their own theory of the ‘peaceful rise’ appears to have more than a passing resemblance to debates that happened long ago in Europe—debates in which Carr himself was centrally involved.49

But if Carr had interesting things to say about peaceful change in world politics, he had equally important things to say about the fate of modern Europe and the role of the nation-state after World War II. Much has been written about his views on nationalism and the importance of moving beyond the nation-state in the process of building a new international order. Indeed, as one of the most influential writers on nationalism—Ernest Gellner—readily conceded, his own work borrowed heavily from Carr, most obviously from his important study, Nationalism and After published in 1945.50 But if Carr’s work on nationalism is by now well known,51 his more general observations about post-war Europe have gone largely, although not entirely, unnoticed. But not any longer it would seem; and ever since the appearance of an earlier study on how British policymakers began to rethink Europe after World War II, there has been growing interest in Carr’s much understudied work in this particular area.52 According to this new work, Carr’s views on the ‘new Europe’ after World War II were not just original and possibly prescient too, but also prove that realists, as much as liberal, had and have important things to say about the European project. In fact, according to two of the ‘new’ Carr scholars, Carr’s brand of subtle realism combining both an appreciation of power married to a vision about the continent’s future could easily be used as the starting-point for explaining both the huge steps taken by Europe after 1945 as well as the many problems facing the European project today.53

But as others have also been quick to point out, if Carr’s discussion about one part of Europe after World War II has generated much positive comment, his views about states in the eastern half of the continent have been the subject of very harsh criticism indeed. The problem began early when Carr as a young diplomat became involved in trying to negotiate a way forward for the ‘new’ states of Europe following the collapse of the main European empires after World War I. As he himself openly confessed, the whole experience left him very badly scarred and he came away from the peace conference in Paris with a very deep suspicion of the Wilsonian idea of self-determination in general (another reason for his opposition to the liberals) and the rights of small nations in particular. He was certainly no great fan of Poland or Polish nationalists, and had little sympathy for democratic countries like Czechoslovakia either—which in part helps explain why he felt little moral angst when Germany took over a large swathe of Czechoslovakia (the Sudetenland) in late 1938. The Soviet Union’s entry into the war three years later only strengthened his view that the small nations of East and Central Europe had no future as self-governing countries. Latvia, Estonia and Lithuania were in a particularly vulnerable position. Carr followed developments there with great interest. Initially supportive of their independence just after World War I, within a few years he was already beginning to think of them in the past tense, almost as the by-products of an unfortunate bout of enthusiasm for a liberal principle which had accompanied the making of the peace in 1919. Anyway, large units he opined were economically more rational than smaller ones, small nations standing alone would for ever be a source of instability, and as part of the new USSR—a multi-national entity committed to progressive policies—the rag bag of failed nations that had emerged from the rubble of empire after World War I had a much better chance of experiencing the benefits of modernity than if they tried to stand alone.54

Carr’s apparent indifference to the fate of small states should of necessity alert us to the simple fact that he was no political saint. On the other hand, his more general warning that nationalism as an ideology and self-determination as a principle might not provide an answer to the ‘national question’, let alone form the basis of a just, stable or open international order, is one we ignore at our peril as we move ever deeper into the twenty-first century. Indeed, his tough-minded and far-from-popular views, on this and many other issues, may in large part explain why Carr—warts and all—continues to exercise a continuing fascination for scholars.55 Carr also reminds us of all of something else as well which has effectively been forgotten by most modern academics: that it is just as important (if not more) for intellectuals to engage in public debate about the real world than it is to publish increasingly specialized articles in increasingly specialized (but highly ranked) journals which only academics read. Carr of course had the ‘privilege’ of living through interesting and challenging times which, it has often been observed, frequently tend to produce writers of great originality whose work is then revisited by later generations. Whether our own times will produce another writer precisely like Carr seems unlikely given so much of what he wrote was conditioned by a revolutionary tide that has over the past 25 years has been ebbing fast, a world depression which in spite of the 2008 crash has so far not been repeated, and two global wars from which policymakers worldwide seem to have drawn the obvious lesson of never again. Yet as even the most establishment observers of the world scene have been forced to concede, we are today living in deeply unsettling times where the abnormal has become the new normal and the future an unknown place. Another rather different but equally disturbing ‘twenty years’ crisis’ could be beckoning—we may already be in it—and one can only hope that our own disturbed times is able to produce thinkers like Carr to help us understand the reasons for our current malaise; and how we might then begin to think of realistic but radical solutions to make the world a better place—a place, where to quote Carr, men and women can ‘exercise’ their ‘reason’ so as to ‘understand’ their ‘environment’ better, and having understood it, ‘act’ in order to create the conditions of a more peaceful and just world.56

Michael Cox

London, UK

1.

|   |

John J. Mearsheimer, ‘Why We Will Soon Miss The Cold War’. The Atlantic Monthly, 266(2), 35–50, August 1990.

2.

|   |

See the early warning by John Mearsheimer, ‘China’s Unpeaceful Rise’. Current History, 105, 160–162, April 2006.

3.

|   |

See Ken Booth, Theory of World Security. Cambridge: Cambridge 0University Press, 2007, especially pp. 396–426.

4.

|   |

See Duncan Bell, ‘International Relations: The Dawn of a Historiographical Turn’. British Journal of Politics and International Relations 2001, 3(1), 115–126.

5.

|   |

See Richard Overy, The Morbid Age: Britain and the Crisis of Civilization, 1919–1939. London, Penguin Books, 2010.

6.

|   |

See Robert Kaufman, ‘Morgenthau’s Unrealistic Realism’. Yale Journal of International Affairs, 1(2), 24–38, Spring 2006. http://www.yale.edu/yjia/articles/Vol_1_Iss_2_Spring2006/kaufman217.pdf

7.

|   |

Of the more sophisticated modern attempts to reclaim Morgenthau see Sean Molloy, ‘Truth, Power, Theory: Hans J. Morgenthau ‘s Formulation of Realism’. Diplomacy and Statecraft, 15(1), 1–34, 2004; and William E. Scheuerman, ‘Was Morgenthau a Realist? Revisiting Scientific Man vs Power Politics’, Constellations, 14(4), 506–530, 2007.

8.

|   |

Christian Frei, Hans J. Morgenthau: An Intellectual Biography. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 2001.

9.

|   |

William E. Scheuerman, Hans Morgenthau: Realism and Beyond. Cambridge, Polity Press, 2009.

10.

|   |

M. Benjamin Mollov, Power and Transcendence: Hans J. Morgenthau and the Jewish Experience. Lexington Books, Rowman and Littlefield Publishing Group, 2002.

11.

|   |

Anthony F. Lang ed; Political Theory and International Affairs: Hans J. Morgenthau on Aristotle’s The Politics. London, Praeger, 2004.

12.

|   |

Michael C. Williams ed; Realism Reconsidered: The Legacy of Hans J. Morgenthau in International Relations. Oxford, Oxford University Press, 2007.

13.

|   |

Daniel Levine, ‘Why Hans Morgenthau was not a Critical Realist (and Why Contemporary IR Realists Should Care)’. International Relations, 27(1), 95–118, 2012.

14.

|   |

Ken Waltz, Man, The State and War. Columbia University Press, 1959 and Theory of International Politics, McGraw Hill, 1979.

15.

|   |

Dan Nexon quoted in Outside the Beltway, 16 May 2013.

16.

|   |

Ken Waltz, ‘The Stability of a Bipolar World’. Daedalus, 93(3), 881–903, Summer 1964.

17.

|   |

Kenneth Waltz, ‘Why Iran Should get the Bomb: Nuclear Balancing Would Mean Stability’. Foreign Affairs, July/August 2012.

18.

|   |

See, for instance, J. Dana Stuster, ‘Requiem for a Realist: The Legacy of Kenneth Waltz’. Foreign Affairs, 16 May 2013, and Robert Art and Robert Jervis, ‘Kenneth Waltz and his Legacy’. Foreign Affairs, 22 May 2013.

19.

|   |

See Ken Booth Realism and World Politics. London and New York, Routledge, 2011.

20.

|   |

Ken Booth, ‘Problem Solvers of the World Unite! Waltz and the Critical Project’. Australian Journal of Political Science, 49(3), 558–563, 2014.

21.

|   |

I discuss the extraordinary range of Carr’s interests—no narrow-minded academic specialist he—in my ‘Will the Real E.H. Carr Please stand up?’. International Affairs, 75(3), 643–653, 1999.

22.

|   |

Hans J. Morgenthau, ‘The Political Science of E.H. Carr’. World Politics, 1(1), 127– 134, 1948.

23.

|   |

Jonathan Haslam, Vices of Integrity: E.H. Carr, 1892–1982. London, Verso, 1999.

24.

|   |

Charles Jones, E.H. Carr and International Relations: a Duty To Lie. Cambridge University Press, 1998.

25.

|   |

See Tim Dunne, Michael Cox and Ken Booth eds; The Eighty Years Crisis: International Relations, 1919–1999. Cambridge University Press, 1998, and my E.H. Carr: A Critical Appraisal. Basingstoke, Palgrave, 2000.

26.

|   |

The Twenty Years’ Crisis was reissued after a long absence in 2001. Sales of the book since have soared.

27.

|   |

See Alessandro Campi, ed; Edward H. Carr, Utopia E Realta: Un’Introduzione Allo Studioe Della Politica Internazionale, Rubbetino Editore, 2009.

28.

|   |

Probably the two best starting points here would be Peter Wilson, ‘Radicalism for a Conservative Purpose: the Peculiar Realism of E.H. Carr’. Millennium, 30(1), 123–136, 2001, and Sean Molloy’s, ‘Dialectics and Transformations: Exploring the International Theory of E.H. Carr’. International Journal of Politics, Culture and Society, 16(4), 279–306, 2003.

29.

|   |

John Mearsheimer, ‘E.H. Carr vs Idealism: The Battle Rages On’. International Relations, 19(2), 139–152, 2005.

30.

|   |

Hedley Bull, ‘The Twenty Years Crisis Thirty Years on’. International Journal, 24(4), 638, 1969.

31.

|   |

See Brian C. Schmidt ed; International Relations and the First Great Debate. London and New York, Routledge, 2012.

32.

|   |

See, for example Peter Lamb, ‘E.H. Carr, Norman Angell and Reassessing the Realist-Utopian Debate’. International History Review, 35(5), 1156–1184, 2013.

33.

|   |

On the British left and international affairs in the inter-war period see Peter Wilson’s The International Theory of Leonard Woolf: A Study in Twentieth Century Idealism. London, Palgrave, 2005 and Lucian Ashworth, International Relations Theory and the Labour Party: Intellectuals and Policy Making 1918–1945. London, I. B. Tauris, 2007. See also Peter Lamb, ‘The British Left in the Problems of Peace lectures: 1926–1938: Diversity that E.H. Carr Ignored’. International History Review, 36(3), 530–549, 2014.

34.

|   |

See William H. McNeill’s, Arnold Toynbee: A Life. New York and Oxford, Oxford University, 1989, for a guide to the views of the best known reformist of the inter-war years.

35.

|   |

See David Long and Peter Wilson eds, Thinkers of the Twenty Years’ Crisis: Inter-War idealism Reassessed. Oxford, Clarendon Press, 1995.

36.

|   |

See for example Sean Molloy, The Hidden History of Realism: A Genealogy of Power Politics. New York, Macmillan, 2006.

37.

|   |

Ken Booth, ‘Security in Anarchy: Utopian Realism in Theory and Practice’. International Affairs, 67(3), 527–545, July 1991.

38.

|   |

See my ‘E.H. Carr and Isaac Deutscher: A Very Special Relationship’, in Michael Cox ed; E.H. Carr: A Critical Appraisal. Basingstoke, Palgrave, 2000.

39.

|   |

See for instance E.H. Carr, ‘The USSR and The West’. New Left Review, 11, 25–36, September–October 1978.

40.

|   |

See Muriel Cozette, ‘Reclaiming the Critical Dimension of Realism: Hans J. Morgenthau and the Ethics of Scholarship’. Review of International Studies, 34(1), 5–27, 2008; and Milan Babik, ‘Realism as Critical Theory: The International Thought of E.H. Carr’. International Studies Review, 15(4), 491–514, December 2013.

41.

|   |

See my ‘E.H. Carr and the Crisis of Liberalism’. Millennium, 38(3), 1–11.

42.

|   |

See Pierre Manent, ‘The Crisis of Liberalism’. Journal of Democracy, 25(1), 131–141, January 2014.

43.

|   |

See George Soros, The Crisis of Global Capitalism. New York, 1998.

44.

|   |

For a Marxist perspective on the crisis of modern liberalism see Alex Callinicos, Bonfire of Illusions: The Twin Crises of Liberalism. Cambridge, Polity Press, 2010.

45.

|   |

James Rosenau, Turbulence in World Politics: A Theory of World Politics. New Jersey, Princeton University Press, 1990.

46.

|   |

Yanis Varoufakis, And the Weak Suffer What They Must? London, Bodley Head, 2016.

47.

|   |

As I argue in my ‘The Uses and Abuses of History: the End of the Cold War and Soviet collapse‘. International Politics, 48(4–5), 627–646, 2011.

48.

|   |

Chinese writers have displayed an especially great interest in another realist— Thucydides—and another period of power shift leading as Thucydides believed, ‘inevitably’, to war: Thucydides famously wrote in his History of The Peloponnesian War that “the real cause” of the war and the “one which was formally most kept out of sight” was “the growth of the power of Athens, and the alarm which this inspired in Sparta”. See Mo Shengkai and Chen Yue, ‘The US-China “Thucydides Trap”: A view from Beijing”. The National Interest, July 10, 2016. http://nationalinterest.org/feature/the-us-china-thucydides-trap-view-beijing-16903

49.

|   |

See Barry Buzan and Michael Cox, ‘China and US: Comparable Cases of the ‘Peaceful Rise’. The Chinese Journal of International Politics, 6(2), 109–132, 2013.

50.

|   |

See Ernest Gellner, ‘Nationalism Reconsidered and E.H. Carr’. Review of International Studies, 18(4), 285–293, October 1992.

51.

|   |

See also Konstantinos Kostagiannis, ‘Mind the Gap between Nationalism and International Relations: Power and the nation-state in E.H. Carr’s realism’. International Politics, 50(6), 830–845, 2013.

52.

|   |

See Peter Wilson, ‘The New Europe Debate in Wartime Britain’, in Visions of European Unity, eds; Philomena Murray and Paul Rich. Boulder, CO, Westview Press, 1996, pp. 39–62.

53.

|   |

Konstantinos Kostagiannis and Daniel Kenealy, ‘Realist Visions of the European Union: E.H. Carr and Integration’. Millennium, 41(2), 221–246, 2013.

54.

|   |

See Kaarel Piirimae, Liberals, Nationalism and Small States: E.H. Carr, Walter Lippmann and the Baltic States, 1918–1944. https://www.academia.edu/10009761/L%C3%A4%C3%A4ne_liberaalid_rahvuslus_ja_v%C3%A4ikeriigid._E._H._Carri_ja_Walter_Lippmanni_vaated_Balti_riikidele_1918-1944

55.

|   |

See for instance Kuniyuki Nishimura, ‘E.H. Carr, Dostoevsky and the Problem of Irrationality in Modern Europe’. International Relations, 25(1), 45–64, March 2011; and his ‘The Age of the Lonely Crowd: E.H. Carr and Peter Drucker on the Fragility pf Modern Life’. Global Society, 25(3), 2011. See also Sean Molloy, ‘Spinoza, Carr, and the Ethics of the 20 Years’ Crisis‘. Review of International Studies, 39(2), 251–271, 2013.

56.

|   |

Quoted in E.H. Carr’s What is History?

Introduction

In 1936 Edward Hallett Carr resigned from the Foreign Office where he had worked for the better part of twenty years to take up the position of the Woodrow Wilson Chair in the Department of International Politics at the University College of Wales Aberystwyth. At first sight it was one of the oddest decisions he ever took in an extraordinarily long and very distinguished career. Aberystwyth, after all, was hardly one of the more fashionable universities in the United Kingdom, and West Wales was about as far away as it was possible to be from the centres of political and intellectual power where Carr had hitherto spent nearly all of his life.1 Carr also discovered (just after the interview) that the President of the College – the redoubtable Lord David Davies, whose support for the League of Nations was only equalled by his benevolence in funding the post – was totally opposed to his appointment on the grounds that Carr was both sceptical about the League2 and critical of the liberal principles enunciated by another, rather more important president, after whom the Chair had originally been named.3 The initial signs were hardly encouraging. But, as the philosophical Carr explained in a letter sent to his publisher (the future Prime Minister, Harold Macmillan), the position did have its advantages. As he pointed out, it was the ‘best’ that there was ‘in the country’ and ‘the obligations of residence’ were ‘extremely small’. It would also give him what he could never have had in the Foreign Office: the freedom ‘to write and lecture on foreign affairs’, something he had ‘long wanted to do’.4 This, if nothing else, was the critical attraction of what he later referred to rather puckishly as this ‘fancy chair’ in the people’s College by the sea.5

The unlikely encounter between Carr the cosmopolitan and Aberyst-wyth the university turned out, in fact, to be one of the most productive in academic history. Given the space he craved Carr published not just one book while in the employ of the University of Wales, but no less than seven, a remarkable output even by Carr’s already remarkably productive standards. The first (Carr’s favourite) sank almost without trace, except for that which it left on the anarchist movement.6 The next – a straightforward student text dealing with the international history of the inter-war period – went on to sell well over 70,000 copies.7 It also had the rare privilege of being his only book published in Welsh.8 At least three more, Conditions of Peace, Nationalism and After and The Soviet Impact on the Western World, were all best-sellers too,9 especially the first one, which even the normally modest Carr admitted had been ‘a spectacular success’.10 Unfortunately, the same could not be said about his earlier and more detailed study on British foreign policy. Published in late 1939 it was more or less still-born.11 The same fate did not await his other volume, however, which appeared at about the same time. Conceived in 1937 with an entirely different title to that which finally appeared on the cover (Carr’s preferred option until he was persuaded otherwise was Utopia and Reality) it was in the end published – after detailed negotiations between Carr and his publisher – under the name by which it ultimately became internationally famous: The Twenty Years’ Crisis: 1919–1939. An Introduction to the Study of International Relations.12

The history of The Twenty Years’ Crisis is almost as interesting (and perhaps as significant) as the book itself. As his letters and diaries of the time reveal, Carr never intended to write a popular or even an especially accessible study. As he rather nicely put it in 1938, this particular volume was not one that ‘people’ would ‘want to take to the seaside or the mountains with them’.13 Nor was it ever written with the mass market in mind, but for what Carr liked to regard as that rather nebulous, but all-important body of human beings known as the intelligent reading public. Indeed, in another communication to Macmillan just after the book was published, he worried that with the onset of the war and the call-up, those for whom the book had originally been intended would not be around to read it.14 He was equally concerned that the new title which he had only agreed with Macmillan a month or so before publication, did not accurately reflect what was in the book itself. A ‘fancy title’ would be inappropriate, he agreed.15 On the other hand, the book was not a ‘bigger and better history of post-war international relations’ (which was implied by The Twenty Years’ Crisis) but rather ‘about international relations in general’16 and while he conceded (reluctantly) that Utopia and Reality might be too ‘abstract’, he was always anxious that the final alternative did not give a clear enough indication of what was actually in the volume itself. In terms of sales at least he need not have worried. Under its new and more popular heading, it sold extremely well and was widely reviewed, a fact that pleased the cautious but quietly confident Carr no end.17 The book, he was happy to report to his College back in Wales in 1943, had achieved ‘substantial success’.18 This not only prompted Macmillan to bring out a new second edition in 1946, but also led to its speedy translation into two foreign languages, to be followed by several more in the years which followed.19 Whether Carr had intended it or not, The Twenty Years’ Crisis had become an academic best-seller.

What Carr could never have anticipated, of course, was the book’s subsequent influence and minor cult-like status within the new academic discipline of international relations, a subject for which he appeared to have very little enthusiasm at all. Indeed, one of the many ironies of The Twenty Years’ Crisis is that its author not only demonstrated little interest in its subsequent fate, but showed even less in the discipline which now claimed the book as one of its classical texts. Clearly this had something to do with his post-war preoccupation; writing a massive history of early Soviet Russia. Yet, as the record shows, his indifference was not just because he had changed academic trains. He also had grave doubts about the subject itself. As he explained in 1971 to an American admirer, he had ‘long thought that International Relations’ was a ‘rag-bag’ into which one was ‘entitled to put anything one pleases’, and that the various attempts to ‘turn it into some sort of organzied self-contained subject’ had ended in ‘fiasco’.20 A few years later and he was saying much the same to another American, the distinguished American academic Stanley Hoffman. If anything he was more hostile, and even attacked his own role in having inadvertently helped establish the subject. ‘Whatever my share in starting this business’ (this ‘business’ being international relations), ‘I do not know that I am particularly proud of it’. Anyway, he asked, what is this thing called international relations in the ‘English speaking countries’ other than the ‘study’ about how ‘to run the world from positions of strength’? In other places, at other times, it might be something else, but within those states which had the influence – as opposed to those that did not – it was little more than a rationalization for the exercise of power by the dominant nations over the weak. There was no ‘science of international relations’ he went on. The subject so-called was an ideology of control masking as a proper academic discipline.21

Carr’s hostility to international relations could not, however, alter the course of academic history, and whether he liked it or not, his apparently unloved child, The Twenty Years’ Crisis, went on to play a quite crucial role in both launching the subject and influencing the way in which generations of students were taught to think about its history. For in spite of what Carr may have intended when he wrote the book, those who came to read it later – and in particular during the dark, dangerous days of the Cold War – came to regard it as a classic ‘realist’ text which condemned any talk of ethics or morals and saw all international politics as a simple struggle for power between competitive states in an unchanging international system.22 This one-sided reading of what was a much more nuanced text, subtly but effectively transformed The Twenty Years’ Crisis from what Carr had originally set out to do – which was to debunk the pretensions of liberalism while providing a way out of the impasse that was the inter-war crisis – and make it into something rather conservative and simple. The Twenty Years’ Crisis was not exactly turned into its opposite. On the other hand, it was stripped bare of any critical edge. This did not necessarily make it the least understood book in the history of international relations. But it definitely came close. Certainly, it was never read with any great care, particularly by those who seemed more intent on legitimizing a particular way of thinking about the world rather than studying what Carr actually said.

However, before going on to look at the very peculiar fate that awaited The Twenty Years’ Crisis, it would be useful first to return to Carr’s original decision to leave the relative security of the Foreign Office to take up that position in that distant university department. We do not do so out of a deference to history – though the history itself is not without its own fascination – but to understand why it was that Carr needed the freedom he so obviously craved to speak out on the major issues of the day. Indeed, only by examining the background to that otherwise odd decision (at least one of his colleagues took it for granted that he had been offered a Chair in Oxford23) can we really begin to understand why he decided to write The Twenty Years’ Crisis in the first place. Books after all do not appear out of thin air, and this particularly influential book, which took him the best part of two years to write, can only be understood if we enter into Carr’s world, a world that stood in ruins long before he took the critical decision to depart the Foreign Office and write the study which finally established his reputation as a major thinker of the first order.

E. H. Carr: the unmaking of a liberal

Our story begins not with Carr the newly created professor (a term by the way that he heartily disliked) but Carr the committed liberal whose early world was marked by certainty and security – ‘security not only in family relations but in a sense of scarcely imaginable today’ he later wrote. As he himself confessed, he grew up in an entirely sheltered environment of public school, Cambridge and the Foreign Office; in a place and time that was ‘solid and stable’, where prices remained the same, where everybody knew their station in life, in which things only changed slowly, and then only for the ‘better’. Even the shock of the First World War and the Bolshevik revolution did little to disturb this equilibrium. The war was a tragedy that destroyed the lives of millions, but, as he recalled, few people at the time ‘thought of it as the end of an epoch’. Instead they regarded it, or at least he did, as some ‘unpredictable natural calamity’ that once over and the damage repaired would leave things more or less as they were before. The same seemed to be true of the Russian revolution. Carr was not foolish enough to think that the new regime would collapse at the very first hint of opposition and resistance, the standard view after 1917. But he never felt that this utopian experiment with what he felt were its unrealizable goals of creating a classless society,24 and spreading proletarian international revolution,25 would ever amount to very much. No doubt for this reason, although there were others, he did not so much fear the Bolsheviks during the first decade of their rule as feel indifferent to them. As he admitted, until the late 1920s and early 1930s he did ‘not give much thought’ to what was happening in the USSR. It was, to paraphrase a term used about another country at another time, a faraway place about which he knew something including the language but did not care a great deal.26

The first seeds of doubt were sown with the Versailles Peace Treaty in 1919, a key historical event which he attended and in which he played a minor role, primarily dealing with the question of minorities in Central Europe.27 The big question, however, was what to do with Germany. Carr was by no means na tve There were critical issues that had to be addressed. Nevertheless, these could not be dealt with seriously, and over the long term by punishing the whole nation, and then treating it as a permanent pariah. If nothing else, this made little sense economically, a view he shared with John Maynard Keynes from whom he derived most of his thoughts about the disastrous ‘economic consequences of the peace’. It was also bound to store up major problems for the future. Moreover, it was unjust, a common opinion amongst a generation of British intellectuals at the time, including Carr himself who battled long and hard within the Foreign Office to get his position accepted. In the end he failed and, as we now know, felt compelled to resign in order to be able to speak out in public. Nor did his views on the subject change much thereafter, in spite of what happened in 1939 and the failure of appeasement as a policy. As a close confidante remarked many years after his death, Carr never had any real sympathy for Hitler. Nonetheless, he always thought Versailles to have been little short of disastrous and a major factor in both bringing Hitler to power in 1933 and causing the war a few years later.28

If the harsh treatment meted out to Germany in 1919 was one of the reasons for Carr’s growing disillusionment, the entry of the United States onto the world’s diplomatic stage at Versailles was undoubtedly another. Carr was not especially anti-American.29 However, he was anti-Woodrow Wilson, and it was his critical engagement with this particular President’s brand of crusading politics that raised serious doubts in his own mind about both liberalism as a doctrine and Wilsonianism as a guide to international politics. His hostility to Wilson in particular (which David Davies could never quite forgive)30 derived from two main sources: a disdain for Wilson’s high-sounding moral rhetoric, which Carr regarded as little more than an idealistic fig-leaf masking America’s ambition of extending its own influence at the expense of others; and a more principled opposition to Wilson’s use of the slogan of the right of national self-determination. Carr was no lover of empires as such. On the other hand, he could detect nothing particularly progressive arising from their collapse in Eastern Europe. Furthermore, as he repeatedly pointed out, the proliferation of a host of small European states in the inter-war period could only add to an already highly unstable international situation. No great fan of small states at the best of times, he soon came to believe that one of the additional reasons for the crisis between the wars was the highly irresponsible way in which the liberal ideal of national self-determination had been applied in 1919. As he noted ‘national self-determination was a principle’ that not only had ‘awkward implications for bourgeois democracy’ but for ‘international concord’ as well.31 Potentially progressive in its consequences at an earlier period in time, its results could only be destructive and reactionary after the First World War, turning it from a source of potential liberation from oppression in one age, to what Carr termed the ‘world’s bane’ in another.32

Carr’s faith in liberalism, however, received its greatest blow from the collapse of the world economy after 1929. In this he was by no means unique but representative of what happened to a whole generation. Yet, once detached from his moorings there seemed to be no going back. ‘England’ and the world along with it ‘was adrift’, he wrote in 1930, and unless a new ‘faith’ could be found there was little hope for the future.33 He found his faith, of course, in social reform and economic planning, as he made clear to an audience at Chatham House a decade later. There could be no return to an economic order that had so obviously failed. What was now needed, he continued, was not some tinkering with the international superstructure (the basic weakness of such schemes as the League of Nations), but a social revolution from below that would attack the underlying source of the current disorder: namely, the unregulated and unplanned character of a liberal economy which presupposed that the hidden hand of the market would invariably lead to the greatest economic good always being achieved for the greatest number. Such an outlook may have made perfect sense in the nineteenth century in a period of expansion: it made none whatsoever in an era of capitalist decline.34 As he explained in a later memo, private enterprise in the past had not just rested on a number of economic assumptions but a set of ‘moral principles’ as well. Now all that had changed, leaving the system that had once ‘enjoyed general assent’ standing indicted before the bar of history.35 The task, therefore, was clear: to find an alternative, or what Carr termed a ‘new society based on new social and economic foundations’ whose first objective would be to promote full employment, equality and social justice. Without such a programme of radical change, the world in general, and Britain in particular, would continue to drift.36

If the trauma of the Depression disturbed Carr, what unsettled him even more was the contrast between what he now saw happening in the West and what he began to see taking place in the Soviet Union. No great supporter of the regime in its earlier, more revolutionary days, the coincidence of the capitalist crisis and the apparent successes being enjoyed by the Five Year Plans after 1929 compelled him to rethink his views.37 This in part was facilitated by his growing love affair with Russian culture more generally.38 Indeed, it was his work on such nineteenth-century figures as Dostoevsky, Herzen and Bakunin (alienated intellectuals who lived ‘outside’ of what Carr called ‘the charmed circle’) that initially led him to think more critically about what he called ‘western ideology’.39 But this was only a precipitating factor. More important by far was what was happening within the USSR itself as it moved from the relative quiet of the 1920s to the hectic drive for modernization that characterized the 1930s. Carr never became an apologist for Stalin or the Soviet Union. On one particularly famous occasion he was even moved to observe that Germany under Hitler ‘was almost a free country’ by comparison with its totalitarian counterpart to the East. But he always retained what he liked to think of as balance, and consequently felt that in spite of everything it was still important to recognize the advances that were being made at the economic level.40 This did not make the USSR a socialist society. Neither did it make it a natural ally of the West. But one could not close one’s eyes to what was going on, and no amount of theoretical criticism from classical liberal economists like von Mises or Hayek could alter the fact that under conditions of planning things were being successfully undertaken that were not being done in the West – and the West could only ignore all this at its peril.41

Finally, as an increasingly unsettled intellectual, Carr was bound to be influenced by new ideas, and as one set of truths collapsed he logically began to look around for another with which to make sense of a world in crisis. Not surprisingly, in the context of the 1930s, this led him to engage more seriously with Marx and Marxism. The outcome was a complex amalgam that managed to combine his own elitist scepticism about socialism and doubts about many aspects of Marxism (including the labour theory of value and the notion of class struggle) with something that could loosely be described as being radical and materialistic without ever being properly defined as Marxist itself. It was by no means a straightforward or happy marriage, as his own rather odd biography of Marx demonstrated.42 Yet even this study demonstrated his respect for Marx as a social scientist and theorist of capitalist crisis.43 Carr was equally impressed by certain writers who had been influenced by Marx without necessarily being Marxist themselves, especially the sociologist Karl Mannheim and the radical theologian Reinhold Niebuhr.44 There is no doubt that Carr studied both in depth, and the two together obviously exerted what Carr later agreed was the ‘strongest influence’ possible ‘upon his thinking’.45 Perhaps for this reason, amongst others, he confessed that although his 1939 study was ‘not exactly a Marxist work’, it was nonetheless ‘strongly impregnated with Marxist ways of thinking, applied to international affairs’.46

Constructing a classic: The Twenty Years’ Crisis

The world that Carr had known therefore was in turmoil and in many ways The Twenty Years’ Crisis gave expression to this. As someone later remarked, while Carr’s classic might have had some important things to say about international relations in general, it was very much marked by the ‘diseased situation’ during which it was been conceived.47 Certainly, Carr’s analysis of why there was a crisis was never entirely consistent.48 At times he seemed to lay most of the blame on liberalism itself, at others on the quality of western diplomacy, occasionally on the selfishness of what he called the ‘have powers’ and their refusal to contemplate any change in the status quo, sometimes on the economic collapse of the 1930s, and by implication on the fundamental contradiction of maintaining any form of equilibrium in an international system composed of nation-states. As such The Twenty Years’ Crisis combined both sharp analysis and acid condemnation in equal measure, which not surprisingly made Carr more than a few enemies. The volume also represented a very special kind of intervention into the foreign policy debates of the day in which Carr had already been closely involved while in the Foreign Office. Carr, to be fair, never sought to hide his views nor apologize for the fact that he favoured some form of détente with Germany. However, he did not do so for the normal conservative anti-Soviet reasons that favoured Germany as the best bulwark against communism, but because he felt that there was really no serious alternative. As a declining power Britain, he believed, faced one of two imperfect choices in an imperfect world: either to oppose any alteration within the European status quo and thus run the risk of war with a potentially superior enemy at a time when neither the United States nor the USSR could be counted upon,49 or to accept the necessity and inevitability of some measured change, and having come to that conclusion, seriously engage with Germany in order to bring it about by peaceful means. The tragedy was that it did neither. The result was disastrous. Unwilling or unable to fight a war or even prepare for one, Britain was compelled to retreat and by so doing fed the dangerous illusion in Germany that it could continue to expand with impunity. By then failing to accept that the status quo was in need of adjustment, and that Germany did in fact have legitimate grievances, British policy-makers only managed to annoy the Germans and exacerbate rather than improve relations between the two countries.50

Carr’s immediate reason for writing The Twenty Years’ Crisis, therefore, was a most practical one. But he also saw himself engaged in something far more important than a mere defence of appeasement (the underlying purpose of the chapter on ‘peaceful change’) or in attacking an increasingly redundant liberalism and certain liberal writers whose only function it seemed was to provide him with a steady supply of ready-made targets which he could then shoot down at regular intervals. His aim, essentially, was to write a more philosophical work that reflected on the nature of knowledge itself and the relationship between different types of knowledge on the one hand, and history and the production of ideas on the other. This is why his original title for the book – Utopia and Reality – was so significant. He was adamant. He was not attempting to publish a more detailed or higher level version of his already popular international history published in 1937. Nor was he interested in writing something on British foreign policy and its failures. What he was seeking to do was something else: to explore the interplay between the world as understood by those whom he defined in a fairly loose sense as ‘utopians’ – a miscellaneous group whose only uniting feature was a desire to project their own thoughts about the world on to the world itself – and those whom he called ‘realists’, whose chief defining characteristic was an empirical approach to the world as it was. According to Carr, utopianism and realism not only represented ‘two methods of approach’ but also determined ‘opposite attitudes towards every political problem’. Thus the utopian, he asserted, was voluntarist, the realist determinist. The utopian made political theory a norm to which political practice ought to conform, the realist regarded political theory as a sort of codification of political practice. Utopianism attracted intellectuals, realism the bureaucrat. The utopian believed in reason, the realist in force. Utopianism was a trait normally (but not always) associated with the radical, realism with the conservative. Finally, and most fundamental of all, the antithesis of utopia and reality was rooted in a different conception of the relationship of politics and ethics. Hence, the utopian would set up an ethical standard which purported to be independent of politics and sought to make politics conform to it. The realist insisted that morality was a function of politics. In fact, whereas the utopian assumed that there was a general morality and a universal standard by which we could judge what was either right and good, the realist believed that there were no absolute standards save that of fact, and that morality therefore could only be relative and not universal. Viewed from this perspective the search for ethical standards outside of time and place was itself utopian and was thus doomed to frustration.

Why Carr began a book on international relations in this particular way is not at first sight obvious. Nor is it clear initially why he spent the time he did discussing something of which he was so critical as utopianism. Yet as the study proceeds along its extraordinarily erudite way,51 the reason for opening with a rather abstract discussion about one particular way of viewing the world starts to make more sense. As Carr suggests in the early stage of The Twenty Years’ Crisis (and as he made clear when he was writing the book), this particular volume was going to be a discussion of what he called ‘fundamental trends in international politics’ and not some ‘topical’ work simply dealing with the current situation.52 It was thus necessary to start not with the immediate crisis but with what he hoped would be a more profound assessment of its underlying causes, one central part of which in his view was the failure of both intellectuals and policymakers alike to understand the world around them. The question was, why? It was at this point that he turned to the issue of utopianism and the unfortunate influence which he felt it had exerted on the new science of international relations in the period immediately after the First World War.

According to Carr, international relations in its early incarnation bore the birthmark associated with its ethical origins. This was quite understandable. After all, the war had been a human catastrophe and it was not surprising that those involved in international politics hoped to avoid another war by promoting peace and the institutions associated with peace, especially that most moral of institutions with which the subject in its initial manifestation was to become so inextricably entangled, the League of Nations. But the problem with this approach was obvious: it substituted prescription for analysis while doing little to help explain the causes of peace, or why certain states, and not others, acted in a manner deemed to be aggressive. It also led to an almost complete disregard for power and the role played by power in international affairs. Assuming as they did that there was an international community, and that reason rather than material and military capabilities governed the actions of states, the utopians floundered around in a world of ‘make believe’ made up of firm resolutions passed by the League of Nations against war but very little else. This made very little difference in the 1920s, when the world was still relatively orderly. It made a great deal, however, after the critical year of 1931 when Japan invaded Manchuria, followed two years later by the rise of Hitler. Now, tired old legalistic slogans about peace and obedience to international law sounded like so much hot air as the revisionist states began to challenge the status quo favoured, not surprisingly, by the remaining democracies in Europe and the European colonial powers in Asia.53

Carr’s opening move therefore made it possible for him to develop what he hoped would be a theoretically more persuasive analysis of the crisis by showing the extent to which it was being determined by the changing distribution of power in the international system. What it also permitted him to do was draw what seemed on the surface to be a very sharp distinction between one approach, which he saw as being flawed, and another which he did not. But this distinction turned out to be more apparent than real.54 Hence, while Carr at the beginning painted a rather black and white picture of two modes of thinking, placing himself not surprisingly in the intellectually superior realist category, as his discussion moved forward this early picture of hostile camps composed of aspirational utopians on the one side and cynical realists on the other, began to give way to something rather more subtle and blurred. In fact, as the book more generally wended its complicated way from early thoughts about the new science of international relations to complex assessments about the role of power and morality, all that originally seemed fixed and well-defined began to assume a rather different shape and form.

The first complication was introduced by Carr himself. Having set up his ideal types he then sought to muddy the waters by implying that these twin poles were not opposites at all, but merely two sides of the same intellectual coin. Indeed, as his analysis unfolds, it becomes increasingly clear that Carr neither favours realism in its pure form nor even thinks that such a thing is possible or even desirable.55 Hence, while he accepts that realism is a necessary corrective to what he calls the exuberance of utopianism, realism without purpose, he argues, is nothing more than ‘the thought of old age’. Then, as if to make the point clearer than the truth, he devotes a whole chapter to exploring the limits of realism, and while we are left in little doubt where Carr’s intellectual sympathies still lie, he is quite clear in his own mind that realism alone cannot provide a complete basis for effective political thinking. In the end, it is only by drawing upon the visionary aspects of utopianism and the analytical tough-mindedness of realism, that one will be able to develop what Carr refers to as ‘sound political thought and a sound political life’.

But this in turn raises a much larger question: what precisely did Carr actually understand by realism? The answer is by no means obvious. For having at one point implied that ‘realism’ was more likely to appeal to the conservative rather than the radical, he then cited a whole list of modern realists who were not conservative at all. This included a number of German thinkers, including Hegel – from whom he drew much intellectual inspiration – Marx and Engels, whom he cited on several occasions, and Lenin, whom he quoted favourably at a number of points. This was hardly the most obvious combination of well-known conservative thinkers. But then Carr did not see modern realism as being an especially conservative methodology. On the contrary, it was in his view a ‘progressive’, even subversive outlook that understood all phenomena not as the expression of some general essence standing outside of time but as something historically specific. As Carr observed in a famous section of the book entitled the ‘relativity of thought’, the supreme virtue of realism was that it allowed the realist to demonstrate that the intellectual theories and ethical principles of one age were all historically conditioned. It also allowed the contemporary realist like Carr to expose the fact – which was critical in terms of his attack on the utopians – that the various ideas of any individual or particular group like the utopians (such as peace and law and order) were not just neutral notions, but rather the expressions of specific interests; and the most urgent task of realism, he went on, was ‘to bring down the whole cardboard structure of utopian thought by exposing the hollowness of the material’ out of which it was built. Only when this had been accomplished, could we begin the task of finding a way out of the current impasse in which the world now found itself.

If Carr had a particular understanding of realism he had an almost unique notion of what constituted utopianism. For in The Twenty Years’ Crisis he did not employ it to refer to those who contemplated the possibility of an alternative society somewhere, at some point, in the future. Instead, the utopians of whom he spoke had no vision about the future at all, but rather hung on to an outmoded set of liberal ideals whose principal claim, according to Carr, was that there existed a basic ‘harmony of interests’ which tried to turn competitive states into members of the same international community. This, he believed, was a simple denial of the basic facts of life in the real world. It was also politically disingenuous. After all, if there was such a ‘harmony’ then clearly those who questioned it were by definition trouble-makers, while those who defended it were by implication the peace-makers. But then what was this ideology of ‘harmony’ other than an ideology justifying a status quo, founded upon a vast inequality of power between the different states? Furthermore, as he pointed out, the utopians so-called did not protest too loudly when the victorious powers imposed their own very harsh peace on the defeated in 1919. However, they made an enormous amount of noise when the ‘have-not’ powers began to strike back a few years later. This not only smacked of gross hypocrisy, it was also very dangerous for it led to an uncritical support of a situation that was neither defensible not legitimate. Some means would have to be found therefore to permit significant reform to the international system. If not, there could only be one outcome – and that outcome would be war.

The issue of reform then led Carr to look at the problem of ‘peaceful change’. He opened his analysis with a discussion of law, treaties and the judicial settlement of international disputes. Given his own outlook, it was hardly surprising that he dealt with each in a way that was least likely to please those who talked rather too easily in his view about the rule of law, the sanctity of treaties, and about the imperative need to resolve international disputes through the various bodies set up under the terms of the League of Nations. Not only did fine words and worthy bodies do little to resolve the outstanding issues; they actually made them worse by fostering the illusion that deep problems could be solved through an appeal to something which did not exist – that is, an international community composed of a society of states who all shared the same goals. This was a chimera and would do nothing to address the underlying causes of conflict which were rooted in the unequal distribution of power. Nor in some ways should one try to arbitrate, for the purpose of arbitration through law was not to change things, but to keep them the way they were. Thus what was required was not some recourse to supranational bodies or courts which had neither the legitimacy nor the power to enforce their decisions, but an honest recognition of the supremacy of politics. Indeed, only by recognizing that all conflicts were ultimately about politics and about the fundamental problem of who gets what, where and when, could one even begin to tackle the problems of the day.

From this assumption Carr drew two important conclusions. The first was that change was both natural and necessary: the task therefore was to ensure that it occured peacefully rather than violently. The second was an acceptance that all change in the end was a function of power rather than morality, and that it was pointless and dangerous standing against the tide of history if the conditions of power determined it. This is why it was essential to concede (up to a point) to the rising power that was Germany. Yet even short-term concessions would not begin to answer the biggest question of all: namely, what sort of international order was required to achieve genuine security over the longer term? Here Carr looked back in order to look forward, and the picture he painted of the future went much further than that ever contemplated by his more utopian enemies.56 Two reforms of the most basic character were required, he believed – one that would have to tackle the problem of the nation-state, and the other the structure of the international economy. The two issues were intimately connected. Hence if the new world was to be a more peaceful place then it was essential to develop an entirely different approach to economics, and if it was to be more prosperous then it could only become so if people were prepared to rethink the notion of sovereignty, and perhaps, in time, the idea of the nation itself. One thing was clear, however. Liberal schemes with their conceptions of a world federation or blueprints of a more perfect League of Nations would not suffice. These neither attacked the deeper sources of the disorder nor provided any serious solution to the dilemmas facing humanity on the eve of the Second World War. When, and only when policy-makers looked beyond these elegant superstructural answers and began digging in the foundations of the international system, could there be serious historical progress. But, as Carr concluded, this remedy, though utopian at one level, was profoundly realistic at another, for instead of being imposed on history, it grew out of existing historical trends. This is what made his vision of a ‘new international order’ as opposed to that which had been proposed in 1919, a real possibility.

Liberal critics: Carr’s response

As Carr anticipated, the appearance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis set off a lively and, in some cases, an increasingly bitter discussion amongst those against whom the book had been aimed. It might have helped his case if he had completed his project just a little earlier, but by the time it appeared Britain was at war, and part of his argument about the need to come to terms with Germany had been rendered obsolete by the march of events. Carr, typically, accepted the judgement passed by history – the ‘world’s only reliable court’ he once observed, quoting Hegel – and within weeks had thrown himself into the war effort, no doubt tinged by some regret that the peaceful change he had argued for had finally given way to a conflict he had hoped might be avoided. Whether he was quite so shocked by what happened as he later seemed to imply was not so clear at the time.57 In many respects, he had already come to the unpalatable conclusion that there was no possibility of accommodating Germany. He made the point abundantly clear in fact in his other book published at about the same time. Begun in late 1938 and completed by the end of June 1939, this hard-hitting study pulled very few punches in its defence of appeasement. Carr even spared more than a few positive words for the much criticized Neville Chamberlain whose policy of ‘realism’ he believed was preferable to the wavering course which had been pursued by his predecessors. Yet Carr was never a blind enthusiast, and by March and April 1939 he realized that the game was up. War was now inevitable, more or less, and the nation had to prepare for the long struggle that lay ahead fought on the traditional British principle of preventing what even the normally diplomatic Carr defined as the ‘brutal domination’ of the continent by a ‘single overwhelming Power’.58 The pity, according to Carr, was that having accepted the logic of their own situation by early 1939, British policy-makers did not then do more to secure the one alliance that might have made the war less likely or at least less costly: that which he was now advocating with Stalin’s Russia.59

These events, and Carr’s speedy return to London to work initially for the Ministry of Information, and then as Assistant Editor for The Times, did not prevent him from keeping an eye on the fate of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Too much effort had gone into the book for it now to be ignored. Certainly, it did not lack for admirers. The reviewer in the Times Literary Supplement, for instance, accepted that even though it was a highly ‘provocative’ volume, there was no doubting that it was a ‘profound’ work whose author should be praised for his ‘fresh and fearless thinking’. Writing under an assumed name, the up and coming Labour politician, Richard Crossman, was equally impressed. Carr’s analysis of the utopians, in particular, was a ‘brilliant success’ and exposed the ‘enervating impact’ which their ideas had had upon the victorious Powers who, instead of using their power in defence of the status quo or for the accomplishment of peaceful change, had engaged in what Crossman called ‘unilateral psychological disarmament’. The American historian, William Maddox, was even more fulsome in his praise. The Twenty Years’ Crisis, he opined, was nothing less than a ‘monument to the human power of sane and detached analysis’ that provided a discussion of the ‘collapse of the international system’ that was entirely ‘devoid of national bias’; there was little question in his mind at least that ‘Professor Carr’ had ‘produced one of the most significant contributions to the systematic study of the theory of international politics’ that he had ‘seen in years’. Another American reviewer agreed and conceded that this ‘professor of international politics’ from Aberystwyth in Wales had written a ‘very forthright’ study. Americans would be especially interested, he thought, in Carr’s tough assessment of Woodrow Wilson, and while careful not to endorse Carr’s critique completely, he hinted strongly that the discerning would find his ‘withering criticism’ of the crusading President particularly ‘stimulating’. The noted sociologist and future theorist of revolutions, Crane Brinton, was equally impressed, though he went on to warn the many US readers of the popular Saturday Review that ‘when British academic liberals’ (by whom he meant Carr) ‘begin to go hardboiled, we are entitled to think that something is about to happen’.60

Carr was more than a little gratified by these initial comments and like any normal author hoped that these favourable reviews would have a positive impact on sales.61 Not that he had very much time himself to reflect on these things. The war had changed everything and the principal task now he felt was not to look back on a crisis that had finally been resolved, but to work out the most effective ways possible of integrating British war aims with its plans for the peace. On one issue, however, he was insistent: that it was necessary to learn the lessons of the past and abandon any faith in those various grand plans that had come to nothing after the First World War. It was also critical that the war should not just be fought on a moral platform alone with the simple ‘negative’ aim of destroying ‘Hitlerism’. This would neither mobilize the people nor provide them with a vision for the future. If the war was to be fought at all – and fought successfully – it would have to be conducted in the form of what Carr called a ‘social war’ against privilege and inequality. Politically this was critical. It was also essential if the Allies wanted to ‘stir up discontent in the conquered countries against the Nazi yoke’; and they were ‘much more likely to’ achieve this ‘by holding out the prospect of bread and butter than by promises of freedom and self-determination’.62

While Carr reflected on the future, his many critics contemplated their next move. One such was the Director of Studies at Chatham House, Arnold Toynbee, one of Carr’s main targets.63 Toynbee fully accepted the power of Carr’s polemic against good liberals like himself. But, he wondered, had not this ‘consummate debunker’ been thoroughly ‘debunked by the war itself’? Moreover, no amount of clever intellectual footwork from the admittedly brilliant author of this ‘very important contribution to the study of recent international affairs’ could disguise the fact that there was a profound ‘moral vacuum’ at the heart of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Criticism was all very well, but unless it led ‘to a clearer view of what’ was ‘morally right and morally wrong’ it would in the end lead nowhere. This particular theme was taken up and developed by yet another of Carr’s known political enemies, Alfred Zimmern, the first holder of the Woodrow Wilson Chair and now Montagu Burton Professor of International Relations at Oxford. He too was disturbed by Carr’s lack of moral compass. Carr was a ‘thorough-going relativist’, he concluded, who had no way of knowing, or even judging, what was good or bad, right or wrong or plain indifferent. And if there were no such objective standards, he asked, then how could anybody, including Carr, arrive at any reasoned judgement about the world?

One of Carr’s many other targets, the well-known liberal theorist, Norman Angell, was even more outraged. The Twenty Years’ Crisis, he felt, was as ‘completely mischievous a piece of sophisticated moral nihilism’ as he had ever read. Angell agreed that Carr had forced his opponents (including himself) ‘to take stock’. But what was one supposed to make of a book which assumed that law, order, and peace were not general interests but simply the particular interests of the rich and the powerful? Ultimately, all that Carr had done, and presumably done quite consciously, was to provide ‘aid and comfort in about equal degree’ to the followers of Karl Marx and Adolf Hitler. The Fabian critic, Leonard Woolf, was equally incensed, but expressed himself in a slightly less intemperate way. However, instead of attacking Carr where others had already attacked him before (on the twin issues of relativism and morality) he decided to interrogate what he regarded as Carr’s misuse of the concept of utopianism. In Woolf’s view Carr never employed the term with any great degree of consistency. Nor did he once think that the same criticism that he had levelled against others might also be levelled against him. Yet if it was legitimate to label as ‘utopian’ all those who had supported the League, then was it not equally reasonable to attack Chamberlain for being a utopian as well? After all, his policy of appeasement was no more successful at stopping the slide towards war than the League but Carr never lambasted him with the same degree of fervour that he had reserved for his liberal opponents. This not only smacked of hypocrisy but pointed to a basic flaw in Carr’s logic, one that he could never admit to of course, because in the end he was guilty of the same inconsistency himself.64

Faced with such a barrage of criticism Carr did not respond directly. To that extent there was no great debate between Carr the ‘realist’ and his ‘idealist’ critics.65 What he did do, was to write yet another book, and while it did not represent a ‘reply’ in any formal sense, it was obvious that part of the reason for publishing Conditions of Peace in 1942 was because he had been stung by the various attacks launched by critics. Carr indeed admitted as much a few years later. As he put it, he began to feel ‘a little ashamed of the harsh realism of The 20 Years’ Crisis’, and so decided ‘to write’ what he called ‘the highly utopian Conditions of Peace’. Admittedly, it was not one of Carr’s more profound studies (he wrote it just under a year). On the other hand, it was by no means as ‘feeble’ as he claimed.66 Nor was the intellectual distance between it and his previous book as great as one of his reviewers seemed to suggest.67 It addressed the same broad issue: the crisis of the old order. It was equally negative in its evaluation of liberalism. It was vituperative against Wilson. And it did at least try to explain why the ‘dissatisfied’ powers like Germany had been so dissatisfied and why the satisfied powers after 1919 like Britain had been the authors of so much of their own undoing in the 1930s. It also happened to cite The Twenty Years’ Crisis on at least one occasion,68 and was attacked in an equally vituperative way by critics, though this time not for its relativism so much as its indifference to the fate of small nations and overly friendly attitude towards the Soviet Union. One politician was even led to the rather apocalyptic conclusion that with the publication of Conditions of Peace Carr had become ‘an active danger to the country’.69

Carr’s other response to The Twenty Year’s Crisis was less to his various critics and more to what he saw as an unresolved tension in the book. As he later noted, he had in 1939 hovered between two positions which he had never quite resolved in his own mind: one which continued to insist that the nation-state would still remain the principal unit of the international system, and another which hinted (no more) that there could be no sense of order within that system so long as the nation-state remained in being.70 A series of events in the meantime, including the experience of wartime planning and further reflection on the future of Europe, had resolved that contradiction. By 1945 he had thus arrived at the conclusion that not only was the small nation-state an impediment standing in the way of international stability and prosperity, but so too was the nation-state more generally. In the past, he had, he confessed, ‘too readily’ and ‘too complacently’ accepted the ‘existing nation-state, (large and small)’ as the basic unit of ‘international society’. By the time the war had come to an end he had arrived at a very different answer to his original question about how to organize the new international order. Indeed, if there was to be one at all, it was absolutely vital to think of security less in terms of nations and more in terms of meeting those most basic of human rights such as freedom from fear, from want and from unemployment, rights that transcended boundaries and united peoples whatever their nationality. Carr had few illusions about how difficult it would be to arrive at such a ‘utopian’ solution. Nonetheless, it would in his view be ‘an illusion’ to think that security could be attained through the vehicle of the nation-state. It would be equally na tve to suppose that the growing and irresistible demand for social justice could be attained by returning to the ‘free’ international economy of the nineteenth century. If mankind was to learn from the past, it had to face up to the simple truth that nineteenth-century solutions were not enough in the modern age; and if history taught anything, it was that ‘old traditions’ would ‘have to be discarded’ and ‘new ones created before Europe and the world’ could ‘recover their balance in the aftermath of the age of nationalism’.71

Mr Carr goes to Washington

The publication of Nationalism and After marked the beginning of an important transitional period in Carr’s already hectic life. In 1945 he signed yet another contract with Macmillan, this time to publish a major study on the History of Soviet Russia, though little anticipating that it would take him over thirty years to complete.72 A year later he brought out two more books, one a partially (but controversially) revised edition of The Twenty Years’ Crisis itself, and the other a relatively short and popular study entitled The Soviet Impact on the Western World, possibly his most pro-Soviet volume to date which contained what even Carr later agreed were a few ‘exaggerations’.73 In 1947 he then resigned his position at Aberystwyth. Thereafter, he held a few temporary appointments before being elected to a Fellowship at Trinity College Cambridge in 1955. Finally, of course, he was very much present at the creation of a new world order, but unfortunately one which bore little resemblance to that which he had looked forward to for so long. Indeed, as the Cold War intensified, Carr found that his particular style of radical theorizing, combined with what many saw as his pro-Soviet outlook, made him something of a political outsider in the new Britain of the late 1940s and early 1950s. Vilified by his conservative enemies on the right, and attacked quite openly by economic liberals like Hayek (who referred to him as one of the ‘totalitarians in our midst’)74 and academic insiders like Isaiah Berlin (who shared his fascination with nineteenth-century Russia but hated his politics),75 Carr effectively became a prophet outcast in his own country.

However, while all this was happening at home, within the newly established bastion of free world anti-communism, his study on international relations started to exert some considerable influence. The Twenty Years’ Crisis had already acquired a fairly wide readership in the United States before the end of the Second World War and its reissue in 1946 then made it more widely available. Carr had further contributed to his reputation (and notoriety) through the publication of Conditions of Peace and Nationalism and After, both of which appeared in American editions. Some insiders were also aware of his many editorials written for the London Times, and while a few might have appreciated the writing of this quasi-anonymous dissident at the heart of the English establishment, others took a less charitable view of the steady stream of pieces flowing from Carr’s pen attacking the fundamentals of the free enterprise system. A number of Americans were equally sensitive to the fact that Carr’s radical views were none too popular amongst certain British politicians either. Indeed, at dinner one evening, the Duke of Devonshire was even reported to have attacked what he and many others viewed as the left-wing drift in The Times, and while nobody named Carr, many believed that it was this ‘Red Professor from Printing House Square’ who was behind the whole thing. This certainly seemed to be the view across the Atlantic where Carr amongst others was seen (by the New York Times no less) as having transformed this once solid bastion of the British ruling class into what one critic called the ‘the final edition of the Daily Worker’ – then the daily newspaper of the British Communist Party.76

Carr was not an unknown in the United States therefore. Nor was he unfamiliar with the country itself. He had visited America in the first three months of 1938 (he had even had tea at the White House with Mrs Roosevelt) and thereafter kept a close watch on developments there as the war unfolded and it became increasingly clear that Britain’s leading role in world affairs was gradually giving way to a new Pax Americana. Carr viewed such a trend with a sense of regret and concern, and warned policy-makers of the dangers of drawing too close to the United States – partly because this would reduce Britain’s room for manoeuvre in the post-war world, but largely because this would alienate the USSR and lead to a new confrontation which he very much wanted to avoid. Not surprisingly, the almost irresistible train of events that led to the Cold War disturbed him greatly. Carr did not blame the West entirely for this drift. However, there was little question in his mind that the main responsibility for the breakdown in relations was America’s refusal after the war – like Britain’s before it – to accommodate the rising power of a potential rival.77

It was within the context of a conflict that Carr fundamentally opposed, in a country which he largely blamed for having initiated it, that The Twenty Years’ Crisis had its greatest success in the immediate post-war years. In many ways Carr was a most fortunate author. His volume was one of only a handful on the market, and although written by a non-American had the advantage of being published by someone from a country that still had more than its fair share of admirers in the United States. It also happened along at a particularly important and favourable juncture when international relations as an academic discipline was beginning to take off as a taught subject in American universities. Naturally, there were other books available, and many more would follow as the subject blossomed in the 1950s.78 However, for the moment, in the land of the rising superpower where numerous courses on ‘IR’ were beginning to proliferate alongside those of other expanding disciplines such as Sovietology (’know the enemy’), Strategic Studies (’know how to deter the enemy’) and Area Studies (’know where the enemy will strike next’), The Twenty Years’ Crisis proved to be particularly popular. As one American reviewer had predicted, it was always likely to do well and ‘would make an admirable introductory text for any college course in diplomatic history or international relations’, especially as it provided both an excellent analysis of the causes of war and an even ‘more fruitful’ discussion of the problems facing the peace-makers.79

The first to discover this, much to his own surprise one suspects, was Carr himself when he returned to America to teach and research in 1948. After having delivered many lectures in ‘various universities’ across the United States, he found out – much to his chagrin – that while The Twenty Years’ Crisis was in great demand, his British-based publishers were failing to meet this with a steady supply of books. This not only made little sense from a commercial point of view, it was also very annoying, especially as Carr had discovered at first hand that ‘the book was being fairly widely used as a textbook in international relations’. What he had also found out was that ‘the subject’ was ‘increasing’ in the US by what he called ‘leaps and bounds’. It was a matter of some urgency therefore that Macmillan ship out more copies without any further delay.80 Two months on and Carr was still urging his publisher to remain ever-vigilant. It was critically important, he felt, to keep the ‘American market well fed’. The volume had proven to be a success, ‘largely’ in the ‘universities’. But it was vital to keep stocks up. Sales had already been adversely affected by a failure on the part of Macmillan to ‘guarantee copies’ in enough numbers in the past, and it was essential not to let this happen again in the future. As he pointed out, American ‘professors and tutors had a habit in this country’ (he noted with some incredulity) of ‘asking publishers in advance whether copies of a book’ were available before they would ‘put it on “reading lists for students”’. And many, he had heard, had not done so because they could not get hold of it. Carr was most insistent, admitting that while he would not be quite so optimistic about sales of some of his other work in the United States, he was ‘sure’ that given conditions in America there would be a ‘lasting demand’ for The Twenty Years’ Crisis.81

Carr’s optimism about the potential market for The Twenty Years’ Crisis in the United States was not misplaced. Its analysis of past failures and rather bleak assessment of what motivated men and nations, seemed to match the American mood as it entered into the dark tunnel that was the Cold War. Naturally enough, not everyone appreciated his materialist epistemology or his debt to Marxism.82 But what one did not appreciate one could simply ignore. The book, after all, told a riveting story about the illusions of liberalism and the collapse of an international system, and many read it as a warning to a new generation not to repeat the same mistakes again. This was one of the reasons presumably why Carr’s work held a particular fascination for one man in particular: the German émigré, Hans J. Morgenthau. Though he was less radical than Carr as a function of his economics, and more inclined to think of the drive for power in terms of human nature rather than the uneven distribution of resources, there was clearly much that the two men had in common.83 Both saw the twentieth century as a tragedy.84 The two together had deep concerns about the relevance of liberalism as a doctrine for the twentieth century. And they had a similar understanding of history and the history of political thought.85 In their very different ways, they were also highly critical of policy-makers in the West, and while Carr was perhaps the more dissident of the two, Morgenthau always retained a deep suspicion of those who wielded what he wrote about most – namely political power.

It was not insignificant therefore that Morgenthau decided to write an extended review of Carr’s work in the first issue of the journal World Politics in 1948. In an essay that was as incisive as it was sparkling, he combined both high praise and serious criticism in equal measure. Morgenthau was in little doubt. Carr, he argued, had written four books since 1939 (The Twenty Years’ Crisis, Conditions of Peace, Nationalism and After and The Soviet Impact on the Western World) that taken together represented a contribution of the ‘first order’ which ‘lucidly and brilliantly’ exposed the faults of ‘contemporary political thought in the Western world’. They were so good in fact that they almost rivalled in depth one of Morgenthau’s (and Carr’s) intellectual heroes: Reinhold Niebuhr. However, there was a fundamental flaw and there was no point denying it. The basic problem was less historic than ‘philosophic’. Carr, he suggested, had done a wonderful job explaining the crisis; where he had failed was in finding a moral solution to it. Here Morgenthau effectively restated what others had already said before – that Carr’s relativism made it impossible for him to develop a ‘transcendent point of view from which to survey the political scene and to appraise the phenomenon of power’. The result was to transform Carr the critic and ‘political moralist’ into Carr the ‘utopian of power’ whose only means of knowing what was right or wrong was by the criteria of power itself. Hence, whoever held seeming superiority of power became of necessity the repository of a superior morality as well. It was one thing quoting Machiavelli; however for an observer standing outside the world of power, it was still a dangerous thing to be a Machiavelli. It was even worse to be a Machiavelli ‘without virtu’.86

Though critical, Morgenthau’s review obviously did Carr’s reputation a great deal of good in the United States, where sales of the book continued to be steady. However, there was a limit to how well a complex study originally entitled Utopia and Reality, written by a radically-inclined Englishman with a distinct bias against the capitalist system, was ever going to do in the United States. Moreover, as the subject continued to expand so too did demand for more accessible textbooks, and whatever else might be said about The Twenty Years’ Crisis it was most definitely not that. It may well have been called an ‘introduction to the study of international relations’, but it could not have read like one to the average American graduate looking for a basic route map through contemporary world problems. This is why Morgenthau’s own volume, Politics Among Nations, first published in 1948, was to do so well. Brought out by a commercial publisher and written very specifically for the student market, it established itself as the book on international relations in ways that The Twenty Years’ Crisis could never have done. With its simple structure and lists of these principles of realism, those definitions of foreign policy, and its four reasons why disarmament could not work, it was the perfect vehicle for those looking for a quick and easy entry into the subject. By contrast, The Twenty Years’ Crisis was not only structurally difficult and intellectually more demanding, but did not even begin to address the sorts of issues such as deterrence and American grand strategy, that were fast becoming part of the staple fare in most American courses on international relations.87

Carr also suffered as the discipline itself began to evolve in the United States from what it had been in the initial stages – a subject as much influenced by history and political philosophy as by political science – to what it gradually became in the 1960s and 1970s: quantitative, behavioural, and narrowly scientific in scope. In this brave new measured world of game theory, where one’s level of analysis appeared to count as much if not more than one’s understanding of the past, Carr’s volume, with its extraordinary range of references drawn from a host of writers who were either unknown or taboo in the United States, must have made The Twenty Years’ Crisis look not only outdated and wordy (and possibly subversive too) but beside the point. No doubt historians of the discipline still found him interesting, as did political theorists.88 But as the focus of the subject altered and the issues it addressed changed, then The Twenty Years’ Crisis began to look more and more like an historical hangover from a bygone age. Not that Carr disappeared from sight completely. In 1964 his book came out in a popular softback American edition, which did quite well. In 1967 he was then made the subject of a major review, though unfortunately not a particularly good or positive one.89 And a few years later he resurfaced once again through the work of Robert Gilpin, whose interest in the concept of hegemony and hegemonic stability led him to engage in a fairly serious way with Carr’s analysis of the inter-war system.90 For some at least The Twenty Years’ Crisis still retained some fascination, even in an age of high positivism when neither his questions nor his answers seemed as pertinent as they once had to an earlier generation growing up in the shadow of the Second World War and the early days of the Cold War.

Carr’s growing marginalization from mainstream international relations in the United States in the 1960s and 1970s, should not, though, obscure his very real impact.91 As yet another American admirer put it, The Twenty Years’ Crisis was in effect the ‘the first "scientific" treatment of modern world politics’ and was regarded as such by very many of those who entered the discipline by one route or another in the years immediately following the war.92 Carr also exerted an influence in another, possibly less positive way: by furnishing students with a particular story about how international relations had evolved and matured into a serious and scientifically respectable academic discipline. The story was simple and optimistic, and like all the best stories it had a happy ending. According to those who told it, this wily Englishman engaged in mortal intellectual combat with a range of woolly-minded thinkers who did not understand the real world, and after several skirmishes met and defeated them in a battle that came to be known as the ‘first great debate’. Naturally enough he won the encounter, and consequently helped establish international relations as a proper subject, cleansed of the ‘utopian’ nonsense that had presumably held it back in the early years. This epic tale of Carr the impaler, confronting and finally defeating the beast of idealism, was repeated so often that few questioned what to later writers looked like a gross simplification. The fact that the beast was never killed, and that the impaler might have set up a series of straw men in the process, was largely ignored. So too was the rather obvious fact that there might have been other writers around who also contributed to the birth of the subject in the modern era.93 But again, this was politely passed over in silence by those who perhaps needed such simplifying ‘foundational myths’ to help them on their way.94 In this fashion, though unbeknown to Carr, The Twenty Years’ Crisis was transformed into an historic morality tale with its wise sages and na tve fools, with the former in the end vanquishing the latter and in the process purging the discipline of its early optimistic excesses.95

The other way in which Carr shaped the course of international relations in the United States was more theoretical than mythical, and this was by helping legitimize a particular theoretical approach that went under the generic name of ‘realism’. The precise extent to which he did so given the obvious differences between himself and Morgenthau, not to mention later versions of realism which possessed neither his critical understanding of the world nor his sensitivity to historical change, has led several writers to doubt there was ever a relationship at all.96 However, there was a connection of sorts.97 Carr may well have been a very different sort of realist, but The Twenty Years’ Crisis still addressed the fundamental problem of how inequality among states led to conflict between them, which remained of central concern to more mainstream writers.98 This might not have made Carr ‘the realist’s realist’,99 any more than his particular brand of realism prevented him from both justifying the appeasement of Hitler while attacking the foundations of bourgeois society at the same time.100 As has been observed, there are many different types of realist and various forms of realism.101 But that has always been the ‘trouble’ with a theory that in one set of hands can justify the use of power, and in others (like Carr’s) can be turned into a critical weapon to attack those who would defend the status quo.102

Carr, Merrie England and the ‘English School’

One of the many ironies about the history of The Twenty Years’ Crisis is that while its meaning was being vigorously debated in the United States, in the land of Carr’s birth it was revered but rarely discussed at all. Even in his almer mata back in Wales it was hardly a cause for fevered discussion. Indeed, according to one who joined the department in 1961 he had ‘no recollection of Carr ever being mentioned in lectures or seminars’.103 Certainly, the more general relationship between the man on the one hand, and what passed for the subject of international relations in Britain in the 1950s and 1960s on the other, could hardly be described as intimate. He reviewed the odd book,104 and once even read a manuscript by C. A. W. Manning in 1961, though only to warn the publishers that if they were to publish it they had better be prepared for some ‘perfunctory and hostile reviews’.105 He also attended a conference commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of his old department back in Aberstwyth,106 and on one occasion was persuaded by NATO to give a lecture on the world scene, which he appropriately entitled ‘The Twenty Years’ Crisis’.107 But that was about the sum of it. Carr had very little interest in the subject as such, while some of those who purported to represent the subject had, it seems, little desire to engage in a positive way with him.108 In fact, when a number of leading lights, including the Cambridge historian, Herbert Butterfield, decided to form what became known as the ‘British Committee on the Theory of International Relations’ in the late 1950s, they did not even invite him. As one of the initial founders of the group, Martin Wight made clear: ‘I hesitate about E. H. Carr’ not on personal grounds, but ‘because he is so much of a Great Power in this region that I should have misgivings lest he might deflect our discussions into channels opened up by his own work’.109 There would have been little point inviting him anyway. The central intellectual concept around which the Committee was originally formed – the idea of an ‘international society’ of states bound by common rules and institutions for the conduct of their relations – was one that was hardly likely to recommend itself to someone as ‘Hobbesian’ as Carr.110

The history of the Committee and its relationship with Carr was by any measure a strange one. Its members obviously knew about his work in general and The Twenty Years’ Crisis in particular. Martin Wight had even written a penetrating and critical review of The Twenty Years’ Crisis in 1946 in which he not only chastised Carr’s ‘provocative’ but ‘unsatisfying’ study, but also claimed that one of his early critics, Leonard Woolf, had penned a ‘deadly reply’.111 The conservative Wight thereafter never appeared to be anything but hostile, and though he felt obliged to come to terms with what even he recognized was a ‘brilliant’ study, was very much opposed to Carr, and, according to one account at least, ‘treated’ him ‘with disdain’.112 He was certainly critical of his views and at different times attacked his defence of appeasement, what he saw as his Marxist-influenced theory of ideology,113 and the fact that he regarded ‘power’ as being ‘anterior to society, law, justice and morality’.114 Nor was one of the other members of the Committee, Butterfield, especially enamoured of his Cambridge colleague either, and for good reason. Carr had after all attacked him in no uncertain terms in 1951 as one of the many historians who propounded what to his eyes at least seemed to be a reactionary theory that denied the possibility of progress.115 He had then criticized him again a decade later, and, more robustly still, for having written a ‘remarkable book’ (The Whig Interpretation of History) that was remarkable amongst other things for not having named ‘a single Whig except Fox, who was no historian, or a single historian save Acton, who was no Whig’.116 Butterfield in turn had little time for Carr whose defence of the Russian revolution left the Christian Butterfield very cold indeed.117 Butterfield was even moved to attack Carr’s views expressed in his best-seller What is History? published in 1961. While conceding that the book was ‘most interesting’ he still thought that there was ‘a distinct tendency’ within Carr’s approach which ‘operates to undermine the status of history as an autonomous science’.118 Interestingly, it was through his prompting that Carr in the end was refused an invitation to join the Committee.119

The renewed interest in Carr, if it can be called that, did not stem from any work done on him by the Committee or by any attempt by this distinctly exclusive group to come to terms collectively with The Twenty Years’ Crisis.120 Rather it manifested itself in one of the more serious individual efforts by one of its members, Hedley Bull, to assess its contribution and relevance thirty years after its original publication. An Australian by birth who came to Britain before returning home in the second half of the 1960s, Bull had been taught by both Wight and Manning at the LSE, though his main inspiration initially was Philip Noel-Baker, even though Bull strongly opposed Noel-Baker’s support for disarmament. In the 1960s he then turned his attention to the issue of how international order could be maintained under conditions of sovereignty and anarchy, and arrived at the conclusion, via a reading of the seventeenth-century legal theorist Grotius, that states did not inhabit a Hobbesian universe but rather constituted a society of their own bound together by law. At first sight, therefore, there was little to suggest that Bull and Carr had a great deal in common. But Bull did have an interest in The Twenty Years’ Crisis and felt obliged to deal with it seriously. Originally entitled ‘E. H. Carr and the Fifty Years’ Crisis’, his critique was finally published as ‘The Twenty Years’ Crisis Thirty Years On’. In many respects, the paper not only represented ‘an important stage in the evolution’ of his own thinking,121 but also constituted something of a manifesto for those who felt that Carr represented more of an obstacle to the development of a mature international relations than an inspiration.

Bull did not reject The Twenty Years’ Crisis in its entirety. Indeed, there were certain things with which he strongly agreed, including its realist rejection of liberal internationalism and suggestive observations on the problem of peaceful change. Bull even went so far as to suggest that Carr’s more general ‘analysis of what international politics’ was like was ‘correct’. However, there were many more things with which he happened to disagree. Most obviously he rejected the book’s ‘relativism’ and by way of example approvingly cited Morgenthau’s earlier observation that Carr, lacking any objective perspective of his own from which to make an ethical judgment about the world, was always compelled to ‘surrender’ to what the American writer had called ‘the immanence of power’. It was no accident of course that Carr had been in favour of appeasement, for it flowed logically from what Bull defined as his ‘relativist and instrumentalist conception of morals’ in which it was impossible to distinguish between good and evil, right and wrong. Bull’s other more substantial objection was historical. The Twenty Years’ Crisis, he believed, was in essence a ‘tract for 1939, not for 1969’. It was important therefore to develop a theory of international relations that reflected new realities. According to Bull, when Carr had written his volume the world was a very different place. Europe stood at its heart, Wilsonianism remained a genuine force in international politics, realism had yet to assert itself, and the main line of division internationally was that deriving from the legacy of 1919. Thirty years on and the situation had altered dramatically. European domination was a thing of the past, the lessons of realism had been assimilated, the main divisions in the world were no longer between the defenders and the critics of the Versailles system, and the greatest challenge now was not how to deal with ‘have-not’ powers like Germany but the new revisionist states in the Third World like communist China. In short, new times posed different questions that were bound to lead to different types of answers.

It was at this point that Bull laid his own particular theoretical cards on the table. Carr, he agreed, had done a fine job demolishing old nineteenth-century illusions about the world, and an even more important one showing how foundational notions developed in one era and unfortunately retained in another – had been one of the main causes of the twenty years’ crisis. However, ‘having completed this work of demolition’ Carr had not then gone on to consider what ‘institutions and devices’ would be necessary to sustain and maintain ‘order’ among states under ‘present circumstances’. This then allowed Bull to introduce his own master concept that of ‘international society’, a notion that Carr ‘scarcely recognized’ in The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Indeed, according to Bull, in the ‘course of demonstrating how appeals to an overriding international society subserve the special interests of the ruling groups of powers’ Carr had jettisoned ‘the idea of international society itself’. This was his major weakness as a theorist then and why his views had to be repudiated now: not because he was wrong in terms of his understanding of history or even in rejecting the claims of the idealists so-called; but rather because his whole outlook denied the possibility of there ever having been (or there being) an order based upon common interests, common values and by implication comnion rules and institutions that taken together formed the basis of ‘an international society’. This was critical: critical in terms of Carr but critical too in terms of the future of international relations because it was this ‘idea’ which Carr had rejected so strongly in 1939 that would, he hoped, form the foundation stone for a ‘new analysis of the problem of international relations’. What Carr had started but failed to complete we should ‘now begin’.

The extent to which Bull presented an entirely accurate picture of Carr’s international relations must be open to some doubt.122 However, the importance of the piece did not lay in its literal accuracy, but in what it said about Carr’s theoretical denial of something which Bull saw as fundamental. On this issue at least Bull could hardly be faulted. The Twenty Years’ Crisis had grappled with the question of how states related to each other, but it had arrived at rather different conclusions to those which Bull regarded as being central to the renewal of international relations. Carr agreed. As he admitted a few years after The Twenty Years’ Crisis had been published, he too had once wondered whether there had been (or could ever be) what he called a ‘community of nations’, but had arrived at the conclusion that under conditions of inequality it was simply out of the question.123 He was also familiar with the work of Charles Manning whose ideas had had a big impact on people like Bull, and he did not think much of them. In fact at about the same time that the British Committee was setting out on its own particular journey, he was privately deriding Manning’s theoretical claims about the ‘nature of international society’ as being likely to ‘encourage illusions’.124 Nor did he change his mind much thereafter, and several years later confessed to an American academic that he and others had tried many years ago ‘to conjure into existence an international society’. However, the whole project had come to nothing for the simple reason that there was no such thing as ‘an international society’ but instead ‘an open club without substantive rules’ a view diametrically opposed to that of Bull’s.125

Bull’s critique of Carr’s theory and Carr’s rejection of the core notion that formed the basis of what subsequently became known as the English School, appeared to leave little room for doubt. The two had little in common and there was little point in trying to reconcile what in the end could not be reconciled.126 Of course, those who constituted the school so-called could hardly ignore The Twenty Years’ Crisis. It was, after all, one of the most famous studies on international relations written by a non-American, and anybody entering the discipline in Britain had to come to terms with it. In the end, however, the distance separating Carr the Englishman and this very specific ‘English’ contribution to the discourse of international relations, was an extraordinarily wide one.127 On one side stood those who stressed the centrality of shared norms and that which Carr had long ago rejected – the idea that there was an entity known as a society of states; and on the other was Carr himself, who, in spite of a certain tough-minded historical realism that people like Bull and Wight appreciated, conceived of international politics in a very different way. That he stimulated critics like Wight and Bull goes without saying. Indeed, in a crucial way, it is difficult to understand what they had to say without first having read Carr. But is difficult to think of Carr actually anticipating their work.128 He may have forced others of a very different persuasion to take him seriously. But, as both Bull and Wight seemed to imply, he represented a hurdle that had to be overcome rather than a resource to be used.129

Carr goes critical

If Carr’s connection to the English School remained decidedly tenuous, one wonders what he would have made of the new interest taken in his work by a group of writers in the 1980s and 1990s. Critical of those who would subsume him under the banner heading of ‘realist’, but equally chary of being labelled Marxist themselves, this diverse band came to see in Carr a much underutilized resource that was going begging in the last decade of the Cold War. Motivated by either a more general discontent with the conservative character of international relations as a discipline, or a desire to take security studies and political economy in a more radical direction, supporters of what became known as ‘critical theory’ came to see in Carr someone who could be deployed in a more creative fashion than he had been in the past. Inspired in some cases by the work of the early German theorist Max Horkheimer who, like Carr, saw a close relationship between the production of ideas and the world of power, and in others by the non-economistic Marxism of the Italian Communist Antonio Gramsci who popularized the key notion of hegemony, the new critical theorists were to go on to make a distinct contribution to the study of international relations, and one of the ways in which they did so was through a re-engagement with Carr’s work.

Perhaps the first move in the reclamation of Carr was taken by the Canadian political economist, Robert Cox. An expert on labour economics who had spent many years of his life working in the International Labour Organization in Geneva, Cox was an eclectic but creative thinker who with the less radical (but equally iconoclastic) Susan Strange had helped build a base within international relations for a more critically inclined political economy. Gramscian rather than Marxist in theoretical orientation, Cox had always been a great admirer of Carr. Significantly though it was not just The Twenty Years’ Crisis that informed his view of Carr (though it played a role) but Carr’s work more generally, including his various biographical studies of Bakunin and Herzen, Marx and Dostoevsky, his later work on the Russian revolution, as well as his thoughts on the nature of history. Indeed, what seemed to impress Cox most was Carr’s stubborn refusal to be bound by the sort of constrictions that later imposed themselves on academics trained in this or that particular narrow specialization. As Cox observed, Carr not only happened to be well informed but could combine many different levels of analysis, and so paint a picture of a particular period that was not merely more interesting than the average, but historically more sensitive as well. As Cox put it in a short, but deeply revealing autobiographical reflection,

Carr brought an historical mode of thought to whatever he wrote. He was equally alive to economic, social, cultural, and ideological matters. He studied individuals, especially those whose intellectual influence marked an era; but most of all, he brought all these elements to an understanding of structural change.130

Cox’s admiration for Carr was thus enormous. He certainly referred to him in his masterwork published in the second half of the 1980s.131 But it was his hugely influential article of 1981 that probably did more than anything else to raise Carr’s profile amongst a new generation of students looking for alternative ways of theorizing international relations. Yet the importance of the piece lay not so much in what Cox said about Carr and history, but in his insistence in drawing a clear line of demarcation between orthodox realism or neo-realism – against which the article was largely directed – and Carr’s own very distinctive approach to the study of world politics. Others had hinted at this in the past, and a few of his more sensitive interpreters had already made the point that Carr’s form of realism bore little resemblance to that propagated by more mainstream international relations in the United States.132 However, it was Cox, probably more than any other writer, who dug the deepest channel between the two, and ‘rescued’ Carr from what he saw as the iron grip that had been imposed upon him by others in the past. Not that Carr had nothing in common with other realists. On the contrary. However, it was his particular brand of realism that inspired Cox. For instead of accepting power as it was, Carr in his view managed to look behind the ideological masks which power wore and reveal its hidden mainsprings. Cox also liked the way in which Carr looked at the world not as a discrete set of realities but as a totality. This was critically important, for it meant that unlike more orthodox realists who made a sharp distinction between the unit of the state and the international system itself, Carr viewed ‘reality’ wholistically, never thinking for one moment that how states acted or what they did could be discussed separately from the larger international system. Nor did he accept that the relations between states were doomed to repeat themselves. Indeed, as Cox pointed out, the whole thrust of Carr’s discussion was to show how changes within states over time had led slowly and irrevocably to the breakdown of the conditions which had made the nineteenth century possible and the twentieth century so unstable. This again was crucial. In fact, it was only by employing a similar methodology (one which Carr, by the way, had developed quite independently of anything he may have said directly about either international relations or the state) that one would be able to illuminate the evolution of the modern state and global relationships in a very rapidly transforming world where production within nations was giving way to the internationalization of production, where the state as constituted since the Treaty of Westphalia was fast being internationalized itself, and where the forms of hegemony that had formed the basis of world order in the post-war period – a question that Carr had addressed briefly in his own study on the inter-war system – were fast dissolving and opening up new historical possibilities.133

In his own work Cox himself distinguished between two ways of thinking – one he termed ‘problem solving’ and the other ‘critical’. The former, which was distinctly not Carr, effectively accepted reality as it was and then attempted to solve any problems facing the world within a specific and set framework defined by those who controlled the reins of power. The latter stood apart from the prevailing order and asked how that order had come about, how it had changed over time, and ultimately how it might be transcended. Cox also insisted (and here he almost paraphrased Carr exactly) that all forms of theory must always be for someone or some purpose, and that unless it proposed a way forward it was little more than useless. Here again Carr served as a model thinker who not only discussed the causes of things – in this case the collapse of the inter-war system – but also tried to propose solutions. He did this initially and tentatively in the last few pages of The Twenty Years’ Crisis, and then in more detail in Conditions of the Peace, Nationalism and After, The Soviet Impact on the Western World and his important study, aptly and significantly called The New Society. This forward-looking or even utopian aspect of Carr’s work (largely ignored by international relations scholars in the United States and Britain during the height of the Cold War) was one that interested a number of writers other than Cox. One was the political theorist, Andrew Linklater. However, whereas Cox used Carr to inform his work on international political economy and large-scale historical change, Linklater deployed him to think creatively about the possibility of constructing a new theory of political community based upon different notions of citizenship.134

Like many in the international relations community, Linklater had for many years regarded Carr’s work as being that of an ‘unadulterated realist’. But in the process of rethinking his own ideas that would in the end take him ‘beyond realism and Marxism’ towards a more serious engagement with the idea of ‘the transformation of political community’, he was forced to come to terms once again with Carr’s contribution.135 He did so first in 1990 in a study that rather tentatively suggested that in The Twenty Years’ Crisis Carr had tried to resolve the basic ‘antinomy between realism and idealism’ by setting forth a ‘defence of national policy which aimed at the extension of moral obligation and the enlargement of political community’. But the idea was never fully developed and it was to take some time before Linklater would exploit Carr to the full. Interestingly this occurred not through any new reading of The Twenty Years’ Crisis, but through a discovery of Carr’s later work on nationalism and the nation-state. Indeed, it was to be Linklater’s meeting with this ‘other’ Carr, and in particular what he later referred to as his ‘magisterial essay’ Nationalism and After published in 1945, that seemed to inspire him far more than Carr’s earlier classic. Linklater’s praise for Carr’s 1945 study seemed to know no bounds. It was in his view ‘an exemplary attempt, unequalled in the field, to show how the achievements of modern political life can be secured while the propensity for violence and exclusion is overcome’; and Carr did so, basically, by both reconfiguring the relationship between the nation-state and the international system on the one hand, and the concept of citizenship and what citizenship meant in a new Europe on the other. The result was one of the more exciting and radical attempts in modern political theory to think through the lessons of the past in order to be able to build a more enlightened future that ‘would be more internationalist’ than its ‘predecessors, more sensitive to cultural differences, and more passionately committed to ending social and economic inequalities’.

What Linklater referred to as his ‘morally charged’ reading of Carr was not unconnected, of course, to a larger political and intellectual agenda in which he had by now become a key figure. Radical in outlook but open to many influences, the central concern of the new wave was to develop new perspectives in international relations that would challenge inequality and exclusion and in this way advance a form of emancipatory politics that was not just ‘problem solving’ (to use Cox’s terminology) but critical all the way down. Carr, he believed, contributed to this project in at least two important ways: through an embryonic but increasingly sophisticated normative analysis of how the nation-state ought to evolve; and by engaging in a serious (though largely unfinished) discussion of how the study of international relations might be reformed in order to tackle the dominant moral and political questions of the epoch. According to Linklater, this did not make Carr a utopian. As he noted, his proposals for a new politics was not spun out of thin air but was rather immanent in his analysis. On the other hand, it did not suffer from the ‘sterility’ normally associated with realism. And it was vitally important to reclaim this aspect of his thought, which had hitherto been obscured by his reputation as a realist. Only when this had been done would it be possible to develop a mature international relations which transcended the immediate without descending into fantasy.

Linklater’s long march back to Carr was paralleled, at least in part, by the journey travelled by an equally influential writer, Ken Booth. A strategist who had made his reputation in the 1970s, Booth gradually came to question most if not all of the central claims made by realism in the 1970s and 1980s. There was no ‘Road to Damascus’ conversion, but instead a series of engagements which over time led him to question that which he had once assumed to be true. The first realist truth to go was probably the notion that all states behaved similarly within a given set of determined structures; the next was the idea of the ‘Soviet threat’ and the logic or illogic of nuclear deterrence; and the last is what he later called the ‘Cold Wars of the mind’ which supported such policies. In the process, Booth carved out a quite unique position within and outside the international relations community, one that preceded the Second Cold War with the publication of his Strategy and Ethnocentrism in 1979, but was then consolidated in the turbulent days which followed in the ongoing debates about the role of nuclear weapons in a divided Europe. An early advocate of the notion of non-offensive defence, and a major enthusiast of Gorbachev’s new thinking about foreign policy and European security, Booth not only challenged conventional thinking about security policy but in the process effectively helped to popularize a set of fairly complex ideas that went under the general heading of ‘critical security studies’. Premised on the assumption that realism in its more developed form was inadequate, but that any prospect for change had to begin from where we were (rather than where we were not), ‘CSS’ as it became known ploughed a path somewhere between more radical critics on the far left who dreamed dreams that could never be realized, and the tired complacency that had for so long characterized thinking about security in the West.136

It was thus of no little significance that Booth decided to make Carr the subject of his inaugural lecture in 1991. Nor was it accidental. Booth, after all, had come to reject the realist norms in which he had originally been trained, and in Carr he saw a writer who had also grappled in the past with the questions posed by realism and found their answers to be wanting too. He was equally interested, however, in Carr the ‘utopian’ who though labelled ‘realist’ had (like himself) pursued what he called the same goal of trying to reconcile the pursuit of a different world – termed ‘utopia’ – but had sought to embed this within a given set of facts called ‘reality’. Booth called this approach ‘utopian realism’, which, though not without its problems, appealed precisely because it tried to bring together the two ‘planes’ of utopia and reality which Carr had said could never meet.137 Others had pursued the same goals of trying to reconcile the two, but it was possibly Carr more than anybody else who had grappled most consistently with the ever-present issue of seeking to develop a theory of the world based upon the world as an empirical reality but never accepting the world as it was. Not that Carr was without his problems. According to Booth, Carr was rather confused as to where he stood in relation to utopianism and realism. His attacks on the utopians so-called had also done a great deal of damage to the reputation of Kant. However, the important task was not to dwell on the limits of The Twenty Years’ Crisis, but instead to rescue its many insights from the realists pure and simple. His more orthodox readers in the past had only seemed to notice where Carr the realist was attacking the utopians. It was equally vital, if not more so, to note his uncertainty towards realism as well as where he made the most positive comments about utopianism itself.138

The attempt by a number of leading writers to retrieve Carr from realism and exploit his critical potential represented a significant move in international relations. Nonetheless, it was not without its problems. First, there was the not insignificant issue of Carr’s economics. Carr lived in an era during which the most readily available answer to the failure of the old economic system was some form of planning that would transcend the limits of the market and make a more effective use of resources in a more equitable way. The events of 1989, followed two years later by the disintegration of the Soviet Union, seemed to put pay to such ideas, and in the process removed at least one of the props supporting Carr’s larger vision of a new international order. His conception of that order moreover left a few things to be desired. A modernist in every respect who was ever keen to be on the side of what he saw as ‘progress’, he was perhaps a little less sensitive than he might have been about the costs which progress tended to exact from those who stood in the way. Indeed, those who did stand in the path of history got short shrift from Carr (small nations and peasants in particular) while those who appeared to be the bearers of a new age, the big powers, Lenin and even Stalin – that great ‘westernizer’, as he once referred to him – were more often than not treated with kid gloves. Carr, as Isaiah Berlin once observed, always seemed to be with the big battalions, the winners of history, and not its losers.139 Finally, if we are to judge Carr as a critical theorist, we can hardly ignore the fact that he effectively provided a rationalization for the foreign policies of Germany before the war, and Soviet Russia after it. No doubt both these ‘have-not’ states had suffered much at the hands of the more powerful democracies, and Carr was honest enough to say so. Unfortunately, in the process, he ended up by providing a theoretical gloss for what the two powers then did in Eastern Europe. This not only denied certain rights to countries like Czechoslovakia and Poland, but also laid Carr open to the quite legitimate charge of being consistently opposed to the West but not to the West’s enemies. Carr might have been critical, but evidently he was not consistently critical enough. To paraphrase a term later made popular in international relations, he was never quite critical ‘all the way down’.

Conclusion

As this extended essay has tried to show, The Twenty Years’ Crisis was not the only book that Carr wrote on international relations; however, it was the one volume that secured his reputation in the field. In a way this was most fortunate for Carr, for whereas what he regarded as his most important contribution to human knowledge – his history of early Soviet Russia – is now hardly read at all, The Twenty Years’ Crisis, in which he displayed only a limited degree of interest, continues to be read and discussed. Indeed, whereas his reputation as an historian of the USSR waned considerably after the system’s collapse in 1991, his standing in international relations appears to have gone from strength to strength. Moreover, this happened during a decade which was not especially kind to more conventional realists. Carr, on the other hand, was never more popular. In 1998 he was the subject of two major reassessments.140 The following year he got the biography he deserved.141 And in 2000 there was an attempt by scholars from a variety of disciplines to deal in a fair but not uncritical way with his contribution to intellectual life over a half-century period.142 So much got to be written about Carr in fact that one commentator was even moved to talk of a new ‘Carr’ industry in the making.143

This renewed interest in Carr raises a fairly obvious question about the contemporary importance and relevance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Carr himself always appeared to be in two minds about the book’s long-term prospects. He accepted that it might be of some ‘interest and significance’ to those who read it later. On the other hand, he did not have the confidence of someone like Thucydides the Greek historian, who predicted (correctly as it turned out) that his volume on the Peloponne-sian Wars would last ‘for ever’.144 Conceived in a pre-superpower age of well-defined nation-states and national economies, The Twenty Years’ Crisis, according to Carr just a few years after it had been published, had ‘already’ become something of ‘a period piece’. Several decades on, and that harsh judgement passed in 1945, when it was perfectly normal to assume (as did Carr) that western capitalism had a past but no future, and that planning and progress were synonymous terms, would appear to be more true than ever.

Yet serious claims can still be made on behalf of the book – the most obvious perhaps being that it does provide us with an extraordinarily exciting analysis of the inter-war period; and, as Carr no doubt anticipated, it was a period that was likely to cast a very long shadow. Certainly, the lessons later drawn from these turbulent years, especially the so-called lessons of ‘Munich’, played a critical role in shaping the way in which subsequent policy-makers in the West came to look at the world around them, particularly during the chill days of the Cold War, when many assumed that the only way of preventing another war now was by hanging tough with the Russians in ways that the democracies had not hung tough with the Germans before 1939. From this perspective, Carr served two entirely different masters in the post-war period: one that pointed to his advocacy of appeasement and cried ‘never again’, and another that relished his attacks on the idealists and applauded him loud and long for reminding the na tve that in an age of aggressive totalitarian powers, it was always wise to carry a big stick – even if one did not always have to use it.

Another important reason for revisiting The Twenty Years’ Crisis is that it is one of those books that can be read on several different levels. Written at a time when one era was about to break down, it can be studied, and more often than not has been, as a particular type of analysis of a very peculiar moment in time. But locked away within its more specific observations about the inter-war system, there was something of a more general character struggling to be heard: namely a theory of international crisis. Eschewing any single-factor structural explanation as to why wars occur or systems break down, Carr in effect identifies three critical factors that have to be present to make any potential crisis dangerous and threatening: the existence of powerful and resentful states situated outside of the international order; a profound and sustained disruption to the operation of the global economy; and finally the unwillingness or inability by any single power or ‘hegemon’ to underwrite international order. Carr may not have intended it, but situated within his explanation of one ‘twenty years’ crisis’ was a larger thesis about global stability and instability, and how and why international systems in general can and do break down, with the most devastating consequences.

The Twenty Years’ Crisis also addresses another major issue of more general concern – that is, how should victorious states set about building and maintaining peace after extended periods of war? The question has been and remains an important one, more so than ever perhaps since the end of the Cold War, when the victors once again were compelled to grapple with what one analyst has called ‘the fundamental problem of international relations’.145 It was certainly a problem with which Carr was familiar. In fact, one of the reasons for originally writing The Twenty Years’ Crisis was not to reflect endlessly on what had gone wrong in the past, but to ensure that the same mistakes were not made again in the future by those to whom Carr dedicated the book: the ‘makers of the coming peace’. And what the past taught was the following. That a successful peace required not only the formation of a set of international institutions but also the creation of a set of social and economic conditions as well; that there could be no peace in Europe unless Germany could find a secure place within it without having to resort to expansion; and that the nation-state had to be regarded as an obstacle to an orderly peace, rather than the vehicle through which order would be achieved. On all counts Carr turned out to be extraordinarily prescient. Indeed, as any study of the way in which those made the peace in 1945 and then again in 1989 would show, indirectly at least they owed a great deal to Carr, and people like Carr, who, having witnessed the failure of one peace settlement, were determined that the same would never happen again.146

The Twenty Years’ Crisis also has a great deal to say about the power of ideas in general, and the meaning of liberalism in particular.147 For Carr, of course, liberalism constituted an ideology of the nineteenth century that was bound to be superseded in the twentieth. In this he turned out to be the prophet of a false collectivist dawn. Liberalism not only survived under the umbrella of American power in the post-war period, but its central tenets proved to be far more resilient than he could ever have anticipated. In fact, with the unexpected victory of the West over communism in 1989, it actually experienced a surge of self-confidence that led at least one well-known writer to proclaim that there was now no serious alternative.148 Yet, as Carr would have observed, what constitutes the common sense of one age can very easily become the dangerous illusions of another, and a decade or so after the victory of liberalism its limits have become only too apparent, even to those who once championed its values of unfettered markets and open economies. And as we move from one era of romantic market triumphalism to another where an increasing number of actors are questioning the limits of the free enterprise system, we could do a lot worse than revisit what Carr had to say on the subject in The Twenty Years’ Crisis.

Finally, Carr’s whole approach to international relations, which understands the present as history and power as a problem that has to be taken seriously, is one that many modern students of the subject could do well to ponder. More recent trends in international relations have led some of its leading practitioners into some fairly arcane corners where discussions about what we know has been replaced by endless debates about whether we can know anything, and where the study of history seems to have been replaced by a series of constructed narratives that take as their point of departure the idea that history as such does not exist. Innovation is no doubt the spice of intellectual life, and all advances in knowledge are likely to be built on the bones of those who have gone before. But an international relations that denies the notion of a past, or takes no interest in power, is hardly likely to come up with any major discoveries. This is why The Twenty Years’ Crisis retains its vitality, as both a reminder of what we need to be studying and why, and why an engagement with history and power does not have to lead to a worship of either. If we take nothing more than that from the study of his classic work, then we may have taken a very great deal indeed.

1.

|   |

See E. L. Ellis, The University College of Wales Aberystwyth 1872–1972 (Cardiff: University of Wales Press, 1972), esp. pp. 245–60.

2.

|   |

In his Inaugural Lecture delivered in Aberystwyth on 14 October 1936, Carr (who had at one time been Assistant Adviser on League Affairs in the Foreign Office) criticized the idea of using economic sanctions to either punish or deter Japanese aggression in Asia. This infuriated his liberal critics who also happened to be close to Davies. One such was Gilbert Murray, who attacked Carr directly in a personal letter for having in his lecture repudiated ‘the whole League principle’. How, he continued, was the expansion of Germany, Japan or Italy to be resisted if sanctions were abandoned? Carr replied that unless one was prepared to resort to force, then all talk of sanctions was pointless. Cited in Christopher Thorne, The Limits of Foreign Policy: the West, the League and the Far Eastern Crisis of 1931–1933 (London: Macmillan, 1972), p. 382. The Carr Lecture was published under the title of ‘Public Opinion as a Safeguard of Peace’, International Affairs, Vol. XV, No. 6, November-December 1936, pp. 1–17. See also his ‘The Future of the League’, The Fortnightly, October 1936 (pp. 385–96) where Carr contrasts the League of the Realists which he associated with the Covenant ‘a cautious and comparatively “realistic” document’, and the ‘League of the Idealists’ who hoped to use the League to prevent war by ‘turning sovereign states into good, law-abiding members of the international community’

3.

|   |

The controversy surrounding the Carr appointment in Aberystwyth is explored in Brian Porter, ‘E. H. Carr – the Aberystwyth Years, 1936–1947’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal (Basingstoke: Palgrave, 2000), pp. 36–67.

4.

|   |

Letter from E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 17 March 1936. Carr Papers, theUniversity of Birmingham Special Collection (hereafter CPB).

5.

|   |

Carr used the term in an interview with Peter Scott, ‘Revolution without Passion’, The Times Higher Educational Supplement, 7 July 1978, p. 7.

6.

|   |

Michael Bakunin (London: Macmillan, 1937).

7.

|   |

International Relations Since the Peace Treaties (London: Macmillan, 1937); later reissued under the new title International Relations Between the Two World Wars (London: Macmillan, 1947). The success of the book was in large part due to Carr spotting a special gap in the market. In his 17 March 1936 letter to Harold Macmillan, he believed that there might be ‘a big demand for such a book — not only for WEA [Workers’ Education Association] purposes but for the sixth forms of schools (particularly girls’ schools where they now all study ‘current events’)’. There are no separate figures to indicate just how many ‘girls’ schools’ actually purchased the volume! (CPB).

8.

|   |

In his 17 March 1936 letter to Harold Macmillan, Carr wrote that ‘the first resultof the appointment [to the Wilson Chair] is that I have been asked whether or not I will write a short text-book on international affairs since 1919 for publication in Welsh by the university press (mainly I gather, for educational purposes). It will only be worth my while to do so if I can also find an English publisher. Would your firm be interested?’. Carr sent in final proofs in January 1937 (CPB).

9.

|   |

Conditions of Peace (London: Macmillan, 1942). Nationalism and After (London: Macmillan, 1945) sold something close to 30,000 copies and was translated into six languages. The Soviet Impact on the Western World (London: Macmillan, 1946) sold nearly as well and was translated into five languages. Figures from the Macmillan Publisher Archives (hereafter MPA).

10.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, ‘Report And Programme Of Wilson Professor’, 6 April 1943, p. 53. The University College of Wales Aberystwyth Archives (hereafter UWA).

11.

|   |

Britain: Study of Foreign Policy from the Versailles Peace Treaty to the Outbreak of War (London: Longmans, Green & Co., 1939).

12.

|   |

Carr signed the contract to write Utopia and Reality on 25 July 1938. The title The Twenty Years’ Crisis (1919–1939): an Introduction to the Study of International Relations was only agreed to on 15 August 1939 (MPA).

13.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 15 December 1938 (MPA).

14.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 12 December 1939 (MPA).

15.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 27 July 1939 (MPA).

16.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 15 August 1939 (MPA).

17.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 2 December 1939 (MPA).

18.

|   |

Professor E. H. Carr, ‘Report and Programme of the Wilson Professor’, 6 April. University of Wales, Aberystwyth Archives (UWA).

19.

|   |

It was planned to translate The Twenty Years’ Crisis into Dutch in 1940 but the war made this impossible. It was first translated into Swedish in 1941 and Spanish in 1942 (Sweden and Spain being neutral countries). It then appeared in Japanese (in 1951 and 1994), German (1972), Portuguese (1981 and 2000), Greek (1999) and Korean (2000). Information from Carr’s literary agents, Curtis Brown of London. Total sales of the book in English are difficult to calculate from the files, but my own estimate is somewhere around 50,000. This includes all the reprints of the 1st edition of 1939 (three in 1940 alone), the thirteen printings of the 2nd edition of 1946, and the Papermac version of the book which came out in 1981, 1983 and 1984 (twice). This figure does not include sales since 1984, foreign language sales, or sales from the US edition published by Harper & Row, New York in 1964.

20.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Sheila Fitzpatrick, 4 November 1971 (CPB).

21.

|   |

Letter E. H. Carr to Stanley Hoffman, 30 September 1977 (CPB).

22.

|   |

See for example, Ieuan John, Moorhead Wright and John Garnett, ‘International Politics at Aberystwyth, 1919–1969’, in Brian Porter (ed.), The Aberystwyth Papers: International Politics (London: Oxford University Press, 1972), p. 97.

23.

|   |

In one diary entry, Carr notes that ‘Simon’ [Sir John Simon] rang up to ask if I had been elected to a chair at Oxford’. 6 February 1936 (CPB).

24.

|   |

Under the nom de plume of John Hallett, Carr wrote in 1933 that the utopian notion of a classless society was the ‘Achilles’ Heel of Marxism’, and that the idea of one was as ‘dull as the heaven of the orthodox Victorian’. See his ‘Karl Marx: Fifty Years After’, Fortnightly, March 1933, p. 321.

25.

|   |

For Carr’s scepticism about ‘world revolution’ see his later History of Soviet Russia (1950–1978. London, Macmillan, 10 volumes, 1950–78). Carr recognized the influence of the USSR on the West. However, he never thought that revolution in the West was likely or feasible.

26.

|   |

On Carr’s early views, see his ‘Autobiography’ in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: Critical Appraisal, pp. xiii-xxii.

27.

|   |

Alan Sharp, ‘Britain and the protection of minorities at the Paris peace conference, 1919’, in A. C. Hepburn (ed.), Minorities in History (New York: St Martin Press, 1979), pp. 173 and 185 n.12.

28.

|   |

Mary Pomeroy letter to Jonathan Haslam, November 1995 (CPB).

29.

|   |

In early 1940 Carr objected to certain additions being proposed in order to update his International Relations Since the Peace Treaties. Significantly, he did so in part because these new ‘references to the United States’ struck him as being ‘both inadequate and to put it mildly, unsympathetic in tone’. He continued ‘I should particularly dislike it if a book for which I retain, in any event, a large share of the responsibility, contained passages about the United States which would inevitably provoke and irritate any American reader into whom whose hands they might fall’. Letter from E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 12 February 1940 (MAB).

30.

|   |

As part of his ongoing campaign against Carr, Lord Davies raised the issue of Carr’s critical attitude towards the American President. Over six years after Carr’s appointment, he wrote ‘I repeat I don’t know what his [Carr’s] policies are, but as you suggest they are anti-Wilson, [and] it seems curious that the Professor [Carr] should be content to occupy the Wilson Chair —’ See his correspondence with Gilbert Murray, 5 June 1943 (UWA).

31.

|   |

Quote from E. H. Carr, From Napoleon to Stalin and other Essays (London: Macmillan, 1980), p. 7.

32.

|   |

John Hallett (E. H. Carr), ‘Nationalism: the World’s Bane’, Fortnightly, June 1932, pp. 694–702.

33.

|   |

See John Hallett, ‘England Adrift’, Fortnightly, September 1930, pp. 354–62.

34.

|   |

Professor E. H. Carr, ‘What Are We fighting For?’ Record of meeting held at Chatham House, 14 August 1940 (CPB).

35.

|   |

Untitled draft dated June 1944, 12pp (CPB).

36.

|   |

Memorandum from Mr E. H. Carr to Mr Barrington-Ward, 5 August 1940 (CPB).

37.

|   |

See, for example, John Hallett (E. H. Carr), ‘The Poets of Soviet Russia’, The Christian Science Monitor, 25 April 1929, and ‘The Soviets Through Soviet Eyes’, The Spectator, 14 September 1934.

38.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, Dostoevsky, 1821–1881 (London: Unwin Books, 1931), The Romantic Exiles (London: Victor Gollancz, 1933) and Michael Bakunin (London: Macmillan, 1937).

39.

|   |

‘An Autobiography’, pp. xvi-xvii.

40.

|   |

Professor E. H. Carr, ‘Impressions of a Visit to Russia and Germany’. Lecture given at Chatham House, London, 12 October 1937 (CPB).

41.

|   |

For a detailed analysis of Carr’s position or positions on the USSR see R. W. Davies, ‘Carr’s Changing Views of the Soviet Union’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal, pp. 91–108.

42.

|   |

E. H. Carr, Karl Marx: a Study in Fanaticism (London: J. M. Dent, 1934).

43.

|   |

John Hallett (E. H. Carr), ‘Karl Marx – Fifty Years Later’, Fortnightly, March 1933, pp. 311–21.

44.

|   |

Two of the books which influenced Carr most were Reinhold Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society: a Study in Ethics and Politics (New York: Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1932) and Karl Mannheim, Ideology and Utopia: an Introduction to the Sociology of Knowledge (London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner & Co., 1936). In 1949 Carr spoke warmly of Niebuhr’s critical insights into the modern condition. See his ‘The Moral Foundations for World Order’, in E. L. Woodward et al., Foundations for World Order (Denver, Colorado: University of Denver Press, 1949), pp. 58–9. In 1953 Carr also wrote a highly sympathetic appreciation of Mannheim. Carr’s description of Mannheim could have almost been autobiographical. He wrote that while Mannheim ‘was never a Marxist — the Marxist foundations of his thought went deep’. See his ‘Karl Mannheim’ in E. H. Carr, From Napoleon to Stalin, pp. 177–83. See also Charles Jones, ‘Carr, Mannheim and a Post-Positivist Science of International Relations’, Political Studies, Vol. XLV, 1997, pp. 232–46.

45.

|   |

Quote from his letter to Stanley Hoffman, 30 September 1977 (CPB).

46.

|   |

‘An Autobiography’, pp. xvi-xvii.

47.

|   |

Martin Wight, International Theory: the Three Traditions (Leicester: Leicester University Press, 1991), p. 267

48.

|   |

See Whittle Johnson, ‘Carr’s Theory of International Relations’, The Journal of Politics, Vol. 29, 1967, pp. 861–84. Johnson is right to suggest that The Twenty Years’ Crisis does not present a unified view of this crisis. He is wrong to say that Carr therefore has ‘two theories of international relations’.

49.

|   |

As early as October 1937, Carr was anticipating a possible rapprochement between the Soviet Union and Nazi Germany. See his ‘Impressions of a Visit to Russia and Germany’, pp. 27–8

50.

|   |

Carr discusses the British security dilemma in his Britain: a Study of Foreign Policy.

51.

|   |

‘For by contrast with Carr’s other works, The Twenty Years’ Crisis is drenched in erudition’. Charles Jones, E. H. Carr and International Relations: Duty to Lie (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), p. 46.

52.

|   |

Letter from E. H. Carr to Harold Macmillan, 31 May 1939 (MAB).

53.

|   |

The issue of power and security, and how to employ force in the cause of peace, was one that increasingly preoccupied the thoughts of a number of Carr’s ‘utopians’, including Lord David Davies. Throughout the 1930s others like Robert Cecil and Gilbert Murray also began to grapple with the same issue. See Martin Ceadel, Semi-Detached Idealists: the British Peace Movement and International Relations, 1854–1945 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000), pp. 276–7.

54.

|   |

See the essays in Peter Wilson and David Long (eds), Thinkers of the Twenty Years’ Crisis: Inter-War Idealism Reassessed (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1995).

55.

|   |

‘It is thus rather curious that Carr remains celebrated for his staunch realist critique of idealism’. Stefano Guzzini, Realism in International Relations and International Political Economy: the Continuing Story of a Death Foretold (London: Routledge, 1999), p. 22.

56.

|   |

For a later elaboration of Carr’s vision for the post-war world see ‘Memorandum From Mr Carr To Mr Barrington–Ward’, 5 August 1940 (CPB)

57.

|   |

In 1980 he recalled that ‘the war came as shock which numbed the thinking process’ cited in ‘An Autobiography’, Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr, p. xix.

58.

|   |

See his Britain: a Study of Foreign Policy From the Versailles Treaty to the Outbreak of War (London: Longmans, Green & Co. 1939).

59.

|   |

Carr later wrote: ‘I remember seeing the guarantee of 1 April 1939, to Poland as the final recipe for disaster. We could not possibly implement it except in alliance with Russia and it was given in such a way to as to preclude any agreement’. See ‘An Autobiography’, Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr, p. xix.

60.

|   |

These reviews can be found in Times Literary Supplement, 11 November 1939, p. 65; Richard Coventry (Crossman), ‘The Illusions of Power’, New Statesman, XVIII, November 25, 1939; Foreign Affairs, Vol. 18, No. 3, April 1940, p. 564; and Crane Brinton, ‘Power and Morality in Foreign Policies’, Saturday Review, 17 February 1940, p. 19. The review of The Twenty Years’ Crisis by William P. Maddox can be found in American Political Science Review, Vol. 34, No. 3, 1940, pp. 587–8.

61.

|   |

See his letter to Macmillan where he criticizes his publishers for not maintaining stocks of The Twenty Years’ Crisis in the London bookshops! 2 December 1939 (MAB).

62.

|   |

Quotes from his memorandum to Barrington-Ward, 5 August 1940 (MAB).

63.

|   |

Carr had earlier attacked Arnold Toynbee’s views on world politics in International Affairs, Vol. XVI, March 1937, pp. 281–3.

64.

|   |

For a more detailed discussion of Carr’s early critics see Peter Wilson, ‘The Myth of the “First Great Debate"’, in Tim Dunne, Michael Cox and Ken Booth (eds), The Eighty Years’ Crisis: International Relations 1919–1999 (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1998), pp. 1–6, and his ‘Carr and his Early Critics: Responses to The Twenty Years’ Crisis, 1939–1946’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal, pp. 165–97.

65.

|   |

See Brian Schmidt, The Political Discourse of Anarchy: a Disciplinary History of International Relations (New York: State University of New York Press, 1998).

66.

|   |

See ‘An Autobiography’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal, p. xix.

67.

|   |

See C. A. W. Manning’s review of E. H. Carr, Conditions of Peace (London: Macmillan, 1942) in International Affairs, Vol. XIX, No. 8, June 1942, pp. 443–4.

68.

|   |

Conditions of Peace, p. xxiii, n. 2.

69.

|   |

See Jonathan Haslam, The Vices of Integrity: E. H. Carr 1892–1982 (London: Verso, 1999), pp. 96–100.

70.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, The Twenty Years’ Crisis 1919–1939: an Introduction to the Study of International Relations (London: Macmillan, 2nd edition, 1946) with a ‘Preface To Second Edition’ completed by Carr on 15 November 1945. See p. viii.

71.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, Nationalism and After (London: Macmillan, 1945).

72.

|   |

How significant Carr regarded the publication of what he termed – without irony – his ‘magnum opus’ on A History of Soviet Russia can be gleaned from letters sent to his publishers on 12 August 1949 and 21 April 1950 (MAB).

73.

|   |

Carr referred to The Soviet Impact on the Western World as ‘the sort of book which one wants to be got out quickly’. Letter to Macmillan Publishers, 21 May 1946 (CPB).

74.

|   |

F. A. Hayek, The Road To Serfdom (London: George Routledge & Sons Ltd. 1944), pp. 138–41.

75.

|   |

See Michael Ignatieff, Isaiah Berlin (London: Chatto & Windus, 1998), pp. 235–6.

76.

|   |

See Charles Jones, “’An Active Danger”: E. H. Carr at The Times’, in Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal, pp. 68–87.

77.

|   |

See, for example, E. H. Carr, ‘The Russian Revolution and the West’, New Left Review, Number 111, September-October 1978, pp. 25–36.

78.

|   |

For a guide see William C. Olson, ‘The Growth of the Discipline’, in Brian Porter (ed.), The Aberystwyth Papers: International Politics 1919–1969 (London: Oxford University Press, 1972), pp. 3–29.

79.

|   |

See W. A. Griswold, review of The Twenty Years’ Crisis, featured as a sales puff in the American edition of the volume which was published in 1964 by Harper & Row Publishers of New York.

80.

|   |

Letter from E. H. Carr to Mr Macmillan, 2 April 1948 (MAB).

81.

|   |

Letter from E. H. Carr to Mr Macmillan, 14 June 1948 (MAB).

82.

|   |

One of Carr’s strongest American defenders (who later helped set up the British Committee on the Theory of International Relations) was nonetheless compelled to criticize his work for its ‘Marxist orientation’. See Kenneth Thompson, Masters of International Thought (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1980), p. 77.

83.

|   |

See the first edition of Hans J. Morgenthau’s classic Power Among Nations: the Struggle for Power and Peace (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1948). In this Morgenthau recommends readers to look at The Twenty Years’ Crisis for the light it throws on ‘the intellectual problems to which the study of international politics give rise’. At another point he cites the same book as being one of a few that dealt seriously with the role of ‘political power’ in world affairs. Elsewhere he briefly mentions Carr’s views on ‘morality’, even though he does not happen to agree with them. See pp. 177, 475, 478, 481, 482, 483.

84.

|   |

R. B. J. Walker, ‘History and Structure in International Relations’, in James DerDerian (ed.), International Theory: Critical Investigations (Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1995), pp. 332–3.

85.

|   |

Compare the similarities between The Twenty Years’ Crisis with Hans J. Morgenthau, Scientific Man vs Power Politics (Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1946).

86.

|   |

Hans J. Morgenthau, ‘The Political Science of E. H. Carr’, World Politics, Volume I, No. 1, 1948, pp. 127–34. A shortened version of the same article was later reissued under the more pungent title, ‘The Surrender to the Immanence of Power: E. H. Carr’ in H. J. Morgenthau (ed.), Dilemmas of Politics (Chicago: Chicago University Press, 1962), pp. 350–7.

87.

|   |

See Chris Brown, Understanding International Relations (Basingstoke: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1997; 2nd edn, 2001), pp. 31–2.

88.

|   |

See the comment by Daniel H. Deudney, ‘Regrounding Realism: Anarchy, Security, and Changing Material Context’, Security Studies, Vol. 10, No. 1, Autumn 2000, p. 19.

89.

|   |

Whittle Johnston, ‘E. H. Carr’s Theory of International Relations: a Critique’, The Journal of Politics, Vol. 29, No. 4, November 1967, pp. 861–84.

90.

|   |

Robert Gilpin referred to Carr (alongside Thucydides and Machiavelli) as one of the ‘three great realist writers’. He later noted that he found in Carr’s work ‘one of the greatest inspiration for his own scribblings in the field’ and ‘incorporated Carr’s analysis of the relationship of international economic and politics into his own work’. See his ‘The Richness of the Tradition of Political Realism’ in Robert Keohane (ed.), Neorealism and its Critics (New York: Columbia University Press, 1986), pp. 306, 309. On Gilpin’s debt to Carr see his Global Political Economy: Understanding the International Economic Order (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2000), pp. 100–1, n.52.

91.

|   |

‘Carr’ also had ‘the distinction’, according to a British academic, of ‘writing one of the few books on international relations, which despite its subject matter, one might read for pleasure’. See Michael Nicholson, Formal Theories in International Relations (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1989), pp. 26–7, n.1.

92.

|   |

See Stanley Hoffman, ‘An American Social Science: International Relations’, Daedalus, Vol. 106, No. 3, Summer 1997, pp. 41–60

93.

|   |

Daniel Deudney notes that Carr managed to ignore the ‘early literature of geopolitics’ produced by German writers associated with the Institute of Geopolitics in Munich. See his ‘Geopolitics and Change’, in Michael Doyle and G. John Ikenberry (eds), New Thinking in International Relations Theory (Colorado: Westview Press, 1997), p. 51.

94.

|   |

See, for example, Steve Smith, ‘International Relations: still an American Social Science?’, British Journal of Politics and International Relations, Vol. 2, No. 3, October 2000, pp. 376–9.

95.

|   |

See Brian C. Schmidt, The Political Discourse of Anarchy: a Disciplinary History of International Relations.

96.

|   |

On the ways in which Carr was read or misread in the United States see the suggestive comments by James Der Derian, ‘A Reinterpretation of Realism’ in his International Theory: Critical Investigations, pp. 363–96 and Vendulka Kubalkova ‘The Twenty Years’ Catharsis: E. H. Carr and IR’ in Vendulka Kubalkova, Nicholas Onuf and Paul Kowert (eds), International Relations in a Constructed World (New York: M. E. Sharpe, 1998), pp. 25–57.

97.

|   |

See Joseph Grieco, ‘Realist International Theory and the Study of World Politics’, in Michael Doyle and G. John Ikenberry (eds), New Thinking in International Relations Theory (Colorado: Westview Press, 1997), p. 107. Grieco argues that Carr remains a realist because he argues that ‘states coexist in a context of international anarchy’ in the ‘shadow of war’ (p. 107). See also the ways in which Carr’s theory of power and peaceful change is employed by Randall L. Schweller and William C. Wohlforth, ‘Evaluating Realism in Response to the End of the Cold War’, Security Studies, Vol. 9, No. 3, Spring 2000, pp. 60–107.

98.

|   |

See Graham Evans, ‘All States are Equal but—’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 7, 1981, p. 62.

99.

|   |

J. D. B. Miller, ‘E. H. Carr: The Realist’s Realist’, The National Interest, Fall 1991, pp. 65–71.

100.

|   |

See John Rawls, The Law of Peoples (Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1999), p. 6 n.8, Peter Wilson, ‘E. H. Carr: the Revolutionist’s Realist’, Unpublished Ms, 2000, l6pp, and William C. Olson and A. J. R. Groom, International Relations: Then and Now: Origins and Trends in Interpretation (London: Routledge, 1991), p. 93.

101.

|   |

See Michael Doyle, ‘Peace, Liberty and Democracy: Realists and Liberals Contest a Legacy’, in Michael Cox, G. John Ikenberry and Takashi Inoguchi (eds), American Democracy Promotion: Impulses, Strategies, and Impacts (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000), pp. 23–7, and Michael Joseph Smith, Realist Thought from Weber to Kissinger (Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1986), p. 2.

102.

|   |

Justin Rosenberg, The Empire of Civil Society: a Critique of the Realist Theory of International Relations (London: Verso, 1994), pp. 9–37

103.

|   |

See Ken Booth, What is His Story? Remarks for the Roundtable, E. H. Carr – The Aberystwyth Years: 1936–1947. Unpublished Manuscript, 13 July 1997. Presented to E. H. Carr: A Critical Reassessment. An International Symposium.

104.

|   |

See, for example, his review of Hans J. Morgenthan’s book on American foreign policy published in The Listener, 15 May 1952.

105.

|   |

The manuscript by C. A. W. Manning was The Nature of International Society published in 1962 and reissued in 1975. Letter E. H. Carr to Macmillan Publishers, 23 January 1961 (MAB).

106.

|   |

See Brian Porter (ed.), The Aberystwyth Papers: International Politics, 1919–69.

107.

|   |

See Dr E. H. Carr (United Kingdom) ‘The Twenty Years’ Crisis’. Lecture delivered on 18 July 1957, NATO Unclassified, 18pp (CPB).

108.

|   |

The only positive comments that Carr ever uttered about international relations in Britain that I have been able to track down can be found in his ‘Academic Questions’, Times Literary Supplement, 16 April 1954.

109.

|   |

The letter was from Martin Wight and is quoted in Tim Dunne, Inventing International Society: a History of the English School (Basingstoke: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1998), p. 93.

110.

|   |

The term Hobbesian was, of course, used by Martin Wight to describe the ‘brilliant’ The Twenty Years’ Crisis in his ‘Western Values in International Relations’, in Herbert Butterfield and Martin Wight (eds), Diplomatic Investigations: Essays in the Theory in International Relations (New York: Columbia University Press, 1966), p. 121.

111.

|   |

Martin Wight ‘The Realist’s Utopia’, Observer, 21 July 1946, p. 3.

112.

|   |

Roger Epp, ‘Martin Wight: International Relations as a realm of persuasion’, in F. A. Beer and R. Hariman (eds), Post-realism: the Rhetorical Turn in International Relations (East Lansing, MI: Michigan State University Press, 1996), p. 122.

113.

|   |

See Martin Wight, Power Politics (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1979), pp. 19, 213.

114.

|   |

See Martin Wight, ‘An Anatomy of International Thought’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 13, 1987, p. 222.

115.

|   |

See Carr’s critique of Herbert Butterfield as an anti-progressive historian in his The New Society (London: Macmillan, 1951), pp. 4–9, 16.

116.

|   |

For Carr’s attacks on Butterfield see E. H. Carr, What Is History? (Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1961), pp. 19, 41–2, 51, 74, 121.

117.

|   |

For a sympathetic assessment of Butterfield see Ian Hall, ‘Historical Learning and Historical Thinking: Sir Herbert Butterfield and International Relations’, Review of International Relations, 2002.

118.

|   |

Herbert Butterfield, ‘What is History?’, The Cambridge Review, 2 December 1961.

119.

|   |

An important fact recalled by Ian Hall in his ‘Still the English patient? Closures and inventions in the English School’, International Affairs, Vol. 77, No. 3, 2001, p. 504.

120.

|   |

Apart from Carr, others not invited to attend the meetings of the British Committee included Harry Hinsley, then lecturer in History at Cambridge, and C. A. W. Manning, Montagu Burton Professor of International Relations at the LSE,1930–62.

121.

|   |

Quote from Kai Alderson and Andrew Hurrell (eds), Hedley Bull On International Society (Basingstoke: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 2000), p. 125.

122.

|   |

See Peter Wilson, ‘The Peculiar Realism of E. H. Carr’, Millennium, Vol. 30, No. 1, 2001, p. 125.

123.

|   |

See E. H. Carr, Nationalism and After, p. 42, n.1.

124.

|   |

Manning’s book was entitled The Nature of International Society and was finally published in 1962 and reissued by Macmillan in 1975. Carr knew and liked Manning and found him and his ideas to be both ‘original and stimulating’; but his basic argument about the existence of an ‘international society’ was quite simply wrong in his view. Carr wrote: ‘My fundamental criticism of this thesis is that the international game implied by it is in fact a creation of small and influential groups in the western world during the past 400 years, and there is no reason to suppose that it will survive the decline of these groups.’ He also added that Manning wrote in an ‘abstract, elusive, hair-splitting style’ and that the ‘manuscript scarcely’ contained ‘a proper name from beginning to end’. See letter from E. H. Carr to Macmillan Publishers, 23 January 1961 (CPB).

125.

|   |

Cited in letter from E. H. Carr to Stanley Hoffman, 30 September 1977.

126.

|   |

See Cecilia Lynch, ‘E. H. Carr, International Relations Theory and the Societal Origins of International Legal Norms’, Millennium, Vol. 23, No. 3, 1994, pp. 589–620.

127.

|   |

See Robert Jackson in American Political Science Review, Vol. 94, No. 3, September 2000, pp. 763–4.

128.

|   |

For an alternative view, see Tim Dunne, Inventing International Society, p. 13, and Charles Jones, ‘Christianity in the English School: Deleted but not Expunged’. Paper given at the International Studies Association, Annual Conference, Chicago, 21–4 February 2001, p. 3.

129.

|   |

The discussion about Carr’s relationship to the English School can be followed in the journal Cooperation and Conflict, Vol. 35, No. 2, June 2000, pp. 193–237, with contributions by Tonny Brems Knudsen, Samuel M. Makinda, Hidemi Suganami and Tim Dunne.

130.

|   |

See Robert W. Cox and Timothy J. Sinclair, Approaches to World Order (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, l996), p. 27.

131.

|   |

Robert W. Cox, Production Power and World Order: Social Forces in the Making of History (New York: Columbia University Press, 1987), p. 157.

132.

|   |

See, in particular, Graham Evans, ‘E. H. Carr and International Relations’, British Journal of International Studies, Vol. 1, No. 2, 1975, pp. 77–97.

133.

|   |

Robert W. Cox, Production, Power and World Order, pp. 49–50, 86, 91, 100, 117, 169, 400, 502.

134.

|   |

Andrew Linklater, ‘The Transformation of Political Community: E. H. Carr and Critical Theory and International Relations’, Review of International Studies, Vol. 23, 1997, pp. 321–8.

135.

|   |

Andrew Linklater, Beyond Realism and Marxism: Critical Theory and International Relations (London: Macmillan, 1990). See also his later The Transformation of Political Community: Ethical Foundations of the post-Westphalian Era (Cambridge: Polity Press, 1998).

136.

|   |

See Ken Booth, ‘Security and Self: Reflections of Falllen Realist’, in Keith Krause and Michael C. Williams (eds), Critical Security Studies (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1997) pp. 83–120.

137.

|   |

For an earlier discussion by Booth of Carr who recognized that all ‘sound political thought must be based on elements of reality and utopia’ see his ‘1931 + 50: It’s Later than we Think’, in David R. Jones (ed.) Soviet Armed Forces Review, Vol. 5 (Gulf Breeze FL: Academic International Press, 1981), pp. 31–49.

138.

|   |

Ken Booth, ‘Security in Anarchy: Utopian Realism in Theory and Practice’, International Affairs, Vol. 67, No. 3, 1991, pp. 527–45.

139.

|   |

Isaiah Berlin, ‘Mr Carr’s Big Batallions’, New Statesman, 5 January 1962.

140.

|   |

Charles Jones, E. H. Carr and International Relations: a Duty to Lie and Tim Dunne, Michael Cox and Ken Booth (eds), The Eighty Years’ Crisis: International Relations 1919–1999.

141.

|   |

Jonathan Haslam, The Vices of Integrity: E. H. Carr, 1892–1982.

142.

|   |

Michael Cox (ed.), E. H. Carr: a Critical Appraisal (Basingstoke: Macmilan Press – now Palgrave, 2000).

143.

|   |

Duncan S. A. Bell, ‘International Relations: the Dawn of a Historiographic Turn?’, British Journal of Politics and International Relations, Vol. 3, No. 1, April 2000, p. 122.

144.

|   |

Thucydides, History of the Peloponnesian Wars (New York: Penguin, 1972), I. 22.

145.

|   |

G. John Ikenberry, After Victory: Institutions, Strategic Restraint, and the Rebuilding of Order After Major Wars (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2000), p. 3.

146.

|   |

See Ian Clark, The Post-Cold War Order: the Spoils of Peace (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2000).

147.

|   |

See Alexander Wendt, The Social Theory of International Politics (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999), pp. 195–6.

148.

|   |

Francis Fukuyama, ‘The End of History’, The National Interest, Vol. 16, Summer 1989, pp. 3–18.

A Brief Guide to the Writings of E. H. Carr

E. H. Carr wrote so much on so many diverse subjects, over such a long period of time, and for so many different audiences, that it is not at all easy to situate him within any particular academic discipline. Indeed, in some ways it is not even accurate to call him an academic, given his many careers and interests; nor to be true to Carr’s own wishes should we even refer to him as a member of the ‘IR’ community. In fact, he did not much like the idea of international relations as a subject and said so on numerous occasions. Yet it is as the author of one of its classical foundational texts that he is perhaps best known today.

So how should we read Carr and make sense of The Twenty Years’ Crisis? One very obvious way of doing so is to get some idea of what he wrote and what he did over his whole life, spanning the period from 1916 – when he took up his position in the Foreign Office – to 1982 when he died at the age of 90. Indeed, it is crucial to do so, for only by setting his famous study within his larger oeuvre can we fully appreciate the true significance of The Twenty Years’ Crisis as one of several attempts made by Carr to make sense of a world turned upside down by one war and the threat and reality of another, the collapse of old economic certainties and the challenge posed by the Soviet Union – not in any military sense but as an ideological alternative. Martin Wight once observed that Carr’s The Twenty Years’ Crisis was the product of diseased times. It would be more accurate to say that all of his work is a response to truly revolutionary times.

The first 20 years of his active professional life, however, were spent within the cloistered confines of an elite British Foreign Office. From this privileged, and at times influential vantage point he studied and advised successive governments about the Russian revolution, the Versailles Peace Treaty, the formation and evolution of the League of Nations, the world depression, the rise of Hitler, and how Britain in the early stages of decline as he perceived it – ought to respond to the threat posed by Germany in the 1930s. The last issue in particular was of special concern to Carr. A close confidante to those within the British foreign policy establishment who had been keen to pursue a policy of de’tente with Hitler, he saw The Twenty Years’ Crisis not as an attempt to provide further justification for a strategy that had manifestly failed by the time the book was first published in November 1939 – the standard view – but as a retrospective critique of those who had palpably failed to do so before 1938. Certainly, without recognizing the very special relationship Carr enjoyed with at least some of those who wielded power and made policy, it is virtually impossible to understand how and why he wrote The Twenty Years’ Crisis, a work which was at once a fairly abstract discourse on the nature of international relations – his preferred title for the book was Utopia and Reality – and also a very direct intervention (admittedly after the policy of appeasement had been abandoned) into the key international debates of the day.

Carr, though, was no ordinary diplomat, and while still serving in the Foreign Office he became increasingly interested in Russian literary and revolutionary politics in general, and Karl Marx in particular – not exactly the normal topics of conversation within the British diplomatic corps. These formed the basis of four biographical studies written in the space of just six years, between 1931 and 1937, a remarkable output by any measure. These included Dostoevsky 1821–1881 (1931; 1949; London: Unwin, 1962), a political and psychological portrait of the great Russian novelist; The Romantic Exiles (1933; London: Serif, 1998), which examined the wonderful and bizarre world of Russian revolutionary exiles in Europe in the mid-nineteenth century; Karl Marx: a Story in Fanaticism (London: J. M. Dent, 1934), in which Carr looked critically at the life and works of what he called ‘this orderly German’; and Michael Bakunin (London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1937), a fascinating study of the Russian anarchist. It was not insignificant that Carr chose not to write about conventional figures, but rather those whom he later described as ‘living outside the charmed circle’. But it was not the scientific Marx who influenced him most (though he did influence Carr a good deal more than later commentators have recognized), but his immersion in the world of Russian nineteenth-century intellectuals, even those ‘who were not in any strict sense revolutionaries at all’. As he later confessed, it was when reading these writers and thinking about their world – one that was so different to his own – that he began to reflect critically about the ‘liberal moralistic ideology’ that had so far formed the ideological bedrock of his own outlook.

Carr thus left the Foreign Office in 1936 a very different person than when he had joined it 20 years earlier. But in the end, however, it was not so much his sympathy for Russian intellectuals but his desire to speak more freely about what he saw as the drift in British foreign policy that led him to resign from the Foreign Office in early 1936 and take up the Woodrow Wilson Chair in International Politics in Aberystwyth. Here he remained on and off until 1947, in the process writing several books, six of which were published by Macmillan: the biography of Michael Bakunin (1937), which was not a good seller; his textbook on the inter-war period, International Relations Since the Peace Treaties (1937; after 1947 International Relations Between The Wars, 1919–1939), which sold well; The Twenty Years’ Crisis (1939); Conditions of Peace (1942), perhaps his most trenchant statement about the world crisis, which also contains a powerful critique of liberal political economy; Nationalism and After (1945), in which he put forward his most radical thoughts to date on international security without the nation-state; and The Soviet Impact on the Western World (1946), which despite its pro-Soviet leanings (Stalin, he claimed, had placed ‘democracy at the forefront of allied war aims’) did contain some important insights about the ways in which the West had evolved since 1917 in direct response to the challenge posed by the USSR. His other works included his largely ignored but significant 1939 study entitled Britain: a Study of Foreign Policy from the Versailles Peace Treaty to the Outbreak of War (London: Longmans, Green & Co, 1939), and his early statement on the failure of the nation-state, The Future of Nations: Independence or Interdependence? (London: Kegan Paul, 1941). Three other studies also deserve brief mention here, all of which were composed after he had resigned from Aberystwyth: Studies in Revolution (1950), a series of 14 essays, most of which had first appeared in the Times Literary Supplement; The New Society (1951), in which he declared his faith in progress and defined freedom as ‘the opportunity for creative activity’; and German–Soviet Relations Between the Wars, 1919–1939 (1952), a standard diplomatic account of a crucial relationship.

As this prodigious output might suggest, Carr was not an average academic. The Wilson Chair moreover was not the standard academic posting and it left him free most of the time to pursue his other interests as a journalist, reviewer and highly active member of various discussion groups at Chatham House in London. Through this latter vehicle he also helped clarify his own ideas on two especially important problems – peaceful change and nationalism – both of which figure prominently in the final draft of The Twenty Years’ Crisis. He also managed to maintain very close contacts with those who remained at the heart of the British political class. It came as no great surprise, therefore, when he was asked to join the Ministry of Information in 1940 in order to be able to play his part in the war he had hoped Britain might have avoided (at least until 1938) by appeasing Germany. However, realizing that the post did not give him a sufficiently important platform from which to express his views, he decided to take up a position as Assistant Editor and leader writer with The Times. This was a critical move, and from this largely anonymous position he set out to shape the debates about the future of Britain and its position within the larger post-war world. Broadly progressive in politics with little faith left in the private enterprise system, Carr inevitably upset Conservatives on the Right. What upset them more, perhaps, was his continued advocacy of good relations with the Soviet Union, even after the war had come to an end and given way to a Cold War for which he largely (though not completely) blamed the West.

In 1945 Carr took a decision that was to determine the course of the rest of his life. Convinced now that the three most important events of the twentieth century were the Russian revolution of 1917, its entry into the war in 1941, and its emergence as some sort of ‘superpower’ by 1945, Carr turned his attention away from the world of international politics to write what he hoped would become the definitive history of the early Soviet Union. The final result was to be ten volumes spanning the period 1917–1929. Three dealt with the early years – The Bolshevik Revolution 1917–1923 (1950, 1952, 1953), one with the transition from Lenin to Stalin – The Interregnum 1923–1924 (1954), three with the middle period of the 1920s – Socialism In One Country, 1924–1926 (1958, 1959, 1964), and another three with the new system in formation – The Foundations of a Planned Economy, 1926–1929 (1969, 1971 and 1978), two of which he co-authored with R. W. Davies (all London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave). He also published three related volumes: The Russian Revolution from Lenin to Stalin, 1917–1929 (1979), The Twilight of the Comintern, 1930–1935 (1982), and The Comintern and the Spanish Civil War (1983) (all London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave). Olympian was the word most frequently used to describe the achievement, and Olympian it most certainly was, especially when we consider that the first of these many volumes was not published until 1950 when Carr was already 58. Little wonder that even he at times felt that the whole project had got completely out of hand.

If Carr had ever been asked what his most important contribution to human knowledge had been, he certainly would not have replied The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Nor would he even have included his hugely influential but relatively short book on the study of history, What Is History? (London: Macmillan Press – now Palgrave, 1961), which went on to sell over a quarter of a million copies in the English language, as well as being translated into 25 others, including Russian and Georgian in 1998, Lithuanian and Korean in 2000, and Macedonian in 2001. First, he would have mentioned his magnum opus on Soviet Russia, a study that dealt in minute detail with the ways in which economic and international realities in the end modified and altered the high ideals of its revolutionary founders. Second, he would have cited (and did in 1980) his now out-of-print and almost impossible to obtain biography of the anarchist Michael Bakunin – a utopian dreamer if ever there was one, whose love of liberty if not understanding of the ‘real’ world inspired Carr to write about him with such great sympathy.

About The Twenty Years’ Crisis he seemed to have no strong opinions at all, even though the complex relationship between the world as it is and the world as it might be – or, as Carr might have put it, between reality and utopia – forms the philosophical foundations upon which it is constructed. But Carr never appeared to see it as anything but a particular type of book written under very peculiar and extreme circumstances. As he noted in the preface to the 1981 printing of the volume, by the end of the war The Twenty Years’ Crisis ‘was already a period piece and such it remains’. It might ‘perhaps retain a wider significance’, he continued, but one should never forget that it was first and foremost ‘an attempt to navigate then relatively unchartered waters’ and should be judged in those terms. Whether or not he succeeded in his navigational efforts remains an open question. The Twenty Years’ Crisis, after all, was never an easy book, nor did it ever lack for critics. Its influence, however, can hardly be denied. Reprinted four times within six months of its publication in late 1939, it went through no less than 17 reprintings between 1946 and 1984. By 2000 it had also been translated into seven languages, including Japanese, German, Portuguese, Greek, Swedish, Spanish and Korean, thus making it one of the best known books on international relations in the world.

Glossary of Names

Sir Norman Angell (1873–1967)

British economist and worker for international peace who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1933. Angell is best known for his book The Great Illusion (1909), which marked a turning point for peace theory by seeking to refute the argument that conquest and war brought a nation great economic advantage. Angell attempted to show the opposite – that war could never profit anyone. In The Twenty Years’ Crisis Carr attacked Angell for believing that war arose as a result of ‘a lack of understanding’. Angell in turn thought Carr’s book to be ‘completely mischievous — a piece of sophisticated moral nihilism’, and later went on to strongly criticize it in his Why Freedom Matters, published in 1940. In this he referred to Carr, amongst other things, as being one of ‘Hitler’s intellectual allies in Britain’.

Arthur Balfour (1848–1940)

British Conservative prime minister from 1902–05. Balfour was brought into the coalition Cabinet as foreign secretary in 1916, and was a member of the British delegation at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919.

Edvard Benes (1884–1948)

Statesman, foreign minister, and founder of modern Czechoslovakia who forged its Western-oriented foreign policy between the First and Second World Wars but was forced to capitulate to Hitler’s demands during the Czech crisis in 1938. As foreign minister he represented his country at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919, and championed the League of Nations throughout the inter-war period. He was to become president of Czechoslovakia in 1935.

Jeremy Bentham (1748–1832)

Economist, political and legal philosopher and social reformer, Bentham was the principal exponent of utilitarianism – a philosophy expressed in the idea that the best outcome in any society was that which provided the ‘greatest good for the greatest number’. Bentham, according to Carr, took the eighteenth-century doctrine of reason and refashioned it to the needs of the nineteenth century. He also advocated a whole raft of social reforms, many of which were later to be pursued by John Stuart Mill, one of Bentham’s pupils. Carr saw Bentham as one of the founders of modern liberal ‘utopianism’, which found its early twentieth-century expression in Wilsonianism in the US.

William jennings Bryan (1860–1925)

American politician and Woodrow Wilson’s Secretary of State who firmly believed in arbitration to prevent war. An avowed pacifist, he eventually resigned after Wilson’s second note to Germany in 1915 protesting about the sinking of the Lusitania.

N. M. Butler (1862–1947)

American educator, publicist and political figure who shared the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1931 and served as president of Columbia University from 1901 to 1945. Butler was a champion of international understanding, helping to establish the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, of which he was a trustee and later president (1925–45). In 1930 he declared that the next generation would ‘see a constantly increasing respect for Cobden’s principles of free trade and peace’, a view Carr strongly disparaged.

Edmund Burke (1729–97)

Best known for his critique of the revolution in France, Reflections on the French Revolution. Burke, despite his Whig sympathies and earlier support for the Americans in the War of Independence, has come to be seen as the principal exponent of Conservative philosophy.

Lord Cecil (1864–1958)

British statesman and winner of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1937, one of the principal draftsmen of the League of Nations Covenant in 1919, and one of the most loyal workers for the League until its supersession by the United Nations in 1945. Carr attacked him in The Twenty Years’ Crisis, among other things, for his na tve faith in the League of Nations Covenant and belief in international conciliation.

Neville Chamberlain (1869–1940)

British Conservative prime minister (1937–1940) who was to be vilified by many for his policy of appeasement towards Nazi Germany. In particular he is remembered for the agreement he concluded with Hitler at Munich in 1938. He was harried by anti-appeasers on the Conservative benches. In September 1939 he was forced to declare war, but was ill-suited for the task ahead of him. A parliamentary revolt ensured his resignation in 1940. Six months later he died a broken man. Carr at the time was altogether more generous towards Chamberlain than later critics. Thus when Chamberlain became prime minister in May 1937, Carr wrote two years later in his Britain: a Study of Foreign Policy from Versailles to the Outbreak of War that Chamberlain was a ‘realist’ who ‘perceived more clearly than any other political leader the growing danger of a policy of words not matched by deeds’. In The Twenty Years’ Crisis Carr praised the Munich Agreement signed by Chamberlain and Hitler on 29 September 1938 as being ‘the nearest approach in recent years to the settlement of a major international issue by the procedure of peaceful change’.

Winston Churchill (1874–1965)

Best known for guiding Britain to victory during the Second World War from 1940–45. However, Churchill had a tumultuous political career long before that. He served as a Liberal minister under Asquith and Lloyd George, and was First Lord of the Admiralty when the First World War broke out. He served in several different ministerial positions during the coalition governments, and went on to become Chancellor of the Exchequer from 1924–29. He was a backbencher throughout the 1930s, though he became an increasingly vociferous opponent of appeasement towards Nazi Germany. The outbreak of the Second World War led to his being returned to the Admiralty, to become prime minister in 1940. Strongly criticized by Carr during the war for having no programme for post-war economic reform, Churchill later attacked Carr and The Times (for which Carr worked during the Second World War) for being critical of British foreign policy in Greece. Carr in turn attacked Churchill’s famous ‘Iron Curtain’ speech made at Fulton, Missouri, in the March of 1946.

Richard Cobden (1804–65)

British politician known for his successful fight for the repeal of the Corn Laws and his defence of free trade. With John Bright, he believed that free trade would result in the reduction of armaments and the promotion of international peace. Theoretically he had influence on the post-First World War ‘utopians’ such as Nicholas Murray Butler whom Carr criticised in The Twenty Years’ Crisis.

Confucius (551–479 BC)

Chinese philosopher who emphasized the importance of moral values in all social and political order. He believed that the hierarchical structure oftraditional Chinese society was natural, though he argued that membership of the ruling class should be moral rather than hereditary.

Peter Drucker (1909-)

American management consultant, educator and author whose later writings provided much of the philosophical and practical underpinning of the modern business corporation. In the 1930s, however, Drucker was far from the conservative he was later to become, and was admired by Carr for having written The End of Economic Man.

Anthony Eden (1897–1977)

Rapidly promoted through the Conservative ranks during the 1930s, he became foreign secretary in 1935. He resigned three years later in opposition to Chamberlain’s policy of appeasement. Eden was brought back into the Cabinet at the outbreak of war in 1939 as dominions secretary, and once again became foreign secretary after Chamberlain’s resignation in 1940. Eventually he became prime minister in 1955. Carr worked closely with Eden while he was still in the Foreign Office until his own resignation in early 1936.

Friedrich Engels (1820–95)

Mainly remembered as a life-long friend, collaborator and financial supporter of Karl Marx. Like Marx, Engels was critical of earlier Socialists such as Robert Owen, Saint-Simon and Fourier, and opposed them for their ‘utopianism’. Carr, it seems, borrowed the notion and transplanted it into his own critique of those early writers on international relations who in his view were ‘utopian’ too.

T. H. Green (1836–82)

English political philosopher who, according to Carr, ‘tempered the doctrines’ of Hegel with British nineteenth-century liberalism. Carr also quoted him as one of those who accepted that the morality of individuals can only be social morality – and social morality implies duty to fellow members of all other communities, including the larger international community. But, as Carr asked of Green in The Twenty Years’ Crisis, ‘In what sense can we find a basis for international morality by positing a society of states?’

Hegel (1770–1831)

German philosopher who developed a dialectical scheme that emphasized the progress of history and ideas from thesis to antithesis, and thence to a higher and richer synthesis. He was one of the great modern creators of a philosophical system that influenced the development of Marxism in particular. Carr had a high opinion of Hegel, whose work he had read in the early 1930s in preparation for his earlier books: The Romantic Exiles (1933), Karl Marx (1934) and Michael Bakunin (1937). Carr saw Hegel – along with Marx – as belonging to the ‘historical school’ of realists; that is, those who championed the view that no ethical standards are applicable to relations between states, an idea that certainly influenced him in writing The Twenty Years’ Crisis.

Leonard Hobhouse (1864–1929)

Political philosopher and activist, a crucial figure in the emergence of ‘social liberalism’, which justified increased state intervention as necessary for the achievement of both social and individual goods, as well as social order. Hobhouse taught at the London School of Economics and had an influence on a number of Liberal reformers whom Carr criticized in The Twenty Years’ Crisis.

Cordell Hull (1871–1955)

F. D. Roosevelt’s secretary of state from 1934–44. Famous in the 1930s for his efforts to maintain some form of open trading system, he was quoted as once saying ‘that when goods crossed frontiers, armies didn’t’.

Immanuel Kant (1724–1804)

German philosopher of the idealist school. In terms of international relations, he argued for a ‘league of nations’ to enforce the natural, derivable and international law, envisaging a decline in the power of individual states as that of the universal authority came to be established. Kantianism is identified in modern international relations as standing in opposition to state-centric realism.

John Maynard Keynes (1883–1946)

Liberal British economist who first became famous for his The Economic Consequences of the Peace – a savage attack on the Versailles Peace Treaty of 1919 with which Carr fully agreed. Keynes went on in the 1930s to write his General Theory, which proposed state intervention to overcome large-scale unemployment.

Sir Hersch Lauterpacht (1870–1924)

British international lawyer of the Grotian school, criticized by Carr for his belief that the events of the 1930s were only a temporary regression of international order that would eventually be overcome.

Lenin (1870–1924)

Leader of the Bolshevik revolution for whom Carr came to have some regard – both as a state builder and a political theorist of revolution. Interestingly, Carr quotes Lenin over half a dozen times in The Twenty Years’ Crisis, often agreeing with what he has to say. He quotes Lenin on law. Lenin insists that law does not reflect any fixed ethical standard but is rather ‘the formulation, the registration of power relations, an expression of the will of the ruling class’.

Maxim Litvinov (1876–1951)

Soviet diplomat and commissar of foreign affairs (1930–39) who was a prominent advocate of world disarmament and of collective security with the Western powers against Nazi Germany before the Second World War.

David Lloyd George (1863–1945)

Born in Wales, Lloyd George became prime minister in the midst of war in 1916, and went on to lead Britain to victory. He subsequently headed the British delegation at the Paris Peace Conference, and continued as prime minster until 1922 when the Conservatives withdrew from the governing coalition.

John Locke (1632–1704)

English philosopher widely regarded as one of the fathers of the Enlightenment and as a key figure in the development of liberalism. Locke was mainly concerned with the proper extent of freedom and religious toleration. He believed that the political authority’s fundamental role was to protect property. Locke defended the concept of private property on the grounds that it was legitimated when it was mixed with the individual’s labour.

Niccoló Machiavelli (1469–1527)

Florentine political adviser and historian. In his best known works The Prince and the Discourses, he outlined a theory of raison d’ètat where he seemed to be suggesting that the use of any technique was permissible as long as it achieved the desired end. The term ‘Machiavellian’ later entered the world’s language to designate cynicism, manipulation and duplicity. Carr was much influenced by Machiavelli and indeed used him as the basis for constructing his own realist critique of what he termed ‘utopianism’. Carr described him as ‘the first important political realist’.

Karl Mannheim (1893–1947)

Hungarian sociologist who made an important contribution to the sociology of knowledge. Like Marx, Mannheim wanted to relate belief systems that emerged in political historical periods to the socio-economic and political conditions that seemed to stimulate and sustain them. Unlike Marx, though, Mannheim believed utopianism to be a forward-looking and visionary tendency that was capable of breaking out of the constraints of the existing social order and could thus point to the possibility of real change in the historical process. The influence of Mannheim’s Ideology and Utopia on Carr was immense. Not only did Carr want to call his own book Utopia and Reality rather than The Twenty Years’ Crisis (this was his publisher’s suggestion), he also used Mannheim’s central theoretical claim about the relativity of knowledge as the basis of his own thinking about ideas.

Charles Manning

Montagu Burton Professor of International Relations at the London School of Economics between 1930 and 1962 – and a friend of Carr’s with whom Carr worked quite closely in the 1930s when developing his own views on peaceful change. Manning read drafts of The Twenty Years’ Crisis, though he was by no means in agreement with all of its central claims. Carr in turn did not share Manning’s views about the existence of a larger ‘international society of states’.

Alfred Marshall (1842–1924)

British economist, one of the chief founders of the school of English neoclassical economics. Marshall is often considered to have been in the line of descent of the great British economists – Adam Smith, David Ricardo and J. S. Mill.

Karl Marx (1818–83)

German philosopher, sociologist, socialist and economist. His influence right across the social sciences has been immense. Fundamentally, Marx was a historical materialist, believing that history could be studied as a scientific process. Marx argued that societies would progress through several stages of socio-economic development. Capitalism was the highest stage, though Marx believed that it contained its own contradictions that would lead it to implode, to be replaced by socialism. Carr was not a Marxist and disagreed with both Marx’s labour theory of value and his idea of the proletariat as a revolutionary class. Nonetheless, Carr borrowed heavily from Marx’s historical sociology and from his various insights about the failure of capitalism as a system in the inter-war period. Two years before his death, in 1980, Carr confessed that The Twenty Years’ Crisis ‘was not exactly a Marxist work’, but was ‘strongly impregnated with Marxist ways of thinking applied to international affairs’. Carr often contrasted Marx the ‘realist’ with the anarchist Bakunin as ‘utopian’.

James Mill (1773–1836)

Liberal thinker, mainly remembered now for the education of his son, John Stuart Mill, and his life-long friendship with Jeremy Bentham.

John Stuart Mill (1806–73)

Liberal philosopher and political activist, strongly influenced by the work of Bentham. However, Mill was to differ from Bentham in his belief in individual personal character and self-regarding personal conduct. Mill was also the leading Liberal feminist of his day.

Reinhold Niebuhr (1892–1971)

American theologian and political scientist, who in the 1930s at least employed critical Marxist categories to understand the modern world. Carr always remained a warm admirer of Niebuhr and was strongly influenced by his 1932 study Moral Man and Immoral Society. The Twenty Years’ Crisis is littered with various hard-hitting quotes from Niebuhr about the hypocrisies of the privileged and the exercise of power. Later Niebuhr moved away from his earlier attachment to Marxism but he continued to have a huge influence in the US in the post-war period.

Robert Owen (1771–1858)

British social reformer whose ideas contributed to the development of nineteenth-century socialism. Owen was essentially a communitarian Socialist who believed that the amelioration of social conditions and intelligent organization of the labour process were the necessary means for the creation of greater equality and justice. Like Engels, Carr regarded him as a utopian Socialist whose contribution to nineteenth-century thought was not his realistic analysis of society but his desire and aspiration to change reality.

Plato (427–347 BC)

Greek philosopher whose most important treatise, the Republic, espoused Plato’s view of the ideal society. Carr saw him as an early example of a type of utopian who proposed what he called in The Twenty Years’ Crisis ‘highly imaginative solutions whose relation to existing facts was one of flat negation’.

Jean-jacques Rousseau (1712–78)

Moral, political and educational philosopher whose political ideas are exemplified in his Social Contract. His main concern was liberty, and he believed that it could be attained through ‘general will’. This is the will of each individual in favour of the good of the whole community, and is superior to his own particular interests.

Sir john Simon (1873–1954)

Liberal politician who served as foreign secretary from 1931–35. He was Chancellor of the Exchequer in Neville Chamberlain’s government from 1937–40, and closely identified with the policy of appeasement towards Nazi Germany.

Saint-Simon (1760–1825)

French social theorist and one of the chief founders of Christian socialism. In his major work, Nouveau Christianisme (1825), he proclaimed a brotherhood of man that must accompany the scientific organization of industry and society. Carr regarded Saint-Simon as another important example of a utopian socialist who aspired to change everything without first having provided a realistic analysis of the world.

Adam Smith (1723–90)

Scottish philosopher and founder of classical economics. In his work, Smith argued in his famous The Wealth of Nations that the individual’s pursuit of private gain would, unintentionally through the ‘invisible hand’, benefit the whole of society. He also described the importance of the division of labour. Carr viewed Smith’s particular brand of laissez-faire economics as being responsible for popularizing the doctrine of the ‘harmony of interests’.

Jan Smuts (1870–1950)

Smuts fought against the British during the Boer War but subsequently became a firm supporter of the Union of South Africa that was established in 1910. He resisted calls for neutrality during the First World War and served in the British army. In 1917 he became a member of the British War Cabinet. Following the war he became prime minister until 1924, and was active in South African politics throughout the inter-war period, becoming prime minister again at the outbreak of the Second World War.

Sophocles (496–406 BC)

One of the three great tragic playwrights of classical Greece, ranking with Aeschylus and Euripides. He wrote some 123 dramas, only 7 of which have survived.

Stoics

The Stoics taught that material possessions were of no importance whatsoever for a man’s happiness. The basis of human happiness, they believed, was to live ‘in agreement’ with oneself, a statement that was later replaced by the formula ‘to live in agreement with nature’. The only real good for man is the possession of virtue; everything else (wealth or poverty, health or illness, life or death) is of little consequence.

William Taft (1857–1930)

Republican president of the US from 1909–13, Taft encouraged ‘dollar diplomacy’ abroad, relying on trade rather than military power to spread influence. However, he is mainly remembered for splitting the Republican Party when his former friend and predecessor, Teddy Roosevelt, decided to run against him in 1912 as a Progressive, splitting the Republican vote and allowing Woodrow Wilson to come to office.

Arnold Toynbee (1889–1975)

British historian, best known for his study of the rise and fall of civilizations over the course of history. He concluded that civilisations rose by responding successfully to challenges under the leadership of creative minorities composed of elite leaders. Civilizations declined when their leaders stopped responding creatively, and the civilizations declined and died. In the 1930s he exercised great influence through Chatham House – where he was director of studies from 1924–54 – and through its annual Survey of International Affairs, which he wrote single-handedly. A liberal internationalist and opponent of appeasement, Carr attacked him frequently in The Twenty Years’ Crisis. Toynbee later argued that ‘Carr is the consummate debunker who was debunked by the war itself’.

Woodrow Wilson (1856–1924)

Democratic president of the US from 1913–21. Mainly remembered for taking his country into the First World War in 1917. Wilson enunciated ‘Fourteen Points’ for achieving peace and led the American delegation at the Paris Peace Conference in 1919, at which he attempted to realize his vision of a new international order. While failing to achieve everything he wanted, his main objective of establishing a League of Nations did come into being, though the Senate vetoed the possibility of American participation in the organization. Carr was a major critic of Wilson on two counts: first he opposed what he saw as Wilson’s indiscriminate use of the slogan of the right of self-determination, which he regarded as economically problematic and politically destabilizing in the inter-war period; second, he saw Wilson as the quintessential moralist in politics who used fine-sounding slogans as a means of advancing American power in the world. On one level The Twenty Years’ Crisis can be read as an extended attack on Wilson and Wilsonianism – this in spite of the fact that Carr held the Woodrow Wilson Chair in International Politics at Aberystwyth from 1936–47.

Sir Alfred Zimmern (1879–1957)

First holder of the Woodrow Wilson Chair at the University of Wales, Aberystwyth, in 1919. Zimmern was a classicist who wrote several books in the inter-war period on international affairs, his best known being The League of Nations and the Rule of Law (1936). Carr and Zimmern stood at opposite ends of the theoretical and political spectrum. Carr was a radical, increasingly critical of the League of Nations, who attacked the Liberal Zimmern in The Twenty Years’ Crisis for failing to grasp the deeper cause of the inter-war crisis. Zimmern was a ‘cautious idealist’, who saw Carr as ‘a thorough-going relativist with no moral compass to guide him’.

Chronology

1919

|   |

Jan. 8

|   |

Opening of the Paris Peace Conference under the Chairmanship of Georges Clemenceau.

June 28

|   |

German representatives sign the Peace Treaty in the Hall of Mirrors at the Palace of Versailles.

Nov. 19

|   |

US Senate votes against ratification of the Treaty of Versailles, thereby leaving the US outside the League of Nations.

1920

|   |

Jan. 10

|   |

Ratification of the Treaty of Versailles brings the League of Nations into existence, with 29 initial members (out of 32 Allied signatures to the Versailles Treaty).

Jan. 16

|   |

US Senate votes against joining the League of Nations.

Feb. 26

|   |

In accordance with the Treaty of Versailles, the League of Nations takes over the Saar area between France and Germany; France takes control of the Saar’s coal deposits.

March 19

|   |

US Senate rejects the Versailles Treaty.

April 6–May 17

|   |

While German troops are suppressing a rebellion in the Ruhr (a demilitarized area), French troops occupy Frankfurt, Darmstadt, and Hanau until German forces have withdrawn.

April 25

|   |

Supreme Allied Council disposes territories formerly in the Ottoman Empire: it assigns mandates over Mesopotamia and Palestine to Britain, and over Syria and the Lebanon to France.

Nov. 15

|   |

Danzig (modern Gdansk) is proclaimed a free city.

1921

|   |

Jan. 6

|   |

End of Russian civil war, with victory to the Bolsheviks.

Jan. 24–29

|   |

Paris Conference fixes Germany’s reparation payments.

March 8

|   |

French troops occupy Du sseldorf and other towns in the Ruhr because of Germany’s failure to make preliminary reparations payment.

April 27

|   |

Reparations Commission fixes Germany’s liability at 132,000 million gold Marks.

May 6

|   |

Peace treaty signed between Germany and Russia.

Sept. 30

|   |

French troops evacuate the Ruhr.

Nov. 12-Feb. 6 1922

|   |

Washington conference on disarmament.

Dec. 29

|   |

US, British Empire, France, Italy and Japan sign Washington Treaty to limit naval armaments.

1922

|   |

April 16

|   |

Rapallo Treaty between Germany and Russia: Germany recognizes Russia as ‘a great power’ and both sides waive reparations claims; the Treaty leads to the resumption of diplomatic and trade relations, and to co-operation between the two countries’ armies.

Oct. 28

|   |

In Italy, Fascists march on Rome, leading to Mussolini forming a government composed of Liberals and Nationalists, as well as Fascists, at the King’s invitation on 31 October.

1923

|   |

Jan. 11

|   |

As a result of Germany’s failure to meet reparations payments, French and Belgian troops occupy the Ruhr; Germans respond with passive resistance and sabotage; the occupiers make arrests and deportations, and cut off the Rhineland from the rest of Germany.

Nov. 8–9

|   |

The ‘Munich Putsch’: Adolf Hitler and the National Socialists attempt a coup d’état in Munich.

1924

|   |

Jan. 21

|   |

Death of Soviet leader Lenin. Stalin takes over.

July 16

|   |

At London conference on reparations, the Dawes Plan, which removes reparations from the sphere of political controversy, is approved.

Aug. 16

|   |

French delegates at London conference agree to evacuate the Ruhr within a year.

1925

|   |

Oct. 5–16

|   |

Locarno Conference discusses the question of a security pact and strikes a balance between French and German interests by drafting treaties (a) guaranteeing the French-German and Belgian-German frontiers; (b) between Germany and France, Belgium, Czechoslovakia and Poland respectively; (c) regarding a mutual guarantee between France, Czechoslovakia and Poland. Britain is involved in the guarantee of Franco-Belgian-German frontiers but not in the arrangements in Eastern Europe.

Dec. 1

|   |

Locarno treaties signed in London.

1926

|   |

Sept. 8

|   |

Germany is admitted into the League of Nations.

1927

|   |

Stalin consolidates his power in Soviet Russia, and in China the first revolution is crushed.

1928

|   |

The Kellogg-Briand Pact outlawing war and providing for pacific settlement of disputes is signed in Paris by 65 states, including the US and the USSR.

1929

|   |

June 7

|   |

Young Committee reviewing German reparations payments recommends that Germany should pay annuities, secured on mortgage of German railways, to an international bank until 1988.

Aug. 6–13

|   |

At a Reparations Conference at the Hague, Germany accepts the Young Plan; Allies agree to evacuate the Rhineland by June 1930.

Oct. 24–29

|   |

Crashes in share values on Wall Street stock market, New York, starting with ‘Black Thursday’ and continuing (after closure of the market from noon on 24 October until 28 October) on ‘Black Monday’ (28 October) and ‘Black Tuesday’ (29 October). Leads to the cessation of American loans to Europe.

1931

|   |

Sept. 18

|   |

Japanese invasion of Manchuria.

1933

|   |

Jan. 30

|   |

Adolf Hitler is appointed Chancellor of Germany; his cabinet includes only two Nazis, Herman Goering (Minister without Portfolio) and Wilhelm Frick (Minister of the Interior). Franz von Papen is Vice-chancellor, Constantin von Neurath foreign minister.

March 4

|   |

Inauguration of F. D. Roosevelt; Cordell Hull is appointed Secretary of State.

March 27

|   |

Japan announces that it will leave the League of Nations (effective from 1935).

Oct. 14

|   |

Germany withdraws from the League of Nations and its Disarmament Conference.

1934

|   |

July 25

|   |

Engelbert Dollfuss, Chancellor of Austria, is murdered in an attempted Nazi coup d’état.

Sept. 18

|   |

USSR is admitted into the League of Nations.

1935

|   |

Jan. 13

|   |

Plebiscite in the Saarland: 90.8 per cent of voters favour incorporation into Germany.

March 16

|   |

Germany repudiates disarmament clauses of the Versailles Treaty and introduces conscription.

May 2

|   |

France-USSR treaty of mutual assistance for five years.

May 16

|   |

USSR-Czechoslovakia pact of mutual assistance.

July 25–Aug. 20

|   |

Meeting of the Third International (Soviet-controlled international Communist organization) declares that Communists in democratic countries should support their governments against Fascist states.

Oct. 2

|   |

Italy invades Ethiopia.

Oct. 7

|   |

Following Italy’s invasion of Ethiopia, the League of Nations Council declares and denounces Italy as the aggressor.

Oct. 19

|   |

League of Nations imposes sanctions against Italy.

1936

|   |

Jan. 6-March 25

|   |

Resumption of London Naval Conference: Japan withdraws on 15 January because other countries refuse to accept its demand for a common upper limit on naval strength.

March 7

|   |

German troops occupy the demilitarized zone of the Rhineland, thereby violating the Treaty of Versailles.

July 17

|   |

Army mutiny in Spanish Morocco, led by Franco, to uphold religion and traditional values; other mutinies occur throughout Spain, thereby starting the Spanish Civil War.

Nov. 1

|   |

Following the visit of Italian Foreign Minister Ciano to Berlin, Italian Prime Minister Benito Mussolini proclaims the Rome-Berlin Axis.

Nov. 25

|   |

Germany and Japan sign Anti-Comintern Pact; the countries agree to work together against international communism; Germany also recognizes Japan’s regime in Manchuria.

1937

|   |

May 28

|   |

On Stanley Baldwin’s retirement, Neville Chamberlain forms a National Government, with Sir John Simon as Chancellor of the Exchequer and Anthony Eden as Foreign Secretary.

July 7

|   |

In China, incident at Marco Polo Bridge, southeast of Beijing, is followed by Japanese invasion of northeast China.

July 17

|   |

Naval agreements between Britain and Germany, and Britain and the USSR.

Nov. 6

|   |

Italy joins German-Japanese Anti-Comintern Pact.

Nov. 17–21

|   |

British cabinet minister Lord Halifax meets Adolf Hitler to attempt peaceful settlement of the Sudeten problem.

Dec. 11

|   |

Italy withdraws from the League of Nations.

1938

|   |

Feb. 20

|   |

British Foreign Secretary Anthony Eden resigns in protest at Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain’s priorities in foreign affairs. Chamberlain had declined President Roosevelt’s suggestion of a conference on international relations and was determined to obtain an agreement with Italy; Eden is succeeded on 25 February by Lord Halifax.

Feb. 21

|   |

Winston Churchill leads an outcry in the House of Commons against Chamberlain and the following day 25 members of the administration vote against the government in a censure motion.

March 12

|   |

German troops enter Austria, which the next day is declared part of the German Reich.

Sept. 15

|   |

British Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain visits Adolf Hitler at Berchtesgaden; Hitler states his determination to annex the Sudetenland in Czechoslovakia on the principle of self-determination.

Sept. 29–30

|   |

The Munich Conference, when Chamberlain, French Prime Minister E– douard Daladier, Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini agree to Germany’s military occupation of the Sudetenland, while the remaining frontiers of Czechoslovakia are guaranteed; Germany becomes the dominant power in Europe and both the Little Entente and the French system of alliances in Eastern Europe are shattered; on his return to London, Chamberlain declares that he has bought ‘peace with honour. I believe it is peace in our time’.

1939

|   |

March 15

|   |

German troops occupy Bohemia and Moravia in Czechoslovakia; Hitler makes a triumphal entry into Prague in the evening; the region becomes a protectorate ruled by Constantin von Neurath.

March 16

|   |

Slovakia is placed under German ‘protection’, while Hungary annexes Ruthenia (formerly part of Czechoslovakia).

March 21

|   |

Germany demands of Poland that Germany should acquire the Free City of Danzig and routes through the ‘Polish corridor’ (which provides Poland with access to the Baltic); Poland rejects the demands.

March 28

|   |

In the Spanish Civil War, Madrid surrenders to nationalists; remaining republican areas surrender the next day, ending the war.

March 28

|   |

Adolf Hitler denounces the non-aggression pact with Poland (of January 1934).

March 31

|   |

Britain and France pledge to support Poland in any attack on Polish independence (pact of mutual assistance agreed on 6 April).

April 18

|   |

USSR proposes triple alliance with Britain and France.

April 28

|   |

Hitler denounces 1935 British-German naval agreement and repeats demands on Poland.

May 22

|   |

Hitler and Mussolini sign ten-year military alliance (the ‘Pact of Steel’).

Aug. 23

|   |

Nazi-Soviet Pact; the parties agree not to fight each other; secret protocols provide for the partition of Poland and for the USSR to operate freely in the Baltic States, Finland, and Bessarabia.

Aug. 25

|   |

British-Polish treaty of mutual assistance signed in London.

Sept. 1

|   |

Germany invades Poland and annexes Danzig; Italy declares neutrality.

Sept. 3

|   |

Britain and France declare war on Germany, following Germany’s failure to reply to ultimata on Poland; Australia and New Zealand also declare war.

CHAPTER FOUR

The Harmony of Interests

The utopian synthesis

No political society, national or international, can exist unless people submit to certain rules of conduct. The problem why people should submit to such rules is the fundamental problem of political philosophy. The problem presents itself just as insistently in a democracy as under other forms of government and in international as in national politics; for such a formula as ‘the greatest good of the greatest number’ provides no answer to the question why the minority, whose greatest good is ex hypothesi not pursued, should submit to rules made in the interest of the greatest number. Broadly speaking, the answers given to the question fall into two categories, corresponding to the antithesis, discussed in a previous chapter, between those who regard politics as a function of ethics and those who regard ethics as a function of politics.

Those who assert the primacy of ethics over politics will hold that it is the duty of the individual to submit for the sake of the community as a whole, sacrificing his own interest to the interest of others who are more numerous, or in some other way more deserving. The ‘good’ which consists in self-interest should be subordinated to the ‘good’ which consists in loyalty and self-sacrifice for an end higher than self-interest. The obligation rests on some kind of intuition of what is right and cannot be demonstrated by rational argument. Those, on the other hand, who assert the primacy of politics over ethics, will argue that the ruler rules because he is the stronger, and the ruled submit because they are the weaker. This principle is just as easily applicable to democracy as to any other form of government. The majority rules because it is stronger, the minority submits because it is weaker. Democracy, it has often been said, substitutes the counting of heads for the breaking of heads. But the substitution is merely a convenience, and the principle of the two methods is the same. The realist, therefore, unlike the intuitionist, has a perfectly rational answer to the question why the individual should submit. He should submit because otherwise the stronger will compel him; and the results of compulsion are more disagreeable than those of voluntary submission. Obligation is thus derived from a sort of spurious ethic based on the reasonableness of recognizing that might is right.

Both these answers are open to objection. Modern man, who has witnessed so many magnificent achievements of human reason, is reluctant to believe that reason and obligation sometimes conflict. On the other hand, men of all ages have failed to find satisfaction in the view that the rational basis of obligation is merely the right of the stronger. One of the strongest points of eighteenth- and nineteenth-century utopianism was its apparent success in meeting both these objections at once. The utopian, starting from the primacy of ethics, necessarily believes in an obligation which is ethical in character and independent of the right of the stronger. But he has also been able to convince himself, on grounds other than those of the realist, that the duty of the individual to submit to rules made in the interest of the community can be justified in terms of reason, and that the greatest good of the greatest number is a rational end even for those who are not included in the greatest number. He achieves this synthesis by maintaining that the highest interest of the individual and the highest interest of the community naturally coincide. In pursuing his own interest, the individual pursues that of the community, and in promoting the interest of the community he promotes his own. This is the famous doctrine of the harmony of interests. It is a necessary corollary of the postulate that moral laws can be established by right reasoning. The admission of any ultimate divergence of interests would be fatal to this postulate; and any apparent clash of interests must therefore be explained as the result of wrong calculation. Burke tacitly accepted the doctrine of identity when he defined expediency as ‘that which is good for the community and for every individual in it’.1 It was handed on from the eighteenth-century rationalists to Bentham, and from Bentham to the Victorian moralists. The utilitarian philosophers could justify morality by the argument that, in promoting the good of others, one automatically promotes one’s own. Honesty is the best policy. If people or nations behave badly, it must be, as Buckle and Sir Norman Angell and Professor Zimmern think, because they are unintellectual and short-sighted and muddle-headed.

The paradise of laissez-faire

It was the laissez-faire school of political economy created by Adam Smith which was in the main responsible for popularizing the doctrine of the harmony of interests. The purpose of the school was to promote the removal of state control in economic matters; and in order to justify this policy, it set out to demonstrate that the individual could be relied on, without external control, to promote the interests of the community for the very reason that those interests were identical with his own. This proof was the burden of The Wealth of Nations. The community is divided into those who live by rent, those who live by wages and those who live by profit; and the interests of ‘those three great orders’ are ‘strictly and inseparably connected with the general interest of the society’.2 The harmony is none the less real if those concerned are unconscious of it. The individual ‘neither intends to promote the public interest, nor knows how much he is promoting it . . . He intends only his own gain, and he is in this, as in many other cases, led by an invisible hand to promote an end which was no part of his intention.’3 The invisible hand, which Adam Smith would perhaps have regarded as a metaphor, presented no difficulty to Victorian piety. ‘It is curious to observe’, remarks a tract issued by the Society for the Propagation of Christian Knowledge towards the middle of the nineteenth century, ‘how, through the wise and beneficent arrangement of Providence, men thus do the greatest service to the public when they are thinking of nothing but their own gain.’4 About the same time an English clergyman wrote a work entitled The Temporal Benefits of Christianity Explained. The harmony of interests provided a solid rational basis for morality. To love one’s neighbour turned out to be a thoroughly enlightened way of loving oneself. ‘We now know’, wrote Mr Henry Ford as recently as 1930, ‘that anything which is economically right is also morally right. There can be no conflict between good economics and good morals.’5

The assumption of a general and fundamental harmony of interests is prima facie so paradoxical that it requires careful scrutiny. In the form which Adam Smith gave to it, it had a definite application to the economic structure of the eighteenth century. It presupposed a society of small producers and merchants, interested in the maximization of production and exchange, infinitely mobile and adaptable, and unconcerned with the problem of the distribution of wealth. Those conditions were substantially fulfilled in an age when production involved no high degree of specialization and no sinking of capital in fixed equipment, and when the class which might be more interested in the equitable distribution of wealth than in its maximum production was insignificant and without influence. But by a curious coincidence, the year which saw the publication of The Wealth of Nations was also the year in which Watt invented his steam engine. Thus, at the very moment when laissez-faire theory was receiving its classical exposition, its premises were undermined by an invention which was destined to call into being immobile, highly specialized, mammoth industries and a large and powerful proletariat more interested in distribution than in production. Once industrial capitalism and the class system had become the recognized structure of society, the doctrine of the harmony of interests acquired a new significance, and became, as we shall presently see, the ideology of a dominant group concerned to maintain its predominance by asserting the identity of its interests with those of the community as a whole.6

But this transformation could not have been effected, and the doctrine could not have survived at all, but for one circumstance. The survival of the belief in a harmony of interests was rendered possible by the unparalleled expansion of production, population and prosperity, which marked the hundred years following the publication of The Wealth of Nations and the invention of the steam engine. Expanding prosperity contributed to the popularity of the doctrine in three different ways. It attenuated competition for markets among producers, since fresh markets were constantly available; it postponed the class issue, with its insistence on the primary importance of equitable distribution, by extending to members of the less prosperous classes some share in the general prosperity; and by creating a sense of confidence in present and future well-being, it encouraged men to believe that the world was ordered on so rational a plan as the natural harmony of interests. ‘It was the continual widening of the field of demand which, for half a century, made capitalism operate as if it were a liberal utopia.’7 The tacit presupposition of infinitely expanding markets was the foundation on which the supposed harmony of interests rested. As Dr Mannheim points out, traffic control is unnecessary so long as the number of cars does not exceed the comfortable capacity of the road.8 Until that moment arrives, it is easy to believe in a natural harmony of interests between road-users.

What was true of individuals was assumed to be also true of nations. Just as individuals, by pursuing their own good, unconsciously compass the good of the whole community, so nations in serving themselves serve humanity. Universal free trade was justified on the ground that the maximum economic interest of each nation was identified with the maximum economic interest of the whole world. Adam Smith, who was a practical reformer rather than a pure theorist, did indeed admit that governments might have to protect certain industries in the interests of national defence. But such derogations seemed to him and to his followers trivial exceptions to the rule. ‘Laissez-faire’, as J. S. Mill puts it, ‘. . . should be the general rule: every departure from it, unless required by some great good, a certain evil.’9 Other thinkers gave the doctrine of the harmony of national interests a still wider application. ‘The true interests of a nation’, observes a late eighteenth-century writer, ‘never yet stood in opposition to the general interest of mankind; and it can never happen that philanthropy and patriotism can impose on any man inconsistent duties.’10 T. H. Green, the English Hegelian who tempered the doctrines of his master with concessions to British nineteenth-century liberalism, held that ‘no action in its own interest of a state which fulfilled its idea could conflict with any true interest or right of general society’,11 though it is interesting to note that the question-begging epithet ‘true’, which in the eighteenth-century quotation is attached to the interests of the nation, has been transferred by the nineteenth century to the interest of the general society. Mazzini, who embodied the liberal nineteenth-century philosophy of nationalism, believed in a sort of division of labour between nations. Each nation had its own special task for which its special aptitudes fitted it, and the performance of this task was its contribution to the welfare of humanity. If all nations acted in this spirit, international harmony would prevail. The same condition of apparently infinite expansibility which encouraged belief in the economic harmony of interests made possible the belief in the political harmony of rival national movements. One reason why contemporaries of Mazzini thought nationalism a good thing was that there were few recognized nations, and plenty of room for them. In an age when Germans, Czechs, Poles, Ukrainians, Magyars and half a dozen more national groups were not yet visibly jostling one another over an area of a few hundred square miles, it was comparatively easy to believe that each nation, by developing its own nationalism, could make its own special contribution to the international harmony of interests. Most liberal writers continued to believe, right down to 1918, that nations, by developing their own nationalism, promoted the cause of internationalism; and Wilson and many other makers of the peace treaties saw in national self-determination the key to world peace. More recently still, responsible Anglo-Saxon statesmen have been from time to time content to echo, probably without much reflexion, the old Mazzinian formulae.12

Darwinism in politics

When the centenary of The Wealth of Nations was celebrated in 1876, there were already symptoms of an impending breakdown. No country but Great Britain had been commercially powerful enough to believe in the international harmony of economic interests. Acceptance of free-trade principles outside Great Britain had always been partial, half-hearted and short-lived. The United States had rejected them from the start. About 1840, Friedrich List, who had spent much time studying industrial development in the United States, began to preach to a German audience the doctrine that, while free trade was the right policy for an industrially dominant nation like Great Britain, only protection could enable weaker nations to break the British stranglehold. German and American industries, built up behind protective tariffs, were soon seriously impinging on the worldwide British industrial monopoly. The British Dominions overseas made use of their newly-won fiscal autonomy to protect themselves against the manufactures of the mother country. The pressure of competition was increasing on all sides. Nationalism began to wear a sinister aspect, and to degenerate into imperialism. The philosophy of Hegel, who identified reality with an eternally recurring conflict of ideas, extended its influence. Behind Hegel stood Marx, who materialized the Hegelian conflict into a class-war of economic interest-groups, and working-class parties came into being which steadfastly refused to believe in the harmony of interests between capital and labour. Above all, Darwin propounded and popularized a biological doctrine of evolution through a perpetual struggle for life and the elimination of the unfit.

It was the doctrine of evolution which for a time enabled the laissez-faire philosophy to make its terms with the new conditions and the new trend of thought. Free competition had always been worshipped as the beneficent deity of the laissez-faire system. The French economist Bastiat, in a work significantly entitled Les Harmonies Économiques, had hailed competition as ‘that humanitarian force . . . which continually wrests progress from the hands of the individual to make it the common heritage of the great human family’.13 Under the growing strains of the latter half of the nineteenth century, it was perceived that competition in the economic sphere implied exactly what Darwin proclaimed as the biological law of nature – the survival of the stronger at the expense of the weaker. The small producer or trader was gradually being put out of business by his large-scale competitor; and this development was what progress and the welfare of the community as a whole demanded. Laissez-faire meant an open field, and the prize to the strongest. The doctrine of the harmony of interests underwent an almost imperceptible modification. The good of the community (or, as people were now inclined to say, of the species) was still identical with the good of its individual members, but only of those individuals who were effective competitors in the struggle for life. Humanity went on from strength to strength, shedding its weaklings by the way. ‘The development of the species,’ as Marx said, ‘. . . and therefore the higher development of the individual, can only be secured through the historical process, in which individuals are sacrificed.’14 Such was the doctrine of the new age of intensified economic competition preached by the school of Herbert Spencer, and commonly accepted in Great Britain in the seventies and eighties. The last French disciple of Adam Smith, Yves Guyot, assisted perhaps by the accident that the French word concurrence means ‘collaboration’ as well as ‘competition’, wrote a work entitled La Morale de la Concurrence. Among English writers who applied this evolutionary principle to international politics, the most popular was Bagehot:

Conquest is the premium given by nature to those national characters which their national customs have made most fit to win in war, and in most material respects those winning characters are really the best characters. The characters which do win in war are the characters which we should wish to win in war.15

About the same time, a Russian sociologist defined international politics as ‘the art of conducting the struggle for existence between social organisms’;16 and in 1900 a distinguished professor, in a once famous book, stated the doctrine in all its naked ruthlessness:

The path of progress is strewn with the wreck of nations; traces are everywhere to be seen of the hecatombs of inferior races, and of victims who found not the narrow way to the greater perfection. Yet these dead peoples are, in very truth, the stepping stones on which mankind has arisen to the higher intellectual and deeper emotional life of to-day.17

In Germany, the same view was propounded by Treitschke and Houston Stewart Chamberlain. The doctrine of progress through the elimination of unfit nations seemed a fair corollary of the doctrine of progress through the elimination of unfit individuals; and some such belief, though not always openly avowed, was implicit in late nineteenth-century imperialism. In the later nineteenth century, as an American historian remarks, ‘the basic problem of international relations was who should cut up the victims’.18 The harmony of interests was established through the sacrifice of ‘unfit’ Africans and Asiatics.

One point had, unfortunately, been overlooked. For more than a hundred years, the doctrine of the harmony of interests had provided a rational basis for morality. The individual had been urged to serve the interest of the community on the plea that that interest was also his own. The ground had now been shifted. In the long run, the good of the community and the good of the individual were still the same. But this eventual harmony was preceded by a struggle for life between individuals, in which not only the good, but the very existence, of the loser were eliminated altogether from the picture. Morality in these conditions had no rational attraction for prospective losers; and the whole ethical system was built on the sacrifice of the weaker brother. In practice, nearly every state had made inroads on the classical doctrine, and introduced social legislation to protect the economically weak against the economically strong. The doctrine itself died harder. In the seventies Dostoevsky, who had none of the prejudices of an Englishman or an economist, made Ivan Karamazov declare that the price of admission to the ‘eternal harmony’ was too high if it included the sufferings of the innocent. About the same time, Winwood Reade made an uncomfortable sensation in Great Britain with a book called The Martyrdom of Man, which drew attention to the immense tale of suffering and waste involved in the theory of evolution. In the nineties, Huxley confessed, in the name of science, to the existence of a discrepancy between the ‘cosmic process’ and the ‘ethical process’;19 and Balfour, approaching the problem from the angle of philosophy, concluded that ‘a complete harmony between “egoism” and “altruism”, between the pursuit of the highest happiness for oneself and the highest happiness for other people, can never be provided by a creed which refuses to admit that the deeds done and the character formed in this life can flow over into another, and there permit a reconciliation and an adjustment between the conflicting principles which are not always possible here’.20 Less and less was heard of the beneficent properties of free competition. Before 1914, though the policy of international free trade was still upheld by the British electorate and by British economists, the ethical postulate which had once formed the basis of the laissez-faire philosophy no longer appealed, at any rate in its crude form, to any serious thinker. Biologically and economically, the doctrine of the harmony of interests was tenable only if you left out of account the interest of the weak who must be driven to the wall, or called in the next world to redress the balance of the present.

The international harmony

Attention has been drawn to the curious way in which doctrines, already obsolete or obsolescent before the war of 1914, were reintroduced in the post-war period, largely through American inspiration, into the special field of international affairs. This would appear to be conspicuously true of the laissez-faire doctrine of the harmony of interests. In the United States, the history of laissez-faire presents special features. Throughout the nineteenth, and well into the twentieth, centuries the United States, while requiring tariff protection against European competition, had enjoyed the advantage of an expanding domestic market of apparently unlimited potentialities. In Great Britain, which continued down to 1914 to dominate world trade, but was increasingly conscious of strains and stresses at home, J. S. Mill and later economists clung firmly to international free trade, but made more and more inroads into laissez-faire orthodoxy in the domestic sphere. In the United States, Carey and his successors justified protective tariffs, but in every other respect maintained the immutable principles of laissez-faire. In Europe after 1919, planned economy, which rests on the assumption that no natural harmony of interests exists and that interests must be artificially harmonized by state action, became the practice, if not the theory, of almost every state. In the United States, the persistence of an expanding domestic market staved off this development till after 1929. The natural harmony of interests remained an integral part of the American view of life; and in this, as in other respects, current theories of international politics were deeply imbued with the American tradition. Moreover, there was a special reason for the ready acceptance of the doctrine in the international sphere. In domestic affairs it is clearly the business of the state to create harmony if no natural harmony exists. In international politics, there is no organized power charged with the task of creating harmony; and the temptation to assume a natural harmony is therefore particularly strong. But this is no excuse for burking the issue. To make the harmonization of interests the goal of political action is not the same thing as to postulate that a natural harmony of interests exists;21 and it is this latter postulate which has caused so much confusion in international thinking.

The common interest in peace

Politically, the doctrine of the identity of interests has commonly taken the form of an assumption that every nation has an identical interest in peace, and that any nation which desires to disturb the peace is therefore both irrational and immoral. This view bears clear marks of its Anglo-Saxon origin. It was easy after 1918 to convince that part of mankind which lives in English-speaking countries that war profits nobody. The argument did not seem particularly convincing to Germans, who had profited greatly from the wars of 1866 and 1870, and attributed their more recent sufferings, not to the war of 1914, but to the fact that they had lost it; or to Italians, who blamed not the war, but the treachery of allies who defrauded them in the peace settlement; or to Poles or Czecho-Slovaks who, far from deploring the war, owed their national existence to it; or to Frenchmen, who could not unreservedly regret a war which had restored Alsace-Lorraine to France; or to people of other nationalities who remembered profitable wars waged by Great Britain and the United States in the past. But these people had fortunately little influence over the formation of current theories of international relations, which emanated almost exclusively from the English-speaking countries. British and American writers continued to assume that the uselessness of war had been irrefutably demonstrated by the experience of 1914–18, and that an intellectual grasp of this fact was all that was necessary to induce the nations to keep the peace in the future; and they were sincerely puzzled as well as disappointed at the failure of other countries to share this view.

The confusion was increased by the ostentatious readiness of other countries to flatter the Anglo-Saxon world by repeating its slogans. In the fifteen years after the first world war, every Great Power (except, perhaps, Italy) repeatedly did lip-service to the doctrine by declaring peace to be one of the main objects of its policy.22 But as Lenin observed long ago, peace in itself is a meaningless aim. ‘Absolutely everybody is in favour of peace in general,’ he wrote in 1915, ‘including Kitchener, Joffre, Hindenburg and Nicholas the Bloody, for everyone of them wishes to end the war.’23 The common interest in peace masks the fact that some nations desire to maintain the status quo without having to fight for it, and others to change the status quo without having to fight in order to do so.24 The statement that it is in the interest of the world as a whole either that the status quo should be maintained, or that it should be changed, would be contrary to the facts. The statement that it is in the interest of the world as a whole that the conclusion eventually reached, whether maintenance or change, should be reached by peaceful means, would command general assent, but seems a rather meaningless platitude. The utopian assumption that there is a world interest in peace which is identifiable with the interest of each individual nation helped politicians and political writers everywhere to evade the unpalatable fact of a fundamental divergence of interest between nations desirous of maintaining the status quo and nations desirous of changing it.25 A peculiar combination of platitude and falseness thus became endemic in the pronouncements of statesmen about international affairs. ‘In this whole Danubian area,’ said a Prime Minister of Czecho-Slovakia, ‘no one really wants conflicts and jealousies. The various countries want to maintain their independence, but otherwise they are ready for any co-operative measures. I am thinking specially of the Little Entente, Hungary and Bulgaria.’26 Literally the words may pass as true. Yet the conflicts and jealousies which nobody wanted were a notorious feature of Danubian politics after 1919, and the co-operation for which all were ready was unobtainable. The fact of divergent interests was disguised and falsified by the platitude of a general desire to avoid conflict.

International economic harmony

In economic relations, the assumption of a general harmony of interests was made with even greater confidence; for here we have a direct reflexion of the cardinal doctrine of laissez-faire economics, and it is here that we can see most clearly the dilemma which results from the doctrine. When the nineteenth-century liberal spoke of the greatest good of the greatest number, he tacitly assumed that the good of the minority might have to be sacrificed to it. This principle applied equally to international economic relations. If Russia or Italy, for example, were not strong enough to build up industries without the protection of tariffs, then – the laissez-faire liberal would have argued – they should be content to import British and German manufactures and supply wheat and oranges to the British and German markets. If anyone had thereupon objected that this policy would condemn Russia and Italy to remain second-rate Powers economically and militarily dependent on their neighbours, the laissez-faire liberal would have had to answer that this was the will of Providence and that this was what the general harmony of interests demanded. The modern utopian internationalist enjoys none of the advantages, and has none of the toughness, of the nineteenth-century liberal. The material success of the weaker Powers in building up protected industries, as well as the new spirit of internationalism, preclude him from arguing that the harmony of interests depends on the sacrifice of economically unfit nations. Yet the abandonment of this premiss destroys the whole basis of the doctrine which he has inherited; and he is driven to the belief that the common good can be achieved without any sacrifice of the good of any individual member of the community. Every international conflict is therefore unnecessary and illusory. It is only necessary to discover the common good which is at the same time the highest good of all the disputants; and only the folly of statesmen stands in the way of its discovery. The utopian, secure in his understanding of this common good, arrogates to himself the monopoly of wisdom. The statesmen of the world one and all stand convicted of incredible blindness to the interest of those whom they are supposed to represent. Such was the picture of the international scene presented, in all seriousness, by British and American writers, including not a few economists.

It is for this reason that we find in the modern period an extraordinary divergence between the theories of economic experts and the practice of those responsible for the economic policies of their respective countries. Analysis will show that this divergence springs from a simple fact. The economic expert, dominated in the main by laissez-faire doctrine, considers the hypothetical economic interest of the world as a whole, and is content to assume that this is identical with the interest of each individual country. The politician pursues the concrete interest of his country, and assumes (if he makes any assumption at all) that the interest of the world as a whole is identical with it. Nearly every pronouncement of every international economic conference held between the two world wars was vitiated by this assumption that there was some ‘solution’ or ‘plan’ which, by a judicious balancing of interests, would be equally favourable to all and prejudicial to none.

Any strictly nationalistic policy [declared the League Conference of economic experts in 1927] is harmful not only to the nation which practises it but also to the others, and therefore defeats its own end, and if it be desired that the new state of mind revealed by the Conference should lead rapidly to practical results, any programme of execution must include, as an essential factor, the principle of parallel or concerted action by the different nations. Every country will then know that the concessions it is asked to make will be balanced by corresponding sacrifices on the part of the other countries. It will be able to accept the proposed measures, not merely in view of its own individual position, but also because it is interested in the success of the general plan laid down by the Conference.27

The sequel of the Conference was the complete neglect of all the recommendations unanimously made by it; and if we are not content to accept the facile explanation that the leading statesmen of the world were either criminal or mad, we may begin to suspect the validity of its initial assumption. It seems altogether rash to suppose that economic nationalism is necessarily detrimental to states which practise it. In the nineteenth century, Germany and the United States, by pursuing a ‘strictly nationalistic policy’, had placed themselves in a position to challenge Great Britain’s virtual monopoly of world trade. No conference of economic experts, meeting in 1880, could have evolved a ‘general plan’ for ‘parallel or concerted action’ which would have allayed the economic rivalries of the time in a manner equally advantageous to Great Britain, Germany and the United States. It was not less presumptuous to suppose that a conference meeting in 1927 could allay the economic rivalries of the later period by a ‘plan’ beneficial to the interests of everyone. Even the economic crisis of 1930–33 failed to bring home to the economists the true nature of the problem which they had to face. The experts who prepared the ‘Draft Annotated Agenda’ for the World Economic Conference of 1933 condemned the ‘worldwide adoption of ideals of national self-sufficiency which cut unmistakably athwart the lines of economic development’.28 They did not apparently pause to reflect that those so-called ‘lines of economic development’, which might be beneficial to some countries and even to the world as a whole, would inevitably be detrimental to other countries, which were using weapons of economic nationalism in self-defence. The Van Zeeland report of January 1938 began by asking, and answering in the affirmative, the question whether ‘the methods which, taken as a whole, form the system of international trade’ are ‘fundamentally preferable’ to ‘autarkic tendencies’. Yet every Power at some period of its history, and as a rule for prolonged periods, has resorted to ‘autarkic tendencies’. It is difficult to believe that there is any absolute sense in which ‘autarkic tendencies’ are always detrimental to those who pursue them. Even if they could be justified only as the lesser of two evils, the initial premise of the Van Zeeland report was invalidated. But there was worse to come. ‘We must . . . make our dispositions’, continued M. Van Zeeland, ‘in such a way that the new system shall offer to all participators advantages greater than those of the position in which they now find themselves.’29 This is economic utopianism in its most purblind form. The report, like the reports of 1927 and 1933, assumed the existence of a fundamental principle of economic policy whose application would be equally beneficial to all states and detrimental to none; and for this reason it remained, like its predecessors, a dead letter.

Economic theory, as opposed to economic practice, was so powerfully dominated in the years between the two world wars by the supposed harmony of interests that it is difficult to find, in the innumerable international discussions of the period, any clear exposition of the real problem which baffled the statesmen of the world. Perhaps the frankest statement was one made by the Yugoslav Foreign Minister at the session of the Commission for European Union in January 1931. Arthur Henderson, on behalf of Great Britain, following the Netherlands delegate Dr Colijn, had pleaded for an all-round tariff reduction ‘which must, by its nature, bring benefit to each and all by allowing that expansion of production and international exchange of wealth by which the common prosperity of all can be increased’.30 Marinkovitch, who spoke next, concluded from the failure to carry out the recommendations of the 1927 Conference, that ‘there were extremely important reasons why the governments could not apply’ those resolutions. He went on:

The fact is that apart from economic considerations there are also political and social considerations. The old ‘things-will-right-themselves’ school of economists argued that if nothing were done and events were allowed to follow their natural course from an economic point of view, economic equilibrium would come about of its own accord. That is probably true (I do not propose to discuss the point). But how would that equilibrium come about? At the expense of the weakest. Now, as you are aware, for more than seventy years there has been a powerful and growing reaction against this theory of economics. All the socialist parties of Europe and the world are merely the expression of the opposition to this way of looking at economic problems.

   We were told that we ought to lower customs barriers and even abolish them. As far as the agricultural states of Europe are concerned, if they could keep the promises they made in 1927 – admitting that the statements of 1927 did contain promises – and could carry that policy right through, we might perhaps find ourselves able to hold our own against overseas competition in the matter of agricultural products. But at the same time we should have to create in Poland, Roumania and Yugoslavia the same conditions as exist in Canada and the Argentine, where vast territories are inhabited by a scanty population and where machinery and other devices are employed. . . . We could not sacrifice our people by shooting them, but they would nevertheless be killed off by famine – which would come to the same thing.

   I am sure that the key to which M. Colijn has referred does not exist. Economic and social life is too complicated to allow of a solution by any one formula; it calls for complicated solutions. We shall have to take into account the many varieties of geographical, political, social and other conditions which exist.31

Marinkovitch went on to dispose of the theory of the ‘long-run’ harmony of interests:

Last year, when I was in the Yugoslav mountains, I heard that the inhabitants of a small mountain village, having no maize or wheat on which to live, were simply cutting down a wood which belonged to them . . . and were living on what they earned by selling the wood. . . . I went to the village, collected together some of the leading inhabitants and endeavoured to reason with them, just like the great industrial states reason with us. I said to them: ‘You possess plenty of common sense. You see that your forest is becoming smaller and smaller. What will you do when you cut down the last tree?’ They replied to me: ‘Your Excellency, that is a point which worries us: but on the other hand, what should we do now if we stopped cutting down our trees?’

   I can assure you that the agricultural countries are in exactly the same situation. You threaten them with future disasters; but they are already in the throes of disaster.32

One further example of unwonted frankness may be quoted. Speaking in September 1937 over one of the United States broadcasting systems, the President of the Colombian Republic said:

In no field of human activity are the benefits of the crisis as clear as in the relationships between nations and especially of the American nations. If it is true that the economic relations have become rigorous and at times harsh, it is also true that they have fortunately become more democratic.

   The crisis freed many countries which had up to then been subordinated to the double mental and financial imperialism of the nations which controlled international markets and policies. Many nations learned to trust less international cordiality and to seek an autonomous life, full of initial obstacles but which nevertheless created strong interests within a short time . . .

   When the arbitrary systems that prevail today begin to be relaxed, there will be a weaker international trade, but there will also be a larger number of nations economically strong.

   Economic co-operation today is a very different and more noble thing than the old co-operation which was based on the convenience of industrial countries and of bankers who tutored the world. The certainty acquired by many small nations that they can subsist and prosper without subordinating their conduct and their activities to foreign interests has begun to introduce a greater frankness and equality in the relations between modern nations . . .

   It is true that the crisis has shipwrecked many high and noble principles of our civilization; but it is also true that in this return to a kind of primitive struggle for existence, peoples are being freed of many fictions and of much hypocrisy which they had accepted in the belief that with them they were insuring their well-being . . .

   The foundation of international economic freedom lies in the recognition that when strong nations place themselves on the defensive, they act just like the weak ones do, and that all of them have an equal right to defend themselves with their own resources.33

The claims made on behalf of the Colombian Republic were perhaps exaggerated. But both the Yugoslav and the Colombian statements were powerful challenges to the doctrine of the harmony of interests. It is fallacy to suppose that, because Great Britain and the United States have an interest in the removal of trade barriers, this is also an interest of Yugoslavia and Colombia. International trade may be weaker. The economic interests of Europe or of the world at large may suffer. But Yugoslavia and Colombia will be better off than they would have been under a régime of European or world prosperity which reduced them to the position of satellites. Dr Schacht spoke a little later of those ‘fanatical adherents of the most-favoured-nation policy abroad, who from the abundance of their wealth cannot realize that a poor nation has nevertheless the courage to live by its own laws instead of suffering under the prescriptions of the well-to-do’.34 Laissez-faire, in international relations as in those between capital and labour, is the paradise of the economically strong. State control, whether in the form of protective legislation or of protective tariffs, is the weapon of self-defence invoked by the economically weak. The clash of interests is real and inevitable; and the whole nature of the problem is distorted by an attempt to disguise it.

The harmony broken

We must therefore reject as inadequate and misleading the attempt to base international morality on an alleged harmony of interests which identifies the interest of the whole community of nations with the interest of each individual member of it. In the nineteenth century, this attempt met with widespread success, thanks to the continuously expanding economy in which it was made. The period was one of progressive prosperity, punctuated only by minor set-backs. The international economic structure bore considerable resemblance to the domestic economic structure of the United States. Pressure could at once be relieved by expansion to hitherto unoccupied and unexploited territories; and there was a plentiful supply of cheap labour, and of backward countries, which had not yet reached the level of political consciousness. Enterprising individuals could solve the economic problem by migration, enterprising nations by colonization. Expanding markets produced an expanding population, and population in turn reacted on markets. Those who were left behind in the race could plausibly be regarded as the unfit. A harmony of interests among the fit, based on individual enterprise and free competition, was sufficiently near to reality to form a sound basis for the current theory. With some difficulty the illusion was kept alive till 1914. Even British prosperity, though its foundations were menaced by German and American competition, continued to expand. The year 1913 was a record year for British trade.

The transition from the apparent harmony to the transparent clash of interests may be placed about the turn of the century. Appropriately enough, it found its first expression in colonial policies. In the British mind, it was primarily associated with events in South Africa. Mr Churchill dates the beginning of ‘these violent times’ from the Jameson Raid.35 In North Africa and the Far East, there was a hasty scramble by the European Powers to secure the few eligible sites which were still vacant. Emigration of individuals from Europe, the point of principal tension, to America assumed unparalleled dimensions. In Europe itself, anti-Semitism – the recurrent symptom of economic stress – reappeared after a long interval in Russia, Germany and France.36 In Great Britain, agitation against unrestricted alien immigration began in the 1890s; and the first act controlling immigration was passed in 1905.

The first world war, which proceeded from this growing tension, aggravated it tenfold by intensifying its fundamental causes. In belligerent and neutral countries in Europe, Asia and America industrial and agricultural production were everywhere artificially stimulated. After the war every country struggled to maintain its expanded production; and an enhanced and inflamed national consciousness was invoked to justify the struggle. One reason for the unprecedented vindictiveness of the peace treaties, and in particular of their economic clauses, was that practical men no longer believed – as they had done fifty or a hundred years earlier – in an underlying harmony of interests between victors and defeated. The object was now to eliminate a competitor, a revival of whose prosperity might menace your own. In Europe, the struggle was intensified by the creation of new states and new economic frontiers. In Asia, India and China built up large-scale manufactures to make themselves independent of imports from Europe. Japan became an exporter of textiles and other cheap goods which undercut European manufactures on the world market. Most important of all, there were no more open spaces anywhere awaiting cheap and profitable development and exploitation. The ample avenues of migration which had relieved the economic pressures of the pre-war period were closed; and in place of the natural flow of migration came the problem of forcibly evicted refugees.37 The complex phenomenon known as economic nationalism swept over the world. The fundamental character of this clash of interests became obvious to all except those confirmed utopians who dominated economic thought in the English-speaking countries. The hollowness of the glib nineteenth-century platitude that nobody can benefit from what harms another was revealed. The basic presupposition of utopianism had broken down.

What confronts us in international politics today is, therefore, nothing less than the complete bankruptcy of the conception of morality which has dominated political and economic thought for a century and a half. Internationally, it is no longer possible to deduce virtue from right reasoning, because it is no longer seriously possible to believe that every state, by pursuing the greatest good of the whole world, is pursuing the greatest good of its own citizens, and vice versa. The synthesis of morality and reason, at any rate in the crude form in which it was achieved by nineteenth-century liberalism, is untenable. The inner meaning of the modern international crisis is the collapse of the whole structure of utopianism based on the concept of the harmony of interests. The present generation will have to rebuild from the foundations. But before we can do this, before we can ascertain what can be salved from the ruins, we must examine the flaws in the structure which led to its collapse; and we can best do this by analysing the realist critique of the utopian assumptions.

Notes

1.

|   |

Burke, Works, v. 407.

2.

|   |

Adam Smith, The Wealth of Nations, Book I. ch. xi. conclusion.

3.

|   |

Ibid., Book IV. ch. ii.

4.

|   |

Quoted in J. M. Keynes, A Tract on Monetary Reform, p. 7.

5.

|   |

Quoted in J. Truslow Adams, The Epic of America, p. 400. I have failed to trace the original.

6.

|   |

See pp. 80–1.

7.

|   |

Nationalism: A Study by a Group of Members of the Royal Institute of International Affairs, p. 229.

8.

|   |

K. Mannheim, Mensch und Gesellschaft im Zeitalter des Umbaus, p. 104.

9.

|   |

J. S. Mill, Principles of Political Economy, II. Book V. ch. xi.

10.

|   |

Romilly, Thoughts on the Influence of the French Revolution, p. 5.

11.

|   |

T. H. Green, Principles of Political Obligation, § 166.

12.

|   |

Mr Eden, for example, in 1938 advocated ‘a comity of nations in which each can develop and flourish and give to their uttermost their own special contribution to the diversity of life’ (Anthony Eden, Foreign Affairs, p. 277).

13.

|   |

Bastiat, Les Harmonies Économiques, p. 355.

14.

|   |

Marx, Theorien u ber den Mebrwert, II, i. p. 309.

15.

|   |

Bagehot, Physics and Politics (2nd ed.), p. 215. What does ‘material’ mean in this passage? Does it merely mean ‘relevant’? Or is the writer conscious of an uncomfortable antithesis between ‘material’ and ‘moral’?

16.

|   |

J. Novicow, La Politique Internationale, p. 242.

17.

|   |

Karl Pearson, National Life from the Standpoint of Science, p. 64.

18.

|   |

W. L. Langer, The Diplomacy of Imperialism, ii. p. 797.

19.

|   |

Huxley, Romanes Lecture, 1893, reprinted in Evolution and Ethics, p. 81.

20.

|   |

Balfour, Foundations of Belief, p. 27.

21.

|   |

The confusion between the two was admirably illustrated by an interjection of Mr Attlee in the House of Commons: ‘It was precisely the object of the establishment of the League of Nations that the preservation of peace was a common interest of the world’ (House of Commons, 21 December 1937: Official Report, col. 1811). Mr Attlee apparently failed to distinguish between the proposition that a natural community of interests existed and the proposition that the League of Nations had been established to create one.

22.

|   |

‘Peace must prevail, must come before all’ (Briand, League of Nations: Ninth Assembly, p. 83). ‘The maintenance of peace is the first objective of British foreign policy’ (Eden, League of Nations: Sixteenth Assembly, p. 106). ‘Peace is our dearest treasure’ (Hitler, in a speech in the German Reichstag on 30 January 1937, reported in The Times, 1 February 1937). ‘The principal aim of the international policy of the Soviet Union is the preservation of peace’ (Chicherin in The Soviet Union and Peace (1929), p. 249). ‘The object of Japan, despite propaganda to the contrary, is peace’ (Matsuoka, League of Nations: Special Assembly 1932–33, iii. p. 73). The paucity of Italian pronouncements in favour of peace was probably explained by the poor reputation of Italian troops as fighters: Mussolini feared that any emphatic expression of preference for peace would be construed as an admission that Italy had no stomach for war.

23.

|   |

Lenin, Collected Works (Engl. transl.), xviii. p. 264. Compare Spencer Wilkinson’s dictum: ‘It is not peace but preponderance that is in each case the real object. The truth cannot be too often repeated that peace is never the object of policy: you cannot define peace except by reference to war, which is a means and never an end’ (Government and the War, p. 121).

24.

|   |

‘When a saint complains that people do not know the things belonging to their peace, what he really means is that they do not sufficiently care about the things belonging to his peace’ (The Note-Books of Samuel Butler, ed. Festing-Jones, pp. 211–12). This would seem to be true of those latter-day saints, the satisfied Powers.

25.

|   |

It is sometimes maintained not merely that all nations have an equal interest in preferring peace to war (which is, in a sense, true), but that war can never in any circumstances bring to the victor advantages comparable with its cost. The latter view does not appear to be true of the past, though it is possible to argue (as does Bertrand Russell, Which Way Peace?) that it is true of modern warfare. If accepted, this view leads, of course, to absolute pacifism; for there is no reason to suppose that it is any truer of ‘defensive’ than of ‘offensive’ war (assuming the distinction between them to be valid).

26.

|   |

Daily Telegraph, 26 August 1938.

27.

|   |

League of Nations: C.E.I. 44, p. 21 (italics in original).

28.

|   |

League of Nations: C.48, M.18, 1933, ii. p. 6.

29.

|   |

Report . . . on the Possibility of Obtaining a General Reduction of the Obstacles to International Trade, Cmd 5648.

30.

|   |

League of Nations: C.144, M.45, 1931, vii. p. 30.

31.

|   |

League of Nations: C.144, M.45, 1931, vii. p. 31.

32.

|   |

Ibid., p. 32.

33.

|   |

Address broadcast by the Columbia Broadcasting System, USA, on 19 September 1937, and published in Talks, October 1937.

34.

|   |

Address to the Economic Council of the German Academy, 29 November 1938.

35.

|   |

Winston Churchill, World Crisis, p. 26.

36.

|   |

The same conditions encouraged the growth of Zionism; for Zionism, as the Palestine Royal Commission of 1937 remarked, ‘on its negative side is a creed of escape’ (Cmd 5479, p. 13).

37.

|   |

‘The existence of refugees is a symptom of the disappearance of economic and political liberalism. Refugees are the by-product of an economic isolationism which has practically stopped free migration’ (J. Hope Simpson, Refugees: Preliminary Report of a Survey, p. 193).

CHAPTER SIX

The Limitations of Realism

The exposure by realist criticism of the hollowness of the utopian edifice is the first task of the political thinker. It is only when the sham has been demolished that there can be any hope of raising a more solid structure in its place. But we cannot ultimately find a resting place in pure realism; for realism, though logically overwhelming, does not provide us with the springs of action which are necessary even to the pursuit of thought. Indeed, realism itself, if we attack it with its own weapons, often turns out in practice to be just as much conditioned as any other mode of thought. In politics, the belief that certain facts are unalterable or certain trends irresistible commonly reflects a lack of desire or lack of interest to change or resist them. The impossibility of being a consistent and thorough-going realist is one of the most certain and most curious lessons of political science. Consistent realism excludes four things which appear to be essential ingredients of all effective political thinking: a finite goal, an emotional appeal, a right of moral judgement and a ground for action.

The conception of politics as an infinite process seems in the long run uncongenial or incomprehensible to the human mind. Every political thinker who wishes to make an appeal to his contemporaries is consciously or unconsciously led to posit a finite goal. Treitschke declared that the ‘terrible thing’ about Machiavelli’s teaching was ‘not the immorality of the methods he recommends, but the lack of content of the state, which exists only in order to exist’.1 In fact, Machiavelli is not so consistent. His realism breaks down in the last chapter of The Prince, which is entitled ‘An Exhortation to free Italy from the Barbarians’ – a goal whose necessity could be deduced from no realist premise. Marx, having dissolved human thought and action into the relativism of the dialectic, postulates the absolute goal of a classless society where the dialectic no longer operates – that one far-off event towards which, in true Victorian fashion, he believed the whole creation to be moving. The realist thus ends by negating his own postulate and assuming an ultimate reality outside the historical process. Engels was one of the first to level this charge against Hegel. ‘The whole dogmatic content of the Hegelian system is declared to be absolute truth in contradiction to his dialectical method, which dissolves all dogmatism.’2 But Marx lays himself open to precisely the same criticism when he brings the process of dialectical materialism to an end with the victory of the proletariat. Thus utopianism penetrates the citadel of realism; and to envisage a continuing, but not infinite, process towards a finite goal is shown to be a condition of political thought. The greater the emotional stress, the nearer and more concrete is the goal. The first world war was rendered tolerable by the belief that it was the last of wars. Woodrow Wilson’s moral authority was built up on the conviction, shared by himself, that he possessed the key to a just, comprehensive and final settlement of the political ills of mankind. It is noteworthy that almost all religions agree in postulating an ultimate state of complete blessedness.

The finite goal, assuming the character of an apocalyptic vision, thereby acquires an emotional, irrational appeal which realism itself cannot justify or explain. Everyone knows Marx’s famous prediction of the future classless paradise:

When work ceases to be merely a means of life and becomes the first living need; when, with the all-round development of the individual, productive forces also develop, and all the sources of collective wealth flow in free abundance – then only will it be possible to transcend completely the narrow horizon of bourgeois right, and society can inscribe on its banner: From each according to his capacities, to each according to his needs.3

Sorel proclaimed the necessity of a ‘myth’ to make revolutionary teaching effective; and Soviet Russia has exploited for this purpose the myth, first of world revolution, and more recently of the ‘socialist fatherland’. There is much to be said for Professor Laski’s view that ‘communism has made its way by its idealism, and not by its realism, by its spiritual promise, not by its materialistic prospects’.4 A modern theologian has analysed the situation with almost cynical clear-sightedness:

Without the ultrarational hopes and passions of religion, no society will have the courage to conquer despair and attempt the impossible; for the vision of a just society is an impossible one, which can be approximated only by those who do not regard it as impossible. The truest visions of religion are illusions, which may be partly realized by being resolutely believed.5

And this again closely echoes a passage in Mein Kampf in which Hitler contrasts the ‘programme-maker’ with the politician:

His [i.e. the programme-maker’s] significance lies almost wholly in the future, and he is often what one means by the word ‘weltfremd’ [unpractical, utopian]. For if the art of the politician is really the art of the possible, then the programme-maker belongs to those of whom it is said that they please the gods only if they ask and demand from them the impossible.6

Credo quia impossible becomes a category of political thinking.

Consistent realism, as has already been noted, involves acceptance of the whole historical process and precludes moral judgements on it. As we have seen, men are generally prepared to accept the judgement of history on the past, praising success and condemning failure. This test is also widely applied to contemporary politics. Such institutions as the League of Nations, or the Soviet or Fascist régimes, are to a considerable extent judged by their capacity to achieve what they profess to achieve; and the legitimacy of this test is implicitly admitted by their own propaganda, which constantly seeks to exaggerate their successes and minimize their failures. Yet it is clear that mankind as a whole is not prepared to accept this rational test as a universally valid basis of political judgement. The belief that whatever succeeds is right, and has only to be understood to be approved, must, if consistently held, empty thought of purpose, and thereby sterilize and ultimately destroy it. Nor do those whose philosophy appears to exclude the possibility of moral judgements in fact refrain from pronouncing them. Frederick the Great, having explained that treaties should be observed for the reason that ‘one can trick only once’, goes on to call the breaking of treaties ‘a bad and knavish policy’, though there is nothing in his thesis to justify the moral epithet.7 Marx, whose philosophy appeared to demonstrate that capitalists could only act in a certain way, spends many pages – some of the most effective in Capital – in denouncing the wickedness of capitalists for behaving in precisely that way. The necessity, recognized by all politicians, both in domestic and in international affairs, for cloaking interests in a guise of moral principles is in itself a symptom of the inadequacy of realism. Every age claims the right to create its own values, and to pass judgements in the light of them; and even if it uses realist weapons to dissolve other values, it still believes in the absolute character of its own. It refuses to accept the implication of realism that the word ‘ought’ is meaningless.

Most of all, consistent realism breaks down because it fails to provide any ground for purposive or meaningful action. If the sequence of cause and effect is sufficiently rigid to permit of the ‘scientific prediction’ of events, if our thought is irrevocably conditioned by our status and our interests, then both action and thought become devoid of purpose. If, as Schopenhauer maintains, ‘the true philosophy of history consists of the insight that, throughout the jumble of all these ceaseless changes, we have ever before our eyes the same unchanging being, pursuing the same course to-day, yesterday and for ever’,8 then passive contemplation is all that remains to the individual. Such a conclusion is plainly repugnant to the most deep-seated belief of man about himself. That human affairs can be directed and modified by human action and human thought is a postulate so fundamental that its rejection seems scarcely compatible with existence as a human being. Nor is it in fact rejected by those realists who have left their mark on history. Machiavelli, when he exhorted his compatriots to be good Italians, clearly assumed that they were free to follow or ignore his advice. Marx, by birth and training a bourgeois, believed himself free to think and act like a proletarian, and regarded it as his mission to persuade others, whom he assumed to be equally free, to think and act likewise. Lenin, who wrote of the imminence of world revolution as a ‘scientific prediction’, admitted elsewhere that ‘no situation exists from which there is absolutely no way out’.9 In moments of crisis, Lenin appealed to his followers in terms which might equally well have been used by so thorough-going a believer in the power of the human will as Mussolini or by any other leader of any period: ‘At the decisive moment and in the decisive place, you must prove the stronger, you must be victorious.’10 Every realist, whatever his profession, is ultimately compelled to believe not only that there is something which man ought to think and do, but that there is something which he can think and do, and that his thought and action are neither mechanical nor meaningless.

We return therefore to the conclusion that any sound political thought must be based on elements of both utopia and reality. Where utopianism has become a hollow and intolerable sham, which serves merely as a disguise for the interests of the privileged, the realist performs an indispensable service in unmasking it. But pure realism can offer nothing but a naked struggle for power which makes any kind of international society impossible. Having demolished the current utopia with the weapons of realism, we still need to build a new utopia of our own, which will one day fall to the same weapons. The human will will continue to seek an escape from the logical consequences of realism in the vision of an international order which, as soon as it crystallizes itself into concrete political form, becomes tainted with self-interest and hypocrisy, and must once more be attacked with the instruments of realism.

Here, then, is the complexity, the fascination and the tragedy of all political life. Politics are made up of two elements – utopia and reality – belonging to two different planes which can never meet. There is no greater barrier to clear political thinking than failure to distinguish between ideals, which are utopia, and institutions, which are reality. The communist who set communism against democracy was usually thinking of communism as a pure ideal of equality and brotherhood, and of democracy as an institution which existed in Great Britain, France or the United States and which exhibited the vested interests, the inequalities and the oppression inherent in all political institutions. The democrat who made the same comparison was in fact comparing an ideal pattern of democracy laid up in heaven with communism as an institution existing in Soviet Russia with class divisions, its heresy hunts and its concentration camps. The comparison, made in each case between an ideal and an institution, is irrelevant and makes no sense. The ideal, once it is embodied in an institution, ceases to be an ideal and becomes the expression of a selfish interest, which must be destroyed in the name of a new ideal. This constant interaction of irreconcilable forces is the stuff of politics. Every political situation contains mutually incompatible elements of utopia and reality, of morality and power.

This point will emerge more clearly from the analysis of the nature of politics which we have now to undertake.

Notes

1.

|   |

Treitschke, Aufsätze, iv. p. 428.

2.

|   |

Engels, Ludwig Feuerbach (Engl. transl.), p. 23.

3.

|   |

Marx and Engels, Works (Russian ed.), xv. p. 275.

4.

|   |

Laski, Communism, p. 250.

5.

|   |

R. Neibuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 81.

6.

|   |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 231.

7.

|   |

Anti-Machiavel, p. 248.

8.

|   |

Schopenhauer, Welt als Wille und Vorstellung, ii. ch. 38.

9.

|   |

Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.), xxv. p. 340.

10.

|   |

Lenin, Collected Works (Engl. transl.), xxi. pt. i. p. 68.

CHAPTER NINE

Morality in International Politics

The place of morality in international politics is the most obscure and difficult problem in the whole range of international studies. Two reasons for its obscurity, one general and one particular, may be suggested.

In the first place, most discussions about morality are obscured by the fact that the term is commonly used to connote at least three different things:

(i)

|   |

The moral code of the philosopher, which is the kind of morality most rarely practised but most frequently discussed.

(ii)

|   |

The moral code of the ordinary man, which is sometimes practised but rarely discussed (for the ordinary man seldom examines the moral assumptions which underlie his actions and his judgements and, if he does, is peculiarly liable to self-deception).

(iii)

|   |

The moral behaviour of the ordinary man, which will stand in fairly close relation to (ii), but in hardly any relation at all to (i).

It may be observed that the relationship between (ii) and (iii) is mutual. Not only is the behaviour of the ordinary man influenced by his moral code, but his moral code is influenced by the way in which ordinary men, including himself, behave. This is particularly true of the ordinary man’s view of political morality, which tends, more than personal morality, to be a codification of existing practice, and in which the expectation of reciprocity always plays an important part.

The monopoly of international studies between the two wars by the utopian school resulted in a concentration of interest on discussions of the question what international morality ought ideally to be. There was little discussion of the moral behaviour of states except to pass hasty and sweeping condemnation on it in the light of this ideal morality. There was no discussion at all of the assumptions of the ordinary man about international morality. This was particularly unfortunate at a period in which the popularization of politics for the first time made the assumptions of the ordinary man a matter of primary importance; and the ever-widening rift between the international utopia and international reality might have been described in terms of this divergence between the theory of the philosopher and practice based on the unexpressed and often unconscious assumptions of the ordinary man. Moreover, utopia met its usual fate in becoming, unknown to itself, the tool of vested interests. International morality, as expounded by most contemporary Anglo-Saxon writers, became little more than a convenient weapon for belabouring those who assailed the status quo. Here as elsewhere, the student of international politics cannot wholly divest himself of utopianism. But he will be well advised to keep his feet on the ground and rigorously maintain contact between his ambitions for the future and the realities of the present. Nor should this be too difficult. The anthropologist who investigates the moral codes and behaviour of a cannibal tribe probably starts from the presupposition that cannibalism is undesirable, and is conscious of the desire that it should be abolished. But he may well be sceptical of the value of denunciations of cannibalism, and will in any case not mistake such denunciations for a scientific study of the subject. The same clarity of thought has not always distinguished students of international morality, who have generally preferred the role of the missionary to that of the scientist.

The second obscurity is peculiar to the international field. Strange as it may appear, writers on international morality are not agreed among themselves – and are not always clear in their own minds – whether the morality which they wish to discuss is the morality of states or the morality of individuals. This point is so vital to the whole discussion that it must be cleared up on the threshold of our enquiry.

The nature of international morality

The period of absolute personal rule in which the modern state first began to take shape was not much troubled by distinction between personal and state morality. The personal responsibility of the prince for acts of state could be assumed without any undue straining of the facts. Charles I may have been a good father and a bad king. But in both capacities, his acts could be treated as those of an individual.1 When, however, the growing complication of the state machine and the development of constitutional government made the personal responsibility of the monarch a transparent travesty, the personality (which seemed a necessary condition of moral responsibility) was transferred from the monarch to the state. Leviathan, as Hobbes said, is an ‘Artificial Man’. This was an important step forward. It was the personification of the state which made possible the creation of international law on the basis of natural law. States could be assumed to have duties to one another only in virtue of the fiction which treated them as if they were persons. But the personification of the state was a convenient way of conferring on it not merely duties, but rights; and with the growth of state power in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries state rights became more conspicuous than state duties. Thus the personification of the state, which began as a liberal and progressive device, came to be associated with the assertion of unlimited rights of the state over the individual and is now commonly denounced as reactionary and authoritarian. Modern utopian thinkers reject it with fervour,2 and are consequently led to deny that morality can be attributed to the state. International morality must, on this view, be the morality of individuals.

The controversy about the attribution of personality to the state is not only misleading, but meaningless. To deny personality to the state is just as absurd as to assert it. The personality of the state is not a fact whose truth or falsehood is a matter for argument. It is what international lawyers have called ‘the postulated nature’ of the state.3 It is a necessary fiction or hypothesis – an indispensable tool devised by the human mind for dealing with the structure of a developed society.4 It is theoretically possible to imagine a primitive political order in which individuals are individuals and nothing more, just as it is possible to imagine an economic order in which all producers and traders are individuals. But just as economic development necessitated resort to the fiction of corporate responsibility in such forms as that of the joint-stock company, so political development necessitated the fiction of the corporate responsibility of the state. Nor are the rights and obligations of these fictitious entities regarded as purely legal. A bank is praised for generosity to its employees, an armaments firm is attacked for unpatriotic conduct, and railways have ‘obligations to the public’ and demand a ‘square deal’ – all issues implying the relevance, not merely of legal, but of moral standards. The fiction of the group-person, having moral rights and obligations and consequently capable of moral behaviour, is an indispensable instrument of modern society; and the most indispensable of these fictitious group-persons is the state. In particular, it does not seem possible to discuss international politics in other terms. ‘Relations between Englishmen and Italians’ is not a synonym for ‘relations between Great Britain and Italy’. It is a curious and significant paradox that those utopian writers on international affairs who most vigorously denounce the personification of the state as absurd and sinister none the less persistently allocate moral praise and blame (generally the latter) to those imaginary entities, ‘Great Britain’, ‘France’ and ‘Italy’, whose existence they deny.

Continuity is another element in society which makes the fiction of the group-person indispensable. The keenest objectors to the personification of the state will have no qualms about celebrating the 150th anniversary of The Times or the 38th victory of ‘Cambridge’ in the boat race, and will confidently expect ‘the London County Council’ to repay, fifty years hence, money which ‘it’ borrows and spends to-day. Personification is the category of thought which expresses the continuity of institutions; and of all institutions the state is the one whose continuity it is most essential to express. The question whether the Belgian Guarantee Treaty of 1839 imposed an obligation on Great Britain to assist Belgium in 1914 raised both legal and moral issues. But it cannot be intelligently discussed except by assuming that the obligation rested neither personally on Palmerston who signed the treaty of 1839, nor personally on Asquith and Grey who had to decide the issue in 1914, neither on all individual Englishmen alive in 1839, nor on all individual Englishmen alive in 1914, but on that fictitious group-person ‘Great Britain’, which was regarded as capable of moral or immoral behaviour in honouring or dishonouring an obligation.5 In short, international morality is the morality of states. The hypothesis of state personality and state responsibility is neither true nor false, because it does not purport to be a fact, but a category of thought necessary to clear thinking about international relations. It is true that another moral issue was also raised in 1914 – the obligation of individual Englishmen. But this was an obligation to ‘Great Britain’, arising out of the obligation of ‘Great Britain’ to ‘Belgium’. The two obligations were distinct; and confused thinking is the inevitable penalty of failure to distinguish between them.

Curiously enough, this distinction seems to present more difficulty to the philosopher than to the ordinary man, who readily distinguishes between the obligation of the individual to the state, and the obligation of the state to another state. In 1935, the Opposition in the House of Commons denounced the Hoare-Laval Plan as ‘a terrible crime’. But it did not denounce Sir S. Hoare as a criminal or regard him as such; it found him guilty only of an error of judgement. In 1938, some Englishmen felt ‘ashamed’ of the Munich Agreement. They were not ‘ashamed’ of themselves; for they would have done anything in their power to prevent it. They were not ‘ashamed’ of Mr Chamberlain; for most of them admitted that he had acted honestly, though mistakenly, and one does not feel ‘ashamed’ of anyone who commits an honest mistake. They were ‘ashamed’ of ‘Great Britain’, whose reputation had, in their view, been lowered by a cowardly and unworthy act. In both these cases, the same act which (in the view of the critics) represented an intellectual failure on the part of the individual represented a moral failure on the part of ‘Great Britain’. The mot became current that the British loan of £10,000,000 to Czecho-Slovakia was ‘conscience money’. The essence of ‘conscience money’ is that it is paid by a moral delinquent; and the moral delinquent who paid the £10,000,000 was not Mr Chamberlain, and not those individual Englishmen who had applauded the Munich Agreement, but ‘Great Britain’. The obligation of the state cannot be identified with the obligation of any individual or individuals; and it is the obligations of states which are the subject of international morality.

Two objections are commonly raised to this view.

The first is that the personification of the state encourages the exaltation of the state at the expense of the individual. This objection, though it accounts for the disfavour into which the personification of the state has fallen among liberal thinkers, is trivial. The personification of the state is a tool; and to decry it on the ground of the use to which it is sometimes put is no more intelligent than to abuse a tool for killing a man. The tool can equally well be put to liberal uses through emphasis on the duty of the state both to the individual and to other states. Nor can democracy altogether dispense with personification as a means to emphasize the duty of the individual. The most sophisticated of us would probably shrink from paying taxes to a group of individual fellow-citizens, though we pay them with comparative alacrity to a personified state. The same applies with greater force to graver sacrifices. ‘You would never have got young men to sacrifice themselves for so unlucky a country as Ireland,’ said Parnell, ‘only that they pictured her as a woman.’6 ‘Who dies if England live?’ is not adequately paraphrased by ‘Who dies if other Englishmen live?’ Moreover, it is difficult to see how orderly international relations can be conducted at all unless Englishmen, Frenchmen and Germans believe (however absurd the belief may be) that ‘Great Britain’, ‘France’ and ‘Germany’ have moral duties to one another and a reputation to be enhanced by performing those duties. The spirit of international relations seems more likely to be improved by stimulating this belief than by decrying it. In any case, it is clear that human society will have to undergo a material change before it discovers some other equally convenient fiction to replace the personification of the political unit.

The second objection is more serious. If international morality is the morality of fictitious entities, is it not itself fictitious and unreal? We can at once accept the view that moral behaviour can only proceed from individuals. To deny that ‘relations between Great Britain and Italy’ means the same as ‘relations between Englishmen and Italians’ is not to deny that ‘relations between Great Britain and Italy’ depend on the actions of individual Englishmen and Italians. The moral behaviour of the state is a hypothesis; but we need not regard as ‘unreal’ a hypothesis which is accepted in certain contexts as a guide to individual behaviour and does in fact influence that behaviour. So long as statesmen, and others who influence the conduct of international affairs, agree in thinking that the state has duties, and allow this view to guide their action, the hypothesis remains effective. The acts with which international morality is concerned are performed by individuals not on their own behalf, but on behalf of those fictitious group persons ‘Great Britain’ and ‘Italy’, and the morality in question is the morality attributed to those ‘persons’. Any useful examination of international morality must start from recognition of this fact.

Theories of international morality

Before we consider the moral assumptions which underlie current thinking about international affairs, we must take some account of current theories of international morality. For though it is the assumptions of the ordinary man, not the assumptions of the philosopher, which determine the accepted moral code and govern moral behaviour, the theories of philosophers also exercise an influence on the thought (and, less frequently, on the action) of the ordinary man, and cannot be left altogether out of the picture. Theories of international morality tend to fall into two categories. Realists – and, as we have seen, some who are not realists – hold that relations between states are governed solely by power and that morality plays no part in them. The opposite theory, propounded by most utopian writers, is that the same code of morality is applicable to individuals and to states.

The realist view that no ethical standards are applicable to relations between states can be traced from Machiavelli through Spinoza and Hobbes to Hegel, in whom it found its most finished and thorough-going expression. For Hegel, states are completely and morally self-sufficient entities; and relations between them express only the concordance or conflict of independent wills not united by any mutual obligation. The converse view that the same standard is applicable to individuals and to states was implicit in the original conception of the personification of the state and has found frequent expression not only in the writings of philosophers, but in the utterances of statesmen of utopian inclinations. ‘The moral law was not written for men alone in their individual character,’ said Bright in a speech on foreign policy in 1858, ‘. . . it was written as well for nations.’7 ‘We are at the beginning of an age’, said Woodrow Wilson in his address to Congress on the declaration of war in 1917, ‘in which it will be insisted that the same standards of conduct and of responsibility for wrong shall be observed among nations and their governments that are observed among the individual citizens of civilized states.’8 And when in July 1918 the faithful House tried his hand at the first draft of a League of Nations, Article I ran as follows:

The same standards of honour and ethics shall prevail internationally and in affairs of nations as in other matters. The agreement or promise of a power shall be inviolate.9

No corresponding pronouncement was included in the Covenant. But Dr Benes at one of the early Assemblies remarked that the League was ‘ipso facto an attempt to introduce into international relationships the principles and methods employed . . . in the mutual relations of private individuals’.10 In his famous Chicago speech of 5 October 1937, President Roosevelt declared that ‘national morality is as vital as private morality’.11 But he did not specifically identify them.

Neither the realist view that no moral obligations are binding on states, nor the utopian view that states are subject to the same moral obligations as individuals, corresponds to the assumptions of the ordinary man about international morality. Our task is now to examine these assumptions.

Ordinary assumptions about international morality

It is noteworthy that the attempt to deny the relevance of ethical standards to international relations has been made almost exclusively by the philosopher, not by the statesman or the man in the street. Some recognition of an obligation to our fellow-men as such seems implicit in our conception of civilization; and the idea of certain obligations automatically incumbent on civilized men has given birth to the idea of similar (though not necessarily identical) obligations incumbent on civilized nations. A state which does not conform to certain standards of behaviour towards its own citizens and, more particularly, towards foreigners will be branded as ‘uncivilized’. Even Hitler in one of his speeches declined to conclude a pact with Lithuania ‘because we cannot enter into political treaties with a state which disregards the most primitive laws of human society’;12 and he frequently alleged the immorality of Bolshevism as a reason for excluding Soviet Russia from the family of nations. All agree that there is an international moral code binding on states. One of the most important and most clearly recognized items in this code is the obligation not to inflict unnecessary death or suffering on other human beings, i.e. death or suffering not necessary for the attainment of some higher purpose which is held, rightly or wrongly, to justify a derogation from the general obligation. This is the foundation of most of the rules of war, the earliest and most developed chapter of international law; and these rules were generally observed in so far as they did not impede the effective conduct of military operations.13 A similar humanitarian motive inspired international conventions for the protection of the ‘backward races’ or of national minorities, and for the relief of refugees.

The obligations so far mentioned have been obligations of the state to individuals. But the obligation of state to state is also clearly recognized. The number of synonyms current in international practice for what used to be called ‘the comity of nations’14 shows the persistence of the belief that states are members of a comity and have obligations as such. A new state on becoming, in virtue of recognition by other Powers, a member of the international community, is assumed to regard itself as automatically bound, without any express stipulation, by the accepted rules of international law and canons of international morality. As we have seen, the concept of internationalism was so freely used between the two wars for the purpose of justifying the ascendancy of the satisfied Powers that it fell into some disrepute with the dissatisfied Powers. But this natural reaction was not a denial of the existence of an international community so much as a protest against exclusion from the privileges of membership. The result of the Versailles Treaty, wrote Dr Goebbels, was ‘to expel Germany from the comity of powerful political countries’, and the function of National Socialism was to ‘unite the people and once more lead it back to its rightful place in the comity of nations’.15 During Hitler’s visit to Rome in May 1938, Mussolini declared that the common aim of Italy and Germany was ‘to seek between them and with others a regime of international comity which may restore equally for all more effective guarantees of justice, security and peace’.16 Constant appeals were made by both these Powers to the injustice of the conditions imposed on them in the past and the justice of demands now made by them; and many people in these countries were beyond doubt sincerely and passionately concerned to justify their policy in the light of universal standards of international morality.

In particular, the theory that, since states have no moral obligations towards one another, treaties have no binding force, is not held even by those statesmen who exhibit least taste for international co-operation. Every state concludes treaties in the expectation that they will be observed; and states which violate treaties either deny that they have done so, or else defend the violation by argument designed to show that it was legally or morally justified. The Soviet Government in the first years of its existence openly violated not only treaties signed by previous Russian governments, but the treaty which it had itself signed at Brest-Litovsk, and propounded a philosophy which seemed to deny international obligation and international morality. But it simultaneously concluded, and offered to conclude, other treaties with the manifest intention of observing them and expecting others to observe them. The German Government accompanied its violation of the Locarno Treaty in 1936 with an offer to enter into a fresh treaty. In neither case is it necessary to doubt the sincerity of the government concerned. Violation of treaties, even when frequently practised, is felt to be something exceptional requiring special justification. The general sense of obligation remains.

The view that the same ethical standard is applicable to the behaviour of states as to that of individuals is, however, just as far from current belief as the view that no standard at all applies to states. The fact is that most people, while believing that states ought to act morally, do not expect of them the same kind of moral behaviour which they expect of themselves and one another.

Many utopian thinkers have been so puzzled by this phenomenon that they have refused to recognize it. Others have sincerely confessed their bewilderment. ‘Men’s morals are paralysed when it comes to international conduct,’ observes Professor Dewey;17 and Professor Zimmern detects a ‘rooted prejudice against law and order in the international domain’.18 The discrepancy is less surprising than it appears at first sight. Casuists have long been familiar with the problem of incompatibilities between personal, professional and commercial morality. International morality is another category with standards which are in part peculiar to itself. Some of the problems of state morality are common to the whole field of the morality of group persons. Others are peculiar to the state in virtue of its position as the supreme holder of political power. The analogy between the state and other group persons is therefore useful, but not decisive.

Differences between individual and state morality

We may now turn to the principal reasons why states are not ordinarily expected to observe the same standards of morality as individuals.

(1) There is the initial difficulty of ascribing to the state, or to any other group person, love, hate, jealousy and other intimate emotions which play a large part in individual morality. It seems plainly incongruous to say, as an eighteenth-century writer said, that ‘a nation must love other nations as itself’.19 For this reason, it is sometimes argued that the morality of the state must be confined to that formal kind of morality which can be codified in a set of rules and approximates to law, and that it cannot include such essentially personal qualities as altruism, generosity and compassion, whose obligations can never be precisely and rigidly defined. The state, like a public corporation, can – it is commonly said – be just, but not generous. This does not seem to be entirely true. We have already noted that group persons are commonly assumed to have moral as well as legal rights and obligations. When a bank or a public company subscribes to a Lord Mayor’s Fund for assistance to victims of some great disaster, the act of generosity must be attributed not to the directors, whose pockets are not affected, and not to the shareholders, who are neither consulted nor informed, but to the bank or company itself. When the Treasury makes a ‘compassionate grant’ in some case of hardship, the act of compassion is performed not by the official who takes the decision, and not by the Chancellor of the Exchequer in his individual capacity, but by the state. Some people expected ‘the United States’ to remit the debts owing to them from European states after the first world war, and criticized their refusal to do so on moral grounds. In other words, paradoxical as it may appear, we do, in certain circumstances, expect states and other group persons, not merely to comply with their formal obligations, but to behave generously and compassionately. And it is precisely this expectation which produces moral behaviour on behalf of a fictitious entity like a bank or a state. Banks subscribe to charitable funds and states make compassionate grants because public opinion expects it of them. The moral impulse may be traced back to individuals. But the moral act is the act of the group person.

Nevertheless, while most people accept the hypothesis that group persons have in certain conditions a moral duty to act altruistically as well as justly, the duty of the group person appears by common consent to be more limited by self-interest than the duty of the individual. In theory, the individual who sacrifices his interests or even his life for the good of others is morally praiseworthy, though this duty might be limited by duty to family or dependents. The group person is not commonly expected to indulge in altruism at the cost of any serious sacrifice of its interests. A bank or public company which failed to pay dividends owing to generous contributions to charities would probably be thought worthy of censure rather than praise. In his presidential campaign of 1932, Franklin Roosevelt referred tauntingly to Mr Hoover’s reputation for humanitarian activities in Europe, and invited him to ‘turn his eyes from his so-called “backward and crippled countries” to the great and stricken markets of Kansas, Nebraska, Iowa, Wisconsin and other agricultural states’.20 It is not the ordinarily accepted moral duty of a state to lower the standard of living of its citizens by throwing open its frontiers to an unlimited number of foreign refugees, though it may be its duty to admit as large a number as is compatible with the interests of its own people. British supporters of the League of Nations who urged Great Britain to render assistance to victims of ‘aggression’ did not maintain that she should do this even to the detriment of her vital interests; they argued that she should render the assistance which she could reasonably afford21 (just as a bank can reasonably afford to give 500 guineas to the victims of an earthquake). The accepted standard of international morality in regard to the altruistic virtues appears to be that a state should indulge in them in so far as this is not seriously incompatible with its more important interests. The result is that secure and wealthy groups can better afford to behave altruistically than groups which are continually preoccupied with the problem of their own security and solvency; and this circumstance provides such basis as there is for the assumption commonly made by Englishmen and Americans that the policies of their countries are morally more enlightened than those of other countries.

(2) It is, however, not merely true that the ordinary man does not demand from the group person certain kinds of moral behaviour which are demanded from the individual; he expects from the group person certain kinds of behaviour which he would definitely regard as immoral in the individual. The group is not only exempt from some of the moral obligations of the individual, but is definitely associated with pugnacity and self-assertion, which become positive virtues of the group person. The individual seeks strength through combination with others in the group; and his ‘devotion to his community always means the expression of a transferred egoism as well as of altruism’.22 If he is strong, he converts the group to the pursuit of his own ends. If he is weak, he finds compensation for his own lack of power to assert himself in the vicarious self-assertion of the group. If we cannot win ourselves, we want our side to win. Loyalty to the group comes to be regarded as a cardinal virtue of the individual, and may require him to condone behaviour by the group person which he would condemn in himself. It becomes a moral duty to promote the welfare, and further the interests, of the group as a whole; and this duty tends to eclipse duty to a wider community. Acts which would be immoral in the individual may become virtue when performed on behalf of the group person. ‘If we were to do for ourselves what we are doing for Italy,’ said Cavour to D’Azeglio, ‘we should be great rogues.’23 The same could truthfully have been said by many directors of public companies and promoters of good causes. ‘There is an increasing tendency among modern men’, writes Dr Niebuhr, ‘to imagine themselves ethical because they have delegated their vices to larger and larger groups.’24 In the same way we delegate our animosities. It is easier for ‘England’ to hate ‘Germany’ than for individual Englishmen to hate individual Germans. It is easier to be anti-Semitic than to hate individual Jews. We condemn such emotions in ourselves as individuals, but indulge them without scruple in our capacity as members of a group.

(3) These considerations apply in some measure to all group persons, though they apply with particular force to the state. There are, however, other respects in which we do not ordinarily demand from the state even the same standard of moral behaviour which we demand from other group persons. The state makes an altogether different kind of emotional appeal to its members from that of any other group person. It covers a far larger field of human activities, and demands from the individual a far more intensive loyalty and far graver sacrifices. The good of the state comes more easily to be regarded as a moral end in itself. If we are asked to die for our country, we must at least be allowed to believe that our country’s good is the most important thing in the world. The state thus comes to be regarded as having a right of self-preservation which overrides moral obligation. In the Cambridge History of British Foreign Policy published after the war, Professor Holland Rose condones the ‘discreditable episode’ of the seizure of the Danish fleet at Copenhagen in 1807 on the ground of Canning’s belief that ‘the very existence of Great Britain was at stake’.25 Those who take a different view commonly argue that Canning was mistaken, not that he should have acted otherwise if his belief had been correct.

Other differences between the standards of morality commonly expected of the state and of other group persons arise from the fact that the state is the repository of political power and that there is no authority above the state capable of imposing moral behaviour on it, as a certain minimum of moral behaviour is imposed on other group persons by the state. One corollary of this is that we are bound to concede to the state a right of self-help in remedying its just grievances. Another corollary is the difficulty of securing the observance by all of a common standard; for while some moral obligations are always thought of as absolute, there is a strong tendency to make the imperativeness of moral obligations dependent on a reasonable expectation of the performance of the same duty by others. Conventions play an important part in all morality; and the essence of a convention is that it is binding so long as other people in fact abide by it. Barclays Bank or Imperial Chemicals Limited would incur moral censure if they employed secret agents to steal confidential documents from the safes of rival institutions, since such methods are not habitually employed by public companies against one another. But no stigma attaches to ‘Great Britain’ or ‘Germany’ for acting in this manner; for such practices are believed to be common to all the Great Powers, and a state which did not resort to them might find itself at a disadvantage. Spinoza argued that states would do likewise if it suited their interest.26 One reason why a higher standard of morality is not expected of states is because states in fact frequently fail to behave morally and because there are no means of compelling them to do so.

(4) This brings us to the most fundamental difficulty which confronts us in our analysis of the moral obligations currently attributed to the state. It is commonly accepted that the morality of group persons can only be social morality (a state or a limited liability company cannot be a saint or a mystic); and social morality implies duty to fellow members of a community, whether that community be a family, a church, a club, a nation or humanity itself. ‘No individual can make a conscience for himself,’ writes T. H. Green; ‘he always needs a society to make it for him.’27 In what sense can we find a basis for international morality by positing a society of states?

Is there an international community?

Those who deny the possibility of an international morality naturally contest the existence of an international community. The English Hegelian Bosanquet, who may be taken as a typical representative of this view, argues that ‘the nation state is the widest organization which has the common experience necessary to found a common life’,28 and rejects with emphasis ‘the assumption that humanity is a real corporate being, an object of devotion and a guide to moral duty’.29 The reply to this would appear to be that a corporate being is never ‘real’ except as a working hypothesis, and that whether a given corporate being is an object of devotion and a guide to moral duty is a question of fact which must be settled by observation and not by theory, and which may be answered differently at different times and places. It has already been shown that there is in fact a widespread assumption of the existence of a worldwide community of which states are the units and that the conception of the moral obligations of states is closely bound up with this assumption. There is a world community for the reason (and for no other) that people talk, and within certain limits behave, as if there were a world community. There is a world community because, as Senor de Madariaga put it, ‘we have smuggled that truth into our store of spiritual thinking without preliminary discussion’.30

On the other hand, it would be a dangerous illusion to suppose that this hypothetical world community possesses the unity and coherence of communities of more limited size up to and including the state. If we examine the ways in which the world community falls short of this standard of coherence, we shall have a clue to the underlying reasons for the shortcomings of international morality. It falls short mainly in two ways: (i) the principle of equality between members of the community is not applied, and is indeed not easily applicable, in the world community, and (ii) the principle that the good of the whole takes precedence over the good of the part, which is a postulate of any fully integrated community, is not generally accepted.

The principle of equality

(i) The principle of equality within a community is difficult to define. Equality is never absolute, and may perhaps be defined as an absence of discrimination for reasons which are felt to be irrelevant. In Great Britain, the reasons for which some receive higher incomes or pay more taxes than others are (rightly or wrongly) felt to be relevant even by most of those in the less-favoured categories, and the principle of equality is not therefore infringed. But the principle would be infringed, and the community broken, if people with blue eyes were less favourably treated than people with brown, or people from Surrey than people from Hampshire. In many countries, minorities are discriminated against on grounds which they feel to be irrelevant, and these minorities cease to feel, and to be regarded, as members of the community.31

In the international community such discrimination is endemic. It arises in the first place from the attitude of individuals. Gladstone is said on one occasion to have exhorted an audience of his fellow-countrymen to ‘remember that the sanctity of life in the villages of the Afghan mountains among the winter snows is no less inviolable in the eyes of the Almighty than your own’.32 It may safely be said that the eyes of the Almighty are not in this respect those of the great majority of Englishmen. Most men’s sense of common interest and obligation is keener in respect of family and friends than in respect of others of their fellow-countrymen, and keener in respect of their fellow-countrymen than of other people. Family and friends form a ‘face-to-face’ group, between whom the sense of moral obligation is most likely to be strong. The members of a modern nation are enabled, through a more or less uniform education, a popular national press, broadcasting and travel facilities, and a skilful use of symbols,33 to acquire something of the character of a ‘face-to-face’ group. The ordinary Englishman carries in his mind a generalized picture of the behaviour, daily life, thoughts and interests of other Englishmen, whereas he has no such picture at all of the Greek or the Lithuanian. Moreover, the vividness of his picture of ‘foreigners’ will commonly vary in relation to geographical, racial and linguistic proximity, so that the ordinary Englishman will be likely to feel that he has something, however slight, in common with the German or the Australian and nothing at all in common with the Chinese or the Turk.34 An American newspaper correspondent in Europe is said to have laid down the rule that an accident was worth reporting if it involved the death of one American, five Englishmen, or ten Europeans. We all apply, consciously or unconsciously, some such standard of relative values. ‘If it was not that China was so far away,’ said Neville Chamberlain in the House of Commons on the occasion of Japanese bombing of Chinese cities, ‘and that the scenes which were taking place there were so remote from our everyday consciousness, the sentiments of pity, horror and indignation which would be aroused by a full observation of those events might drive this people to courses which perhaps they had never yet contemplated.’35 The same motif recurred in his national broadcast during the Czecho-Slovak crisis on 27 September 1938; ‘How horrible, fantastic, incredible it is that we should be digging trenches and trying on gas-masks here because of a quarrel in a far-away country between people of whom we know nothing.’36 These words were criticized in many quarters. But there is little doubt that they represented the initial reaction of the ordinary Englishman. Our normal attitude to foreigners is a complete negation of that absence of discrimination on irrelevant grounds which we have recognized as the principle of equality.

This attitude of the individual is reflected in the attitude of states to one another; and the difficulty is intensified by the structure of the international community. Even if equality between individuals of different countries were recognized, the inequalities between states would be none the less flagrant. The existing inequalities among a handful of known states subject to no external control are infinitely more glaring, more permanent and more difficult to forget than inequalities between the anonymous mass of citizens subject, at any rate in name, to the same law. The importance attached to the idea of equality in international politics is shown by the number and insistence of the demands based on it. ‘Most-favoured-nation treatment’, the ‘Open Door’, ‘freedom of the seas’, the Japanese claim for the recognition of racial equality in the Covenant of the League of Nations, the old German claim to ‘a place in the sun’, the more recent German claim to Gleichberecbtigung or ‘equality of status’, have all been demands for the application of the principle of equality. The praises of equality were repeatedly sung in the Assemblies and Committees of the League of Nations – mainly, if not exclusively, by delegates of minor Powers.37 Yet there is little attempt at consistency in the use of the term. Sometimes it merely means formal equality of states before the law. In other contexts, it may mean equality of rights, or equality of opportunity or equality of possessions. Sometimes it seems to mean equality between Great Powers. When Hitler argued that ‘according to all common sense, logic and the general principles of high human justice . . . all peoples ought to have an equal share of the goods of the world’,38 he hardly intended to convey that Lithuania ought to enjoy as much of ‘the goods of the world’ as Germany. Yet if we assume that equality of rights or privileges means proportionate, not absolute, equality, we are little advanced so long as there is no recognized criterion for determining the proportion. Nor would even this help us much. The trouble is not that Guatemala’s rights and privileges are only proportionately, not absolutely, equal to those of the United States, but that such rights and privileges as Guatemala has are enjoyed only by the good will of the United States. The constant intrusion, or potential intrusion, of power renders almost meaningless any conception of equality between members of the international community.

The good of the whole and the good of the part

(ii) The other capital shortcoming of the international community is failure to secure general acceptance of the postulate that the good of the whole takes precedence over the good of the part. Great Britain possesses a common national consciousness because the man from Surrey will normally act on the assumption that the good of Great Britain is more important than the good of Surrey. One of the chief obstacles to the growth of a common German national consciousness was the difficulty in persuading Prussians, Saxons and Bavarians to treat the good of Germany as more important than the good of Prussia, Saxony and Bavaria. Now it is clear that, despite pious aspirations, people still hesitate to act on the belief that the good of the world at large is greater than the good of their own country. Loyalty to a world community is not yet powerful enough to create an international morality which will override vital national interests. Yet the conception of a community implies recognition of its good as something which its members are under an obligation to promote, and the conception of morality implies the recognition of principles of a universally binding character. If we refuse altogether to recognize the overriding claims of the whole, can any world community or any kind of international morality be said to exist at all?

This is the fundamental dilemma of international morality. On the one hand, we find the almost universal recognition of an international morality involving a sense of obligation to an international community or to humanity as a whole. On the other hand, we find an almost equally universal reluctance to admit that, in this international community, the good of the part (i.e. our own country) can be less important than the good of the whole. This dilemma is, in practice, resolved in two different ways. The first is the method, which Hitler borrowed from the Darwinian school, of identifying the good of the whole with the good of the fittest. The fittest are by assumption ‘the bearers of a higher ethic’;39 and it is only necessary to prove in action that one’s country is the fittest in order to establish the identity of its good with the good of the whole. The other method is that of the neo-liberal doctrine of the harmony of interests, of which Woodrow Wilson, Lord Cecil and Professor Toynbee have been quoted as representatives. This doctrine, like every doctrine of a natural harmony of interests, identifies the good of the whole with the security of those in possession. When Woodrow Wilson declared that American principles were the principles of mankind, or Professor Toynbee that the security of the British Empire was ‘the supreme interest of the whole world’,* they were in effect making the same claim made by Hitler that their countrymen are ‘the bearers of a higher ethic’; and the same result is produced of identifying the good of the whole international community with the good of that part of it in which we are particularly interested. Both these methods are equally fatal to any effective conception of international morality.

There is no escape from the fundamental dilemma that every community, and every code of morality, postulates some recognition that the good of the part may have to be sacrificed to the good of the whole. The more explicitly we face this issue in the international community, the nearer we shall be to a solution of our problem. The analogy of the national community, though imperfect, is once more helpful. Modern liberalism, wrote Hobhouse shortly before 1914, ‘postulates, not that there is an actually existing harmony requiring nothing but prudence and judgement for its effective operation, but only that there is a possible ethical harmony to which . . . men might attain, and that in such attainment lies the social ideal’.40 The word ‘ethical’ betrays the break in the argument. The nineteenth-century ‘harmony requiring nothing but prudence and judgement for its effective operation’ was a harmony of interests. The ‘ethical harmony’ is one achieved by the sacrifice of interests, which is necessary precisely because no natural harmony of interests exists. In the national community, appeals to self-sacrifice are constantly and successfully made, even when the sacrifice asked for is the sacrifice of life. But even in the national community, it would be erroneous to suppose that the so-called ‘harmony’ is established solely through voluntary self-sacrifice. The sacrifice required is frequently a forced one, and the ‘harmony’ is based on the realistic consideration that it is in the ‘interest’ of the individual to sacrifice voluntarily what would otherwise be taken from him by force. Harmony in the national order is achieved by this blend of morality and power.

In the international order, the role of power is greater and that of morality less. When self-sacrifice is attributed to an individual, the sacrifice may or may not be purely voluntary. When self-sacrifice is attributed to a state, the chances are greater that this alleged self-sacrifice will turn out on inspection to be a forced submission to a stronger power. Yet even in international relations, self-sacrifice is not altogether unknown. Many concessions made by Great Britain to the Dominions cannot be explained in terms either of British interests or of submission to the stronger. Concessions made by Great Britain to Germany in the nineteen-twenties, ineffective as they were, were dictated, not wholly by British interests or by fear of Germany’s strength, but by a belief in some conception of international morality which was independent of British interests. Any international moral order must rest on some hegemony of power. But this hegemony, like the supremacy of a ruling class within the state, is in itself a challenge to those who do not share it; and it must, if it is to survive, contain an element of give and take, of self-sacrifice on the part of those who have, which will render it tolerable to the other members of the world community. It is through this process of give and take, of willingness not to insist on all the prerogatives of power, that morality finds its surest foothold in international – and perhaps also in national – politics. It is, no doubt, useless to begin by expecting far-reaching sacrifices. The standard of what we can reasonably afford must not be pitched too high. But the course most detrimental to international morality is surely to pretend that the German people are the bearers of a higher ethic, or that American principles are the principles of humanity, or that the security of Great Britain is the supreme good of the world, so that no sacrifices at all by one’s own nation are in fact necessary. When Professor Zimmern urges ‘the ordinary man’ to ‘enlarge his vision so as to bear in mind that the public affairs of the twentieth century are world affairs’,41 the most concrete meaning which can be given to this injunction is that the recognition of the principle of self-sacrifice, which is commonly supposed to stop short at the national frontier, should be extended beyond it. It is not certain that ordinary man will remain deaf to such an appeal. If the Chancellor of the Exchequer were to attempt to justify an increase in the income tax on the ground that it would make us better off, we should dismiss him as a humbug; and this is the kind of argument which is almost invariably used to justify any international policy involving apparent sacrifice of interests. A direct appeal to the need of self-sacrifice for a common good might sometimes prove more effective.

But it is necessary to clear up a further point on which many illusions are current. In the national community, we assume that in this process of self-sacrifice and give and take the giving must come principally from those who profit most by the existing order. In the international community, the assumption is commonly made by statesmen and writers of the satisfied Powers that the process of give and take operates only within the existing order and that sacrifices should be made by all to maintain that order. International peace, said Mr Eden once, must be ‘based on an international order with the nations leagued together to preserve it’; and to this international peace ‘each nation makes its own contribution because it recognizes that therein lies its own enduring interest’.42 The fallacy latent in this and many similar pronouncements is fatal to any workable conception of international morality. The process of give and take must apply to challenges to the existing order. Those who profit most by that order can in the long run only hope to maintain it by making sufficient concessions to make it tolerable to those who profit by it least; and the responsibility for seeing that these changes take place as far as possible in an orderly way rests as much on the defenders as on the challengers. This leads us to an examination of the problems of law and change in international politics.

Notes

*

|    |

See pp. 72, 74.

1.

|    |

The Allied Governments in the Versailles Treaty attempted to revive this historic assumption by holding the ex-Kaiser personally responsible for acts of state; but the attempt was almost universally condemned as soon as passions began to cool. Modern dictatorships, however, helped to bring this conception back to fashion. Thus Professor Toynbee called the invasion of Abyssinia ‘Signor Mussolini’s deliberate personal sin’ (Survey of International Affairs, 1935, ii. p. 3), though he would probably have felt it incongruous to describe the Hoare–Laval Plan as the ‘personal sin’ of Sir S. Hoare or Laval.

2.

|    |

Duguit, for example, calls it ‘valueless and meaningless anthropomorphism’ (Traité de droit constitutionnel, i. ch. v).

3.

|    |

Hall, International Law (8th ed.), p. 50; Pearce Higgins, International Law and Relations, p. 38.

4.

|    |

This does not, of course, mean that the state is a necessary form of political organization, but only that, so long as the state is the accepted form, its personification is a necessary fiction. The same would apply to any other form (e.g. the class). The personification of the proletariat has gone far in Soviet Russia (e.g. the fiction that it ‘owns’ the means of production).

5.

|    |

A striking example of confused thinking on this subject occurred in a recent letter to The Times. Commenting on the alleged British obligation to France in 1914, a distinguished professor of history wrote that ‘Grey may have regarded his personal honour as involved in support of France, but he certainly did not think that of the Cabinet was’ (The Times, 28 February 1939). The promise, if any, to support France must have been given by Grey not on his own behalf, but on behalf of Great Britain. Unless he believed that the whole Cabinet was under the same obligation as himself to see that Great Britain’s promise was honoured, he could not properly have given it at all.

6.

|    |

Quoted in Democracy and War, ed. G. E. C. Catlin, p. 128.

7.

|    |

John Bright, Speeches on Questions of Public Policy, p. 479.

8.

|    |

Public Papers of Woodrow Wilson: War and Peace, i. p. II.

9.

|    |

Intimate Papers of Colonel House, ed. C. Seymour, iv. p. 28.

10.

|    |

League of Nations: Fourth Assembly, i. p. 144.

11.

|    |

International Conciliation, No. 334, p. 713.

12.

|    |

Speech in the Reichstag, 21 May 1935.

13.

|    |

The rules of war have since 1914 been exposed to an exacting test. The distinction between combatant and non-combatant grows less and less. A deliberate attack on so-called non-combatants may in fact promote important military objectives; and the conception of unnecessary suffering, which the belligerent is not entitled to inflict because it is not essential to his military purpose, becomes more and more restricted and difficult to sustain. In short, modern conditions of warfare are doing much to break down, in one important point, a previously existing and effective sense of universal obligation.

14.

|    |

Half a dozen synonyms, used quite indiscriminately, are quoted from recent documents by Dr G. Schwarzenberger (American Journal of International Law, xxxiii. p. 59). There is no reason to suspect sarcasm in the reference, in a Japanese Imperial Rescript of 1933, to ‘the fraternity of nations’.

15.

|    |

Völkischer Beobachter, 1 April 1939.

16.

|    |

The Times, 9 May 1938.

17.

|    |

Foreign Affairs, 15 March 1923, p. 95.

18.

|    |

Zimmern, Towards a National Policy, p. 137.

19.

|    |

Christian Wolff, quoted in H. Kraus, Staatsethos, p. 187.

20.

|    |

Speech at the Metropolitan Opera House, New York, reported in the New York Times, 4 November 1932.

21.

|    |

The League of Nations Union ‘advocates sanctions only in cases where the number and resources of the governments co-operating on the League’s behalf make it reasonably certain that the would-be aggressor will abandon his intention, so that war will not break out at all’ (Headway, December 1937, p. 232).

22.

|    |

R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, p. 40.

23.

|    |

Quoted in E. L. Woodward, Three Studies in European Conservatism, p. 297.

24.

|    |

R. Niebuhr, Atlantic Monthly, 1927, p. 639.

25.

|    |

Cambridge History of British Foreign Policy, i. pp. 363–4.

26.

|    |

Spinoza, Tractatus Politicus, iii. § 14.

27.

|    |

T. H. Green, Prolegomena to Ethics, p. 351.

28.

|    |

B. Bosanquet, The Philosophical Theory of the State, p. 320.

29.

|    |

B. Bosanquet, Social and International Ideals, p. 292.

30.

|    |

S. de Madariaga, The World’s Design, p. 3.

31.

|    |

It is only in recent times that there has begun to be even a presumption that all inhabitants of a territory are members of the community. Like Jews in Nazi Germany, the coloured inhabitants of the Union of South Africa are today not regarded as members of the community. In the United States, most white Southerners would hesitate to admit that the negroes are members of the community in the same sense as they are themselves.

32.

|    |

Quoted by the Delegate of Haiti in League of Nations: Fifteenth Assembly, 6th Committee, p. 43.

33.

|    |

‘Moral attitudes always develop most sensitively in person-to-person relationships. That is one reason why more inclusive loyalties, naturally more abstract than immediate ones, lose some of their power over the human heart; and why a shrewd society attempts to restore that power by making a person the symbol of the community’ (R. Niebuhr, Moral Man and Immoral Society, pp. 52–3).

34.

|    |

The variations of feeling are naturally also influenced by current political prejudices.

35.

|    |

House of Commons, 21 June 1938: Official Report, col. 936. A correspondent in The Times, commenting on ‘the inconsistencies of compassion’ in the international sphere, enquires whether ‘the world’s conscience’ regards ‘100 dead or destitute Chinese as equivalent to one persecuted Jew’, or whether it is ‘simply that the Jews are near at hand, while the Chinese are a very long way away, and yellow at that’ (The Times, 25 November 1938).

36.

|    |

N. Chamberlain, The Struggle for Peace, p. 275.

37.

|    |

Of the Great Powers only France, largely dependent for her position on the support of minor Powers, consistently advocated the principle of equality. ‘There is not, and we trust there never will be,’ said M. Blum on one occasion (League of Nations: Sixteenth Assembly, Part II, p. 28), ‘an order of precedence among the Powers forming the international community. Were a hierarchy of States to be established within the League of Nations . . . then the League would be ruined, both morally and materially’ – a remarkable statement in view of the hierarchical constitution of the Council.

38.

|    |

Speech in the Reichstag of 28 April 1939.

39.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 421.

40.

|    |

L. T. Hobhouse, Liberalism, p. 129.

41.

|    |

Zimmern, The Prospects of Civilisation, p. 26.

42.

|    |

Anthony Eden, Foreign Affairs, p. 197.

CHAPTER TEN

The Foundations of Law

No topic has been the subject of more confusion in contemporary thought about international problems than the relationship between politics and law. There is, among many people interested in international affairs, a strong inclination to treat law as something independent of, and ethically superior to, politics. ‘The moral force of law’ is contrasted with the implicitly immoral methods of politics. We are exhorted to establish ‘the rule of law’, to maintain ‘international law and order’ or to ‘defend international law’; and the assumption is made that, by so doing, we shall transfer our differences from the turbulent political atmosphere of self-interest to the purer, serener air of impartial justice. Before adhering to these popular conceptions, we must examine rather carefully the nature and function of law in the international community and its relation to international politics.

The nature of international law

International law differs from the municipal law of modern states in being the law of an undeveloped and not fully integrated community. It lacks three institutions which are essential parts of any developed system of municipal law: a judicature, an executive and a legislature.

(1) International law recognizes no court competent to give on any issue of law or fact decisions recognized as binding by the community as a whole. It has long been the habit of some states to make special agreements to submit particular disputes to an international court for judicial settlement. The Permanent Court of International Justice, set up under the Covenant of the League, represents an attempt to extend and generalize this habit. But the institution of the Court has not changed international law: it has merely created certain special obligations for states willing to accept them.

(2) International law has no agents competent to enforce observance of the law. In certain cases, it does indeed recognize the right of an aggrieved party, where a breach of the law has occurred, to take reprisals against the offender. But this is the recognition of a right of self-help, not the enforcement of a penalty by an agent of the law. The measures contemplated in Article 16 of the Covenant of the League, in so far as they can be regarded as punitive and not merely preventive, fall within this category.

(3) Of the two main sources of law – custom and legislation – international law knows only the former, resembling in this respect the law of all primitive communities. To trace the stages by which a certain kind of action or behaviour, from being customary, comes to be recognized as obligatory on all members of the community is the task of the social psychologist rather than of the jurist. But it is by some such process that international law has come into being. In advanced communities, the other source of law – direct legislation – is more prolific, and could not possibly be dispensed with in any modern state. So serious does this lack of international legislation appear that, in the view of some authorities, states do on certain occasions constitute themselves a legislative body, and many multilateral agreements between states are in fact ‘lawmaking treaties’ (traités-lois).1 This view is open to grave objections. A treaty, whatever its scope and content, lacks the essential quality of law: it is not automatically and unconditionally applicable to all members of the community whether they assent to it or not. Attempts have been made from time to time to embody customary international law in multilateral treaties between states. But the value of such attempts has been largely nullified by the fact that no treaty can bind a state which has not accepted it. The Hague Conventions of 1907 on the rules of war are sometimes treated as an example of international legislation. But these conventions were not only not binding on states which were not parties to them, but were not binding on the parties vis-a’ -vis states which were not parties. The Kellogg-Briand Pact is not, as is sometimes loosely said, a legislative act prohibiting war. It is an agreement between a large number of states ‘to renounce war as an instrument of national policy in their relations with one another’. International agreements are contracts concluded by states with one another in their capacity as subjects of international law, and not laws created by states in the capacity of international legislators. International legislation does not yet exist.

These shortcomings of international law, serious as they are, do not however deprive it of the title to be considered as law, of which it has all the essential characteristics. In particular, the relation of law to politics will be found to be the same in the international as in the national sphere.

It has been observed that the fundamental question of political philosophy is why men allow themselves to be ruled. The corresponding question which lies at the root of jurisprudence is why men obey the law. Why is law regarded as binding? The answer cannot be obtained from the law itself any more than a proof of Euclid’s postulates can be obtained from Euclid. Law proceeds on the assumption that the question has been satisfactorily disposed of. But it is a question which cannot be burked by those who seek to justify the ‘rule of law’. It applies to international as well as to municipal law. In international law, it sometimes takes the form of the question whether, and on what grounds, treaties are binding. The legal answer to this question is that treaties are binding in international law, which includes the rule (subject to some reservations which will be discussed presently) that treaties must be kept. But what the questioner probably means to ask is: Why is international law, and with it the rule that treaties must be kept, binding, and should they be regarded as binding at all? These are not questions which can be answered by international law. It is the purpose of this chapter to enquire in what domain the answer to them should be sought, and what that answer should be.

In approaching the problem of the ultimate authority of law, we shall find the same fundamental divergence which we have traced in the field of politics between utopians, who think in terms of ethics, and realists, who think in terms of power. Among students of law, the utopians are commonly known as ‘naturalists’, who find the authority of law in natural law, and the realists as ‘positivists’, who find the authority of law in the will of states. The terminology tends to become blurred and fluctuating. Some utopians purport to reject natural law, and adopt some other standard such as reason, utility, ‘objective right’,2 ‘ultimate sense of right’,3 or a ‘fundamental norm’. Conversely, some positivists such as Spinoza purport to accept natural law, but empty it of its meaning by virtually identifying it with the right of the stronger. Other positivists fly the colours of ‘the historical school of law’ or of ‘the economic interpretation of law’. But the fundamental divergence remains between those who regard law primarily as a branch of ethics, and those who regard it primarily as a vehicle of power.

The naturalist view of law

The naturalist view of law, like the utopian view of politics, has a longer history behind it than the positivist or realist view. In primitive communities, law is bound up with religion and, until a fairly late stage of human development, always appears to emanate from a god or a divinely appointed lawgiver. The secular civilization of the Greeks divorced law from religion, but not from morality. Greek thinkers found in the conception of natural law a higher unwritten law from which man-made law derived its validity and by which it could be tested. The acceptance of Christianity by the Roman Empire restored divine authority. Natural law was for a time identified with divine law, and it was only at the Renaissance that it resumed its independent role as a non-theological ethical standard. As we have seen, the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries revived in a new form the identification of natural law with reason. ‘Law in general’, says Montesquieu, ‘is human reason, inasmuch as it governs all the peoples of the earth.’4 It was under these auspices that modern international law was created by Grotius and his successors to meet the needs of the new nation-states which had arisen on the ruins of the mediaeval world. International law was therefore by origin strongly utopian. This was necessary and inevitable. The new conventions which came more or less effectively to govern relations between states grew no doubt out of practical needs. But they could never have secured as wide an acceptance as they did if they had not been treated as binding in virtue of natural law and universal reason. But here we shall note the recurrence of a paradox which is also apparent in the political field. Where practice is least ethical, theory becomes most utopian. Owing to the more primitive state of development of the international community, morality plays a smaller effective role in the practice of international law than of municipal law. In theories of international law, utopia tends to predominate over reality to an extent unparalleled in other branches of jurisprudence. Moreover, this tendency is greatest at periods when anarchy is most prevalent in the practice of nations. During the nineteenth century, a comparatively orderly period in international affairs, international jurisprudence took on a realist complexion. Since 1919, natural law has resumed its sway, and theories of international law have become more markedly utopian than at any previous time.

The modern view of natural law differs, however, in one important respect from the view which prevailed down to the end of the eighteenth century. Prior to that time, natural law had always been conceived as something essentially static, a fixed and eternal standard of right which must, in the nature of things, be the same yesterday, to-day and for ever. The historical tendency of nineteenth-century thought, which at first threatened to eclipse natural law altogether, gave it a new direction; and towards the end of the century there emerged the new conception of ‘natural law with a variable content’.5 Natural law, in this interpretation, connotes no longer something external, fixed and invariable, but men’s innate feeling at any given time or place for what ‘just law’ ought to be. This revised definition of natural law helps us a little. It gets over the old crux that slavery was at one time thought to be sanctioned, and at another time to be prohibited, by natural law, or that private property is in some places regarded as a natural right and in other places as an infringement of natural right. We are now asked to treat law as binding because it is an emanation not of some eternal ethical principle, but of the ethical principles of a given time and community. This is, at any rate, a part of the truth. The ethical character of the impulse which lies behind many rules of law, municipal and international, including the rule of international law that treaties should be kept, will not be denied by any reasonable person. The prevalence in most European languages of words which bestride the frontier between law and ethics betrays a widespread conviction of the close relationship between them.

Nevertheless, this explanation why law is regarded as binding will turn out, on further examination, to be inadequate and in some degree misleading. The main crux about natural law is not that people differ from time to time and from place to place about what particular rules it prescribes (for this crux might be surmounted by the ‘variable’ theory), but that natural law (or reason or ‘objective right’ or any of its other substitutes) can be just as easily invoked to incite disobedience to the law as to justify obedience to it. Natural law has always had two aspects and two uses. It can be invoked by conservatives to justify the existing order, as when the rights of the rulers or the rights of property are alleged to rest on natural law. It can equally be invoked by revolutionaries to justify rebellion against the existing order. There is in natural law an anarchic element which is the direct antithesis of law. Theories of law which seek the ultimate authority of law in its ethical content can explain only why good laws (or laws regarded as good at a given time and place) are regarded as binding. Yet there is a fairly general consensus of opinion which regards as binding even laws recognized as bad; and it may be doubted whether any community could long survive in which such an opinion did not prevail. It is commonly admitted that there may be a right or duty to disobey a bad law. But in such cases, a conflict is recognized to exist between two duties; and it is generally felt that only the most exceptional circumstances justify a decision in favour of the duty to disobey. No theory of law seems adequate which explains that law is regarded as binding because it conforms to natural law or because it is good.

The realist view of law

The positivist or realist view of law was first clearly and explicitly stated by Hobbes, who defined law as a command: Ius est quod iussum est. Law is thus divorced altogether from ethics. It may be oppressive or otherwise immoral. It is regarded as binding because there is an authority which enforces obedience to it. It is an expression of the will of the state, and is used by those who control the state as an instrument of coercion against those who oppose their power. The law is therefore the weapon of the stronger. That contradictory thinker Rousseau, who elsewhere treats law as the antithesis of despotism, has recorded this view in emphatic terms: ‘The spirit of the laws of all countries is always to favour the strong against the weak and him that has against him that has not. This drawback is inevitable, and there are no exceptions to it.’6 According to Marx, all law is a ‘law of inequality’.7 The principal contribution of Marxism to the problem is its insistence on the relativity of law. Law reflects not any fixed ethical standard, but the policy and interests of the dominant group in a given state at a given period. Law, as Lenin puts it, is ‘the formulation, the registration of power relations’ and ‘an expression of the will of the ruling class’.8 The realist view of the ultimate basis of law is well summed up by Professor Laski: ‘Legal rules are always seeking to accomplish an end deemed desirable by some group of men, and it is only by constant formulation of what that end is that we can obtain a realistic jurisprudence.’9

The realist answer to the question why law is regarded as binding contains, like the ‘naturalist’ answer, a part of the truth. Some people do in fact obey some laws because lawbreaking will bring them into unwelcome contact with the police and the courts. But no community could survive if most of its members were law-abiding only through an ever-present fear of punishment. As Laud says, ‘No laws can be binding if there be no conscience to them’;10 and there is plenty of evidence of the difficulty of enforcing laws which seriously offend the conscience of the community or of any considerable part of it. Law is regarded as binding because it represents the sense of right of the community: it is an instrument of the common good. Law is regarded as binding because it is enforced by the strong arm of authority: it can be, and often is, oppressive. Both these answers are true; and both of them are only half-truths.

Law as a function of political society

If then we wish to reconcile these contradictory and inadequate half-truths, and to find a single answer to the question why law is regarded as binding, we must seek it in the relationship of law to politics. Law is regarded as binding because, if it were not, political society could not exist and there could be no law. Law is not an abstraction. It ‘can only exist within a social framework…. Where there is law, there must be a society within which it is operative.’11 We need not dwell on the old controversy whether, as the positivists held, the state creates law, or as the naturalists held, law creates the state. It is sufficient to say that no political society can exist without law, and that law cannot exist except in a political society.12 The point has been clearly put by a contemporary German writer:

All law is always the expression of a community. Every legal community (Rechtsgemeinschaft) has a common view of law (Recht) determined by its content. It is an impossible undertaking to seek to construct a legal community without such a common view, or to establish a legal community before a minimum common view about the content of the community’s law has been attained.13

Politics and law are indissolubly intertwined; for the relations of man to man in society which are the subject-matter of the one are the subjectmatter of the other. Law, like politics, is a meeting place for ethics and power.

The same is true of international law, which can have no existence except in so far as there is an international community which, on the basis of a ‘minimum common view’, recognizes it as binding. International law is a function of the political community of nations. Its defects are due, not to any technical shortcomings, but to the embryonic character of the community in which it functions. Just as international morality is weaker than national morality, so international law is necessarily weaker and poorer in content than the municipal law of a highly organized modern state. The tiny number of states forming the international community creates the same special problem in law as in ethics. The evolution of general rules equally applicable to all, which is the basis of the ethical element in law, becomes extremely difficult. Rules, however general in form, will be constantly found to be aimed at a particular state or group of states; and for this reason, if for no other, the power element is more predominant and more obvious in international than in municipal law, whose subjects are a large body of anonymous individuals. The same consideration makes international law more frankly political than other branches of law.

Once therefore it is understood that law is a function of a given political order, whose existence alone can make it binding, we can see the fallacy of the personification of law implicit in such popular phrases as ‘the rule of law’ or ‘the government of laws and not of men’. The man in the street tends to personify law as something which, whether he approves it or not, he recognizes as binding on him; and this personification is as natural for everyday purposes as the personification of the state. It is, nevertheless, dangerous to clear thinking. Law cannot be self-contained; for the obligation to obey it must always rest on something outside itself. It is neither self-creating nor self-applying. ‘There are men who govern,’ says a Chinese philosopher, ‘but there are no laws that govern.’14 When Hegel finds the embodiment of the highest moral good in the state, we are entitled to ask, What state? or, better, Whose state? When modern writers on international politics find the highest moral good in the rule of law, we are equally entitled to ask, What law? and Whose law? The law is not an abstraction. It cannot be understood independently of the political foundation on which it rests and of the political interests which it serves.

We shall also have no difficulty in detecting the fallacy in the common illusion that law is more moral than politics. A transaction, by becoming legal, does not become moral. To pay a workman less than a living wage is not any more moral because the wage is fixed in a contract signed by the workman and valid in law. The annexations of French territory by Germany in 1871 and of German territory by the Allies in 1919 may have been moral or immoral. But they are not made any more moral by the fact that they were registered in treaties signed by the defeated Powers and valid in international law. It is not in itself any more moral to deprive Jews of their property by a law to that effect than simply to send storm troopers to evict them. The laws of the Medes and Persians were probably not conspicuously moral. If the law is ‘always seeking to accomplish an end deemed desirable by some group of men’, the ethical character of the law is obviously conditioned by that end. Political action can be, and often is, invoked to remedy immoral or oppressive law. The peculiar quality of law which makes it a necessity in every political society resides not in its subject-matter, nor in its ethical content, but in its stability. Law gives to society that element of fixity and regularity and continuity without which no coherent life is possible. It is the fundamental basis of organized political society that the rights and duties of citizens in relation both to one another and to the state should be defined by law. Law which is uncertain in its interpretation or capricious in its application fails to fulfil its essential function.

Stability and continuity are, however, not the only requisites of political life. Society cannot live by law alone, and law cannot be the supreme authority. The political arena is the scene of a more or less constant struggle between conservatives, who in a general way desire to maintain the existing legal situation, and radicals, who desire to change it in important respects; and conservatives, national and international, have the habit of posing as defenders of law and of decrying their opponents as assailants of it. In democracies, this struggle between conservatives and radicals is carried on openly in accordance with legal rules. But these rules are themselves the product of a pre-legal political agreement. Every system of law presupposes an initial political decision, whether explicit or implied, whether achieved by voting or by bargaining or by force, as to the authority entitled to make and unmake law. Behind all law there is this necessary political background. The ultimate authority of law derives from politics.

Notes

1.

|    |

The Carnegie Endowment has, for example, given the title International Legislation to a collection published under its auspices of ‘multipartite instruments of general interest’.

2.

|    |

Duguit, Traité de droit constitutionnel, i. p. 16.

3.

|    |

Krabbe, The Modern Idea of the State (Engl. transl.), p. 110.

4.

|    |

Montesquieu, Esprit des Lois, Book I. ch. iii.

5.

|    |

The phrase comes from Stammler, whose Lehre von dem richtigen Recbte (1902–7) has been translated into English under the title The Theory of Justice.

6.

|    |

Rousseau, Émile, Book IV.

7.

|    |

Marx and Engels, Works (Russian ed.), xv. p. 272.

8.

|    |

Lenin, Works (2nd Russian ed.), xv. p. 330; xii, p. 288.

9.

|    |

Representative Opinions of Mr Justice Holmes, ed. Laski, Introduction.

10.

|    |

Laud, Sermon IV, Works, i. p. 112.

11.

|    |

Zimmern, International Affairs, xvii. (January-February 1938), p. 12.

12.

|    |

‘We shall no longer ask whether the state is prior to law, or law is prior to the state. We shall regard them both as inherent functions of the common life which is inseparable from the idea of man. They will both be primordial facts: they will both have been given, as seeds or germs, coevally with man himself: they will both appear, as developed fruits, simultaneously with one another and in virtue of one another’ (Gierke, Natural Law and the Theory of Society, Engl. transl., p. 224).

13.

|    |

F. Berber, Sicherbeit und Gerechtigkeit, p. 145.

14.

|    |

Hsun-tze, quoted in Liang Chi-chao, History of Chinese Political Thought, p. 137. A perfect illustration of the confusion which results from treating law as something self-contained and self-applying may be found in a reported dictum of Mr Winston Churchill: ‘There must be the assurance that some august international tribunal shall be established which will uphold, enforce and itself obey the law’ (Manchester Guardian, 12 December 1938). If Mr Churchill had paused to ask who would establish the august tribunal, who would enforce its decisions, who would make the law and who would see that the tribunal obeyed it, the implications of this apparently simple proposition would have become apparent.

CHAPTER FOURTEEN

The Prospects of a New International Order

The end of the old order

Periods of crisis have been common in history. The characteristic feature of the crisis of the twenty years between 1919 and 1939 was the abrupt descent from the visionary hopes of the first decade to the grim despair of the second, from a utopia which took little account of the reality to a reality from which every element of utopia was rigorously excluded. The mirage of the nineteen-twenties was, as we now know, the belated reflexion of a century past beyond recall – the golden age of continuously expanding territories and markets, of a world policed by the self-assured and not too onerous British hegemony, of a coherent ‘Western’ civilization whose conflicts could be harmonized by a progressive extension of the area of common development and exploitation, of the easy assumptions that what was good for one was good for all and that what was economically right could not be morally wrong. The reality which had once given content to this utopia was already in decay before the nineteenth century had reached its end. The utopia of 1919 was hollow and without substance. It was without influence on the future because it no longer had any roots in the present.

The first and most obvious tragedy of this utopia was its ignominious collapse, and the despair which this collapse brought with it. ‘The European masses realized for the first time’, said a writer before the second world war, ‘that existence in this society is governed not by rational and sensible, but by blind, irrational and demonic forces.’1 It was no longer possible to rationalize international relations by pretending that what was good for Great Britain was also good for Yugoslavia and what was good for Germany was also good for Poland, so that international conflicts were merely the transient products of avoidable misunderstanding or curable ill-will. For more than a hundred years, the reality of conflict had been spirited out of sight by the political thinkers of Western civilization. The men of the nineteen-thirties returned shocked and bewildered to the world of nature. The brutalities which, in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, were confined to dealings between civilized and uncivilized peoples were turned by civilized peoples against one another. The relation of totalitarianism to the crisis was clearly one not of cause, but of effect. Totalitarianism was not the disease, but one of the symptoms. Wherever the crisis raged, traces of this symptom could be found.

The second tragedy of the collapse of utopia, which proceeded from the first and further intensified it, was of a subtler kind. In the latter half of the nineteenth century, when the harmony of interests was already threatened by conflicts of increasing gravity, the rationality of the world was saved by a good stiff dose of Darwinism. The reality of conflict was admitted. But since conflict ended in the victory of the stronger, and the victory of the stronger was a condition of progress, honour was saved at the expense of the unfit. After 1919 only Fascists and Nazis clung openly to this outmoded device for rationalizing and moralizing international relations. But the Western countries resorted to an equally dubious and disastrous expedient. Smitten by the bankruptcy of the harmony of interests, and shocked by its Darwinian deviation, they attempted to build up a new international morality on the foundation, not of the right of the stronger, but of the right of those in possession. Like all utopias which are institutionalized, this utopia became the tool of vested interests and was of the status quo. It is a moot point whether the politicians and publicists of the satisfied Powers, who attempted to identify international morality with security, law and order and other time-honoured slogans of privileged groups, do not bear their share of responsibility for the disaster as well as the politicians and publicists of the dissatisfied Powers, who brutally denied the validity of an international morality so constituted. Both these attempts to moralize international relations necessarily failed. We can accept neither the Darwinian doctrine, which identifies the good of the whole with the good of the fittest and contemplates without repugnance the elimination of the unfit, nor the doctrine of a natural harmony of interests which has lost such foundation in reality as it once had, and which inevitably becomes a cloak for the vested interests of the privileged. Both these doctrines have become untenable as the basis of international morality. Their breakdown has left us with no ready solution of the problem of reconciling the good of the nation with the good of the world community; and international morality is in the melting-pot.

In what direction can we look for a revival of international morality? It is, of course, possible that no such revival is in prospect and that the world is descending into one of those historical periods of retrogression and chaos in which the existing mould of society is riven asunder and from which new and familiar forms eventually emerge. If so, the experience is unlikely to be either brief or painless. Those who believe in world revolution as a short cut to utopia are singularly blind to the lessons of history; and the number of those who hold this belief appears to have diminished in recent years. There is no more reason to assume that the path lies through world revolution than to take refuge in blank despair. Our task is to explore the ruins of our international order and discover on what fresh foundations we may hope to rebuild it; and like other political problems, this problem must be considered from the standpoint both of power and of morality.

Will the nation survive as the unit of power?

Before considering the role of power in any new international order, we must first ask what will be the unit of power. The current form of international politics is due to the fact that the effective units are nation-states. The form of the future international order is closely bound up with the future of the group unit.

The French Revolution, which inaugurated the period of history now drawing to its close, raised the issue of the rights of man. Its demand for equality was a demand for equality between individuals. In the nineteenth century, this demand was transformed into a demand for equality between social groups. Marx was right in perceiving that the individual in isolation could not be the effective unit in the struggle for human rights and human equality. But he was wrong in supposing that the ultimate unit was the social class, and in discounting the cohesive and comprehensive qualities of the national unit. The great European figures of the later nineteenth century were Disraeli and Bismarck, who strove to weld together the ‘two nations’ into one through the agencies of the social service state, popular education and imperialism, refuted the taunt that ‘the worker has no country’, and paved the way for ‘national labour’, ‘national socialism’ and even ‘national communism’. Before 1914 the demand for equality was already beginning in Western Europe to pass over from the issue of equality between classes to that of equality between nations. Italian writers had described Italy as a ‘proletarian’ nation, using the term in the sense of ‘under-privileged’. Germany demanded equality in the form of her place in the sun, which must, as Bernhardi said, be ‘fought for and won against a superior force of hostile interests and powers’.2 In France, socialist and ex-socialist ministers appealed for industrial peace in the interests of national unity. Imperceptibly the struggle between classes was coming to seem, even to the workers themselves, less important than the struggle between nations. And the struggle for equality became, in accordance with the ordinary laws of political power, indistinguishable from the struggle for predominance.

This then is the basic reason for the overwhelming importance of international politics after 1919. The conflict between privileged and unprivileged, between the champions of an existing order and the revolutionaries, which was fought out in the nineteenth century within the national communities of Western Europe, was transferred by the twentieth century to the international community. The nation became, more than ever before, the supreme unit round which centre human demands for equality and human ambitions for predominance. Everywhere in Europe, national governments and one-party states made their appearance; and where party issues survived, they were thought of as something outmoded and deplorable – a blot on national unity which cried out to be erased. The inequality which threatened a world upheaval was not inequality between individuals, nor inequality between classes, but inequality between nations. ‘Just as inequality of wealth and opportunity between the classes often led to revolutions,’ said Mussolini, ‘so similar inequality between the nations is calculated, if not peaceably adjusted, to lead to explosions of a much graver character.’3 The new harmony which was required was not (as the philosophers of laissez-faire assumed) a harmony between individuals, and not (as Marx assumed when he denied the possibility of its realization) a harmony between classes, but a harmony between nations. To-day we need not make the mistake, which Marx made about the social class, of treating the nation as the ultimate group unit of human society. We need not pause to argue whether it is the best or the worst kind of unit to serve as the focus of political power. But we are bound to ask ourselves whether, and if so by what, it is likely to be superseded. Speculation on this subject falls naturally into two questions:

(a)

|   |

Are the largest and most comprehensive units of political power in the world necessarily of a territorial character?

(b)

|   |

If so, will they continue to take approximately the form of the contemporary nation-state?

The question whether the largest and most comprehensive power units must necessarily be territorial cannot receive a dogmatic answer applicable to all periods of history. At present, such units have a distinctively territorial form. It is easy to read past history as a gradual development leading up, with occasional relapses, to this consummation; and political power is probably never, even in the most primitive societies, entirely divorced from the possession of territory. Yet in many periods of history, of which the mediaeval is the most recent, power has been based ostensibly – and in part, really – on grounds other than those of territorial sovereignty. It was acceptance of the principle cuius regio eius religio which substituted the unit based on domicile for the unit based on religious allegiance, and thereby laid the foundation of the modern nation-state. In no previous period of modern history have frontiers been so rigidly demarcated, or their character as barriers so ruthlessly enforced, as to-day; and in no period, as we have already seen, has it been apparently so impossible to organize and maintain any international form of power. Modern technique, military and economic, seems to have indissolubly welded together power and territory. It is difficult for contemporary man even to imagine a world in which political power would be organized on a basis not of territory, but of race, creed or class. Yet the enduring appeal of ideologies which transcend the limits of existing political units cannot be ignored. Few things are permanent in history; and it would be rash to assume that the territorial unit of power is one of them. Its abandonment in favour of some other form of organized group power would, however, be so revolutionary that little that holds true of international politics in the present period would apply to the new dispensation. International relations would be supplanted by a new set of group relationships.

The question whether the territorial units of the future are likely to retain approximately their present form is one of more immediate practical importance. The problem of the optimum size of units – whether units of industrial or agricultural production or units of political and economic power – is one of the most puzzling and important of the present time; and the near future may well see striking developments. In the field of political power, two contrary tendencies may be observed.

In one direction, there is a clearly marked trend towards integration and the formation of ever larger political and economic units. This trend set in in the latter part of the nineteenth century, and appears to have been closely connected with the growth of large-scale capitalism and industrialism, as well as with the improvement of means of communication and of the technical instruments of power. The first world war threw this development into conspicuous relief.

Sovereignty, that is freedom to make decisions of wide historical importance [wrote Naumann in his famous book published in 1915], is now concentrated at a very few places on the globe. The day is still distant when there shall be ‘one fold, one shepherd’, but the days are past when shepherds without number, lesser or greater, drove their flocks unrestrained over the pastures of Europe. The spirit of large-scale industry and of super-national organization has seized politics…This is in conformity with centralized military technique.4

The interlude of 1918, when nationalism momentarily resumed its disintegrating role, proved – at any rate in Europe – a dangerous fiasco. The multiplication of economic units added disastrously to the problems of the postwar period. Naumann with his Mittel-Europa proved a surer prophet than Woodrow Wilson with his principle of self-determination. The victors of 1918 ‘lost the peace’ in Central Europe because they continued to pursue a principle of political and economic disintegration in an age which called for larger and larger units. The process of concentration still continued. The more autarky is regarded as the goal, the larger the units must become. The United States strengthened their hold over the American Continents. Great Britain created a ‘sterling bloc’ and laid the foundations of a closed economic system. Germany reconstituted Mittel-Europa and pressed forward into the Balkans. Soviet Russia developed its vast territories into a compact unit of industrial and agricultural production. Japan attempted the creation of a new unit of ‘Eastern Asia’ under Japanese domination. Such was the trend towards the concentration of political and economic power in the hands of six or seven highly organized units, round which lesser satellite units revolved without any appreciable independent motion of their own. On the other hand there is some evidence that, while technical, industrial and economic development within the last hundred years has dictated a progressive increase in the size of the effective political unit, there may be a size which cannot be exceeded without provoking a recrudescence of disintegrating tendencies. If any such law is at work, it is impossible to formulate it with any precision; and prolonged investigation would be necessary to throw any light on the conditions which govern the size of political and economic units. The issue is, however, perhaps likely to be more decisive than any other for the course of world history in the next few generations.

One prediction may be made with some confidence. The concept of sovereignty is likely to become in the future even more blurred and indistinct than it is at present. The term was invented after the break-up of the mediaeval system to describe the independent character of the authority claimed and exercised by states which no longer recognized even the formal overlordship of the Empire. It was never more than a convenient label; and when distinctions began to be made between political, legal and economic sovereignty or between internal and external sovereignty, it was clear that the label had ceased to perform its proper function as a distinguishing mark for a single category of phenomena. Discussion of such questions as whether the British Dominions are ‘sovereign’ Powers, or in whom ‘sovereignty’ of the mandated territories is vested, reveals the growing confusion. Such discussions are either legal arguments on the question what powers the authorities in those areas are constitutionally entitled to exercise (in which case the use of the term ‘sovereignty’ gives little help), or else arguments of pure form on the question whether it is convenient to use the label ‘sovereignty’ to describe situations which diverge to a greater or less extent from a common pattern. The concept of sovereignty becomes definitely misleading when, for instance, in a computation of the value of British colonial trade or British colonial investment, Egypt and Iraq are excluded on the ground that they are sovereign states. It is unlikely that the future units of power will take much account of formal sovereignty. There is no reason why each unit should not consist of groups of several formally sovereign states so long as the effective (but not necessarily the nominal) authority is exercised from a single centre. The effective group unit of the future will in all probability not be the unit formally recognized as such by international law. Any project of an international order which takes these formal units as its basis seems likely to prove unreal.

It may be well to add at this point that group units in some form will certainly survive as repositories of political power, whatever form these units may take. Nationalism was one of the forces by which the seemingly irreconcilable clash of interest between classes within the national community was reconciled. There is no corresponding force which can be invoked to reconcile the now seemingly irreconcilable clash of interest between nations. It is profitless to imagine a hypothetical world in which men no longer organize themselves in groups for purposes of conflict; and the conflict cannot once more be transferred to a wider and more comprehensive field. As has often been observed, the international community cannot be organized against Mars. This is merely another aspect of the dilemma with which the collapse of the spacious conditions of nineteenth-century civilization has confronted us. It seems no longer possible to create an apparent harmony of interests at the expense of somebody else. The conflict can no longer be spirited away.

Power in the new international order

Power is a necessary ingredient of every political order. Historically, every approach in the past to a world society has been the product of the ascendancy of a single Power. In the nineteenth century the British fleet not only guaranteed immunity from major wars, but policed the high seas and offered equal security to all; the London money market established a single currency standard for virtually the whole world; British commerce secured – it is true, in an imperfect and attenuated form – a widespread acceptance of the principle of free trade; and English became the lingua franca of four continents. These conditions, which were at once the product and the guarantee of British supremacy, created the illusion – and to some extent the reality – of a world society possessing interests and sympathies in common. The working hypothesis of an international order was created by a superior power. The hypothesis has been destroyed by the decline, relative or absolute, of that power. The British fleet is no longer strong enough to prevent war; the London market can enforce a single currency standard only over a limited area; free trade has wholly broken down; and if the English language retains, and has increased, its ascendancy, this is due to the fact that it is shared by Great Britain with other important countries. By what power can the international order be restored?

This question is likely to be answered by different nations in different ways. Most contemporary Englishmen are aware that the conditions which secured the overwhelming ascendancy of Great Britain in the nineteenth century no longer exist. But they sometimes console themselves with the dream that British supremacy, instead of passing altogether away, will be transmuted into the higher and more effective form of an ascendancy of the English-speaking peoples. The pax Britannica will be put into commission and become a pax Anglo-Saxonica, under which the British Dominions, standing halfway between the mother country and the United States, will be cunningly woven into a fabric of Anglo-American co-operation. This romantic idea goes back to the last years of the nineteenth century when Great Britain was already conscious of the growing burden of world supremacy, and when Cecil Rhodes had one of the first recorded visions of world empire based on an Anglo-American partnership. Oddly enough, it was an American Ambassador in London who, just before the war, gave the idea its most concrete expression. In 1913, Walter Hines Page proposed that President Wilson should visit London and conclude an Anglo-American alliance. ‘I think’, he added, ‘the world would take notice to whom it belongs and – be quiet.’5 The Washington Naval Treaty of 1922 was a more or less conscious bid by Great Britain for an equal partnership with the United States in the management of the world. The hope was reiterated again and again, with the reserves and the caution dictated by American susceptibilities, by British statesmen between the two world wars.

I have always believed [said Lord Baldwin at the Albert Hall in May 1935] that the greatest security against war in any part of the world whatever, in Europe, in the East, anywhere, would be the close collaboration of the British Empire with the United States of America. The combined powers of the navies, the potential manpower, the immediate economic power of the combined blockade, and a refusal to trade or lend money would be a sanction that no power on earth however strong dare face. It may be a hundred years before that desirable end may be attained; it may never come to pass. But sometimes we may have our dreams. I look forward to the future, and I see that union of forces for peace and justice in the world, and I cannot but think, even if men cannot advocate it openly yet, that some day and some time those who follow us may see it and know that the peace of the world is guaranteed by those who speak our tongue.6

The enormous growth of interest in Great Britain in everything relating to the United States shows what deep roots this ambition has struck in British hearts.

On the other side of the Atlantic, the picture necessarily looks rather different. Instead of an old firm, anxious to renew its strength by taking young blood into partnership, we have here a young and untried nation, reliant on its own strength, but still uncertain how far that strength will carry it. The United States did not, until the turn of the century, stake out their claim for recognition as a Great Power. But it was not long before leading Americans were beginning to see visions of world supremacy.

My dream [said Woodrow Wilson in a speech on Independence Day, 1914] is that as the years go by and the world knows more and more of America, it…will turn to America for those moral inspirations which lie at the basis of all freedom, … and that America will come into the full light of day when all shall know that she puts human rights above all other rights, and that her flag is the flag not only of America, but of humanity.7

The dream proved prophetic. In 1918 world leadership was offered, by almost unanimous consent, to the United States. The fact that it was then declined does not prove that it may not be grasped at some future time. If historical precedents count for anything, a pax Americana imposed on a divided and weakened Europe would be an easier contingency to realize than a pax Anglo-Saxonica based on an equal partnership of English-speaking peoples. But we are here in the realm of speculation, where the serious student cannot do more than canvass guesses and possibilities.

The necessary drawback about all conceptions of a world order depending on the ascendancy of a superior Power is that they ultimately involve recognition of the right of the strongest to assume world leadership. The pax Romana was the product of Roman imperialism, the pax Britannica of British imperialism. The ‘good neighbour’ policy of the United States in Latin America is not the antithesis, but the continuation and consequence of ‘Yankee imperialism’; for it is only the strongest who can both maintain their supremacy and remain ‘good neighbours’. There is no theoretical reason to refuse to other nations the right to aspire to world leadership.

Whoever really desires in his heart the victory of the pacifist conception of the world [writes Hitler in Mein Kampf] must devote himself by every means to the conquest of the world by the Germans. … The pacifist, humanitarian idea will perhaps be excellent when the man superior to all others shall first have so conquered and subjugated the world that he becomes its sole master.8

The policy of Japan, as the Chinese delegate remarked at an Assembly of the League of Nations, was to establish a pax Japonica in the Far East.9 The Englishman or the American is entitled to resist such ambitions. But he cannot resist them on universal grounds which will appeal to the German or the Japanese. The conception of a pax Germanica or a pax Japonica, i.e. of a world order dominated by Germany or Japan, was a priori no more absurd and presumptuous than the conception of a pax Britannica would have seemed in the reign of Elizabeth or of a pax Americana in the days of Washington and Madison. The only reason why it would seem absurd for Nicaragua or Lithuania to aspire to world leadership is that, according to any reasonable prognostication, these countries will never be strong enough to have the slightest hope of attaining such an ambition. To attempt to ignore power as a decisive factor in every political situation is purely utopian. It is scarcely less utopian to imagine an international order built on a coalition of states, each striving to defend and assert its own interests. The new international order can be built only on a unit of power sufficiently coherent and sufficiently strong to maintain its ascendancy without being itself compelled to take sides in the rivalries of lesser units. Whatever moral issues may be involved, there is an issue of power which cannot be expressed in terms of morality.

Morality in the new international order

If, however, it is utopian to ignore the element of power, it is an unreal kind of realism which ignores the element of morality in any world order. Just as within the state every government, though it needs power as a basis of its authority, also needs the moral basis of the consent of the governed, so an international order cannot be based on power alone, for the simple reason that mankind will in the long run always revolt against naked power. Any international order presupposes a substantial measure of general consent. We shall, indeed, condemn ourselves to disappointment if we exaggerate the role which morality is likely to play. The fatal dualism of politics will always keep considerations of morality entangled with considerations of power. We shall never arrive at a political order in which the grievances of the weak and the few receive the same prompt attention as the grievances of the strong and the many. Power goes far to create the morality convenient to itself, and coercion is a fruitful source of consent. But when all these reserves have been made, it remains true that a new international order and a new international harmony can be built up only on the basis of an ascendancy which is generally accepted as tolerant and unoppressive or, at any rate, as preferable to any practicable alternative. To create these conditions is the moral task of the ascendant Power or Powers. The most effective moral argument which could be used in favour of a British or American, rather than a German or Japanese, hegemony of the world was that Great Britain and the United States, profiting by a long tradition and by some hard lessons in the past, have on the whole learned more successfully than Germany and Japan the capital importance of this task. Belief in the desirability of seeking the consent of the governed by methods other than those of coercion has in fact played a larger part in the British and American than in the German or Japanese administration of subject territories. Belief in the uses of conciliation even in dealing with those against whom it would have been easy to use force has in the past played a larger part in British and American than in German and Japanese foreign policy. That any moral superiority which this may betoken is mainly the product of long and secure enjoyment of superior power does not alter the fact, though this consideration may well affect the appeal of the argument to Germans and Japanese and expose British and Americans to the charge of self-righteousness when they invoke it.

It is, however, useless to discuss these problems of power and morality in a nineteenth-century setting, as if some fortunate turn of the wheel could restore the old conditions and allow a reconstitution of the international order on something like the old lines. The real international crisis of the modern world is the final and irrevocable breakdown of the conditions which made the nineteenth-century order possible. The old order cannot be restored, and a drastic change of outlook is unavoidable. Those who seek international conciliation may study with advantage the conditions which have made the process of conciliation between social classes in some degree successful. Essential conditions of that process were that the reality of the conflict should be frankly recognized, and not dismissed as an illusion in the minds of wicked agitators; that the easy hypothesis of a natural harmony of interests, which a modicum of good will and common sense would suffice to maintain, should be consigned to oblivion; that what was morally desirable should not be identified with what was economically advantageous; and that economic interests should, if necessary, be sacrificed in order to resolve the conflict by the mitigation of inequalities. None of these conditions has yet been realized in the international community. Responsible British and American statesmen still commonly speak as if there were a natural harmony of interests between the nations of the world which requires only good will and common sense for its maintenance, and which is being wilfully disturbed by wicked dictators. British and American economists still commonly assume that what is economically good for Great Britain or the United States is economically good for other countries and therefore morally desirable. Few people are yet willing to recognize that the conflict between classes cannot be resolved without real sacrifices, involving in all probability a substantial reduction of consumption by privileged groups and in privileged countries. There may be other obstacles to the establishment of a new international order. But failure to recognize the fundamental character of the conflict, and the radical nature of the measures necessary to meet it, is certainly one of them.

Ultimately the best hope of progress towards international conciliation seems to lie along the path of economic reconstruction. Within the national community, necessity has carried us far towards the abandonment of economic advantage as the test of what is desirable. In nearly every country (and not least in the United States), large capital investments have been made in recent years, not for the economic purpose of earning profits, but for the social purpose of creating employment. For some time the prejudice of orthodox economists against this policy was strong enough to restrict it to half measures. In Soviet Russia, such prejudice was nonexistent from the outset. In the other totalitarian states, it rapidly disappeared. But elsewhere rearmament and war provided the first substantial cure for unemployment. The lesson will not be overlooked. A repetition of the crisis of 1930–33 will not be tolerated anywhere, for the simple reason that workers have learned that unemployment can be cured by a gigantic programme of economically unremunerative expenditure on armaments; and such expenditure would be equally effective from the standpoint of employment if it were devoted to some other economically unremunerative purpose such as the provision of free housing, free motor cars or free clothing. In the meanwhile we are moving rapidly everywhere towards the abolition or restriction of industrial profits. In the totalitarian countries this has now been virtually accomplished. In Great Britain, the assumption has long been made that to earn more than a limited rate of profit on the provision of essential public services is immoral. This assumption has now been extended to the armaments industry. Its extension to other industries is only a matter of time, and will be hastened by any crisis. The rearmament crisis of 1939, even if it had passed without war, would have produced everywhere changes in the social and industrial structure less revolutionary only than those produced by war itself. And the essence of this revolution is the abandonment of economic advantage as the test of policy. Employment has become more important than profit, social stability than increased consumption, equitable distribution than maximum production.

Internationally, this revolution complicates some problems and may help to solve others. So long as power wholly dominates international relations, the subordination of every other advantage to military necessity intensifies the crisis, and gives a foretaste of the totalitarian character of war itself. But once the issue of power is settled, and morality resumes its role, the situation is not without hope. Internationally as nationally, we cannot return to the pre-1939 world any more than we could return to the pre-war world in 1919. Frank acceptance of the subordination of economic advantage to social ends, and the recognition that what is economically good is not always morally good, must be extended from the national to the international sphere. The increasing elimination of the profit motive from the national economy should facilitate at any rate its partial elimination from foreign policy. After 1918, both the British and United States Governments granted to certain distressed countries ‘relief credits’, from which no economic return was ever seriously expected. Foreign loans for the purpose of stimulating production in export trades have been a familiar feature of postwar policy in many countries. Later extensions of this policy were dictated mainly by military considerations. But if the power crisis can be overcome, there can be no reason why it should not be extended for other purposes. The more we subsidize unproductive industries for political reasons, the more the provision of a rational employment supplants maximum profit as an aim of economic policy, the more we recognize the need of sacrificing economic advantage for social ends, the less difficult will it seem to realize that these social ends cannot be limited by a national frontier, and that British policy may have to take into account the welfare of Lille or Du sseldorf or Lodz as well as the welfare of Oldham or Jarrow. The broadening of our view of national policy should help to broaden our view of international policy; and as has been said in an earlier chapter,* it is by no means certain that a direct appeal to the motive of sacrifice would always fail.

This, too, is a utopia. But it stands more directly in the line of recent advance than visions of a world federation or blueprints of a more perfect League of Nations. Those elegant superstructures must wait until some progress has been made in digging the foundations.

Notes

*

|    |

See p. 152.

1.

|    |

P. Drucker, The End of Economic Man, p. 56.

2.

|    |

Bernhardi, Germany and the Next War (Engl. transl.), p. 81.

3.

|    |

The Times, 21 April 1939.

4.

|    |

F. Naumann, Central Europe (Engl. transl.), pp. 4–5.

5.

|    |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson: Life and Letters, v. p. 31.

6.

|    |

The Times, 28 May 1935.

7.

|    |

R. S. Baker, Woodrow Wilson and World Settlement, i. p. 18.

8.

|    |

Hitler, Mein Kampf, p. 315.

9.

|    |

League of Nations: Eighteenth Assembly, p. 49.